<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ThML PUBLIC 
    "-//CCEL/DTD Theological Markup Language//EN"
    "http://www.ccel.org/dtd/ThML10.dtd">
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml"
    href="http://www.ccel.org/ss/thml.html.xsl" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl"
    href="http://www.ccel.org/ss/thml.html.xsl" ?>
-->
    
<!-- Copyright Christian Classics Ethereal Library -->
<ThML>
<ThML.head>

<generalInfo>
<description><i>On the Incarnation of the Word</i> is a classic 
work of Orthodox theology written by noted bishop of 
Alexandria, St. Athanasius. In this apologetic treatise, 
St. Athanasius defends the incarnation of Christ against 
the derision of 4th century non-believers. St Athanasius 
explains why God chose to approach his fallen people in 
human form. He states, "The death of all was consummated 
in the Lord's body; yet, because the Word was in it, death and 
corruption were in the same act utterly abolished." St. Athanasius 
resolves the paradox of the Incarnate by relying heavily on both 
Scripture and the teachings of the early Church. St. Athanasius also 
answers several objections to his account, many of which are still 
raised against Christians today by those outside the Church. <i>On the 
Incarnation of the Word</i> was highly recommended by modern writer and 
Christian apologist, C.S. Lewis, who suggested that contemporary 
Christian audiences could benefit from reading more ancient classics. 
Indeed, though St. Athanasius wrote this text in the 4th century, his 
style is easy to follow and his concepts are of irreplaceable worth. 
<br /><br />Emmalon Davis<br />CCEL Staff Writer </description>
<firstPublished />
<pubHistory />
<comments /></generalInfo>

<printSourceInfo>
<published />
</printSourceInfo>

<electronicEdInfo>
<publisherID>ccel</publisherID>
<authorID>athanasius</authorID>
<bookID>incarnation</bookID>
<workID>incarnation</workID>
<bkgID>athanasius-incarnation</bkgID>
<version>1.0</version>
<series /><editorialComments />
<revisionHistory />
<status />

<DC>
<DC.Title>On the Incarnation of the Word</DC.Title>
<DC.Title sub="short" />
<DC.Creator sub="Author" scheme="short-form">St. Athanasius</DC.Creator>
<DC.Creator sub="Author" scheme="file-as">Athanasius, St. Archbishop of Alexandria (c.296-c.373)</DC.Creator>
<DC.Creator sub="Author" scheme="ccel">athanasius</DC.Creator>
<DC.Creator scheme="ccel" sub="Translator" />
<DC.Creator scheme="file-as" sub="Translator" />
<DC.Creator scheme="short-form" sub="Translator" />
<DC.Subject scheme="ccel">All; Theology; Early Church</DC.Subject>
<DC.Subject scheme="LCCN">BT220.A75</DC.Subject>
<DC.Subject scheme="lcsh1">Doctrinal theology</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="lcsh2">Christology</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Description />
<DC.Publisher>Christian Classics Ethereal Library, Grand Rapids, MI</DC.Publisher>
<DC.Date sub="Created" scheme="ISO8601">2004-08-25</DC.Date>
<DC.Contributor sub="Transcriber" />
<DC.Contributor sub="Markup" />
<DC.Source sub="ElectronicEdition" />
<DC.Source sub="ElectronicEdition" scheme="URL" />
<DC.Language scheme="ISO639-3">eng</DC.Language>
<DC.Rights>Public Domain</DC.Rights>
<DC.Type>Text.Monograph</DC.Type>
<DC.Identifier scheme="URL">/ccel/athanasius/incarnation.html</DC.Identifier>
<DC.Format scheme="IMT">text/xml</DC.Format>
</DC>
</electronicEdInfo>





<style type="text/css">
</style>

<style type="text/xcss">
</style>


</ThML.head>


<ThML.body>

<div1 title="Title Page" progress="0.27%" prev="toc" next="ii" id="i">
<h1 id="i-p0.1">On the Incarnation</h1>
<h3 id="i-p0.2">by St. Athanasius</h3>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 1. Creation and the Fall" progress="0.30%" prev="i" next="iii" id="ii">
<h2 id="ii-p0.1">Chapter 1</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="ii-p1"><i>Creation and the Fall</i></p>

<p id="ii-p2"><b>(1) </b>In our former book<note n="1" id="ii-p2.1">i.e. the <i>Contra Gentes</i>.</note> 
we dealt fully enough with a few of the chief points about the 
heathen worship of idols, and how those false fears originally arose. We also, 
by God's grace, briefly indicated that the Word of the Father is Himself divine, 
that all things that are owe their being to His will and power, and that it is 
through Him that the Father gives order to creation, by Him that all things are 
moved, and through Him that they receive their being. Now, Macarius, true lover 
of Christ, we must take a step further in the faith of our holy religion, and 
consider also the Word's becoming Man and His divine Appearing in our midst. 
That mystery the Jews traduce, the Greeks deride, but we adore; and your own 
love and devotion to the Word also will be the greater, because in His Manhood 
He seems so little worth. For it is a fact that the more unbelievers pour scorn 
on Him, so much the more does He make His Godhead evident. The things which 
they, as men, rule out as impossible, He plainly shows to be possible; that 
which they deride as unfitting, His goodness makes most fit; and things which 
these wiseacres laugh at as "human" He by His inherent might declares divine. 
Thus by what seems His utter poverty and weakness on the cross He overturns the 
pomp and parade of idols, and quietly and hiddenly wins over the mockers and 
unbelievers to recognize Him as God.</p>
<p id="ii-p3">Now in dealing with these matters it is necessary first to recall what has 
already been said. You must understand why it is that the Word of the Father, so 
great and so high, has been made manifest in bodily form. He has not assumed a 
body as proper to His own nature, far from it, for as the Word He is without 
body. He has been manifested in a human body for this reason only, out of the 
love and goodness of His Father, for the salvation of us men. We will begin, 
then, with the creation of the world and with God its Maker, for the first fact 
that you must grasp is this: <i>the renewal of creation has been 
wrought by the Self-same Word Who made it in the beginning</i>. There is thus no inconsistency between creation and salvation for the One Father has 
employed the same Agent for both works, effecting the salvation of the world 
through the 
same Word Who made it in the beginning.</p>
<p id="ii-p4"><b>(2)</b> In regard to the making of the universe and the 
creation of all things there have been various opinions, and each person has 
propounded the theory that suited his own taste. For instance, some say that all 
things are self-originated and, so to speak, haphazard. The Epicureans are among 
these; they deny that there is any Mind behind the universe at all. This view is 
contrary to all the facts of experience, their own existence included. For if 
all things had come into being in this automatic fashion, instead of being the 
outcome of Mind, though they existed, they would all be uniform and without 
distinction. In the universe everything would be sun or moon or whatever it was, 
and in the human body the whole would be hand or eye or foot. But in point of 
fact the sun and the moon and the earth are all different things, and even 
within the human body there are different members, such as foot and hand and 
head. This distinctness of things argues not a spontaneous generation but a 
prevenient Cause; and from that Cause we can apprehend God, the Designer and 
Maker of all.</p>
<p id="ii-p5">Others take the view expressed by Plato, that giant among the Greeks. He said 
that God had made all things out of pre-existent and uncreated matter, just as 
the carpenter makes things only out of wood that already exists. But those who 
hold this view do not realize that to deny that God is Himself the Cause of 
matter is to impute limitation to Him, just as it is undoubtedly a limitation on 
the part of the carpenter that he can make nothing unless he has the wood. How 
could God be called Maker and Artificer if His ability to make depended on some 
other cause, namely on matter itself? If He only worked up existing matter and 
did not Himself bring matter into being, He would be not the Creator but only a 
craftsman.</p>
<p id="ii-p6">Then, again, there is the theory of the Gnostics, who have invented for 
themselves an Artificer of all things other than the Father of our Lord Jesus 
Christ. These simply shut their eyes to the obvious meaning of Scripture. For 
instance, the Lord, having reminded the Jews of the statement in Genesis, "He Who created them in the beginning made them male 
and female . . . ," and having shown that for that reason a man should leave 
his parents and cleave to his wife, goes on to say with reference to the 
Creator, "What therefore God has joined together, let no man put asunder."<note n="2" id="ii-p6.1"><scripRef passage="Matthew 19:4-6" id="ii-p6.2" parsed="|Matt|19|4|19|6" osisRef="Bible:Matt.19.4-Matt.19.6">Matt. xix. 4–6</scripRef></note> 
How 
can they get a creation independent of the Father out of that? And, again, St. 
John, speaking all inclusively, says, 
"All things became by Him and without Him came nothing 
into being."<note n="3" id="ii-p6.3"><scripRef passage="John 1:3" id="ii-p6.4" parsed="|John|1|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.1.3">John i. 3</scripRef></note> 
How then could the Artificer be someone different, other than the Father of Christ?</p>
<p id="ii-p7"><b>(3)</b> Such are the notions which men put forward. But the 
impiety of their foolish talk is plainly declared by the divine teaching of the 
Christian faith. From it we know that, because there is Mind behind the 
universe, it did not originate itself; because God is infinite, not finite, it 
was not made from pre-existent matter, but out of nothing and out of 
non-existence absolute and utter God brought it into being through the Word. He 
says as much in Genesis: 

"In the beginning God created the heavens and the 
earth;<note n="4" id="ii-p7.1"><scripRef passage="Genesis 1:1" id="ii-p7.2" parsed="|Gen|1|1|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.1.1">Gen.  i. 1</scripRef></note> 
and again through that most helpful book <i>The Shepherd</i>, 
"Believe thou first and foremost that there is One God 
Who created and arranged all things and brought them out of non-existence into 
being."<note n="5" id="ii-p7.3"><i>The Shepherd of Hermas</i>, Book II. I</note> 
Paul also indicates the same thing when he says, 
"By faith we understand that the worlds were framed by 
the Word of God, so that the things which we see now did not come into being 
out of things which had previously appeared."<note n="6" id="ii-p7.4"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 11:3" id="ii-p7.5" parsed="|Heb|11|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.11.3">Heb. xi. 3</scripRef></note> 
For God is good—or rather, of all goodness He is Fountainhead, and it is impossible 
for one who is good to be mean or grudging about anything. Grudging existence to 
none therefore, He made all things out of nothing through His own Word, our Lord 
Jesus Christ and of all these His earthly creatures He reserved especial mercy 
for the race of men. Upon them, therefore, upon men who, as animals, were 
essentially impermanent, He bestowed a grace which other creatures 
lacked—namely the impress of His own Image, a share in the reasonable being of 
the very Word Himself, so that, reflecting Him and themselves becoming 
reasonable and expressing the Mind of God even as He does, though in limited 
degree they might continue for ever in the blessed and only true life of the 
saints in paradise. But since the will of man could turn either way, God secured 
this grace that He had given by making it conditional from the first upon two 
things—namely, a law and a place. He set them in His own paradise, and laid 
upon them a single prohibition. If they guarded the grace and retained the 
loveliness of their original innocence, then the life of paradise should be 
theirs, without sorrow, pain or care, and after it the assurance of immortality 
in heaven. But if they went astray and became vile, throwing away their 
birthright of beauty, then they would come under the natural law of death and 
live no longer in paradise, but, dying outside of it, continue in death and in 
corruption. This is what Holy Scripture tells us, proclaiming the command of God, 
"Of every tree that is in the garden thou shalt surely 
eat, but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil ye shall not eat, but 
in the day that ye do eat, ye shall surely die."<note n="7" id="ii-p7.6"><scripRef passage="Genesis 2:16" id="ii-p7.7" parsed="|Gen|2|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.2.16">Gen.  ii. 16 f.</scripRef></note> 
<i>"Ye shall surely die"</i>—not just die only, but remain in the state of death 
and of corruption.</p>
<p id="ii-p8"><b>(4)</b> You may be wondering why we are discussing the 
origin of men when we set out to talk about the Word's becoming Man. The former 
subject is relevant to the latter for this reason: it was our sorry case that 
caused the Word to come down, our transgression that called out His love for us, 
so that He made haste to help us and to appear among us. It is we who were the 
cause of His taking human form, and for our salvation that in His great love He 
was both born and manifested in a human body. For God had made man thus (that 
is, as an embodied spirit), and had willed that he should remain in 
incorruption. But men, having turned from the contemplation of God to evil of 
their own devising, had come inevitably under the law of death. Instead of 
remaining in the state in which God had created them, they were in process of 
becoming corrupted entirely, and death had them completely under its dominion. 
For the 
transgression of the commandment was making them turn back again 
according to their nature; and as they had at the beginning come into being out 
of non-existence, so were they now on the way to returning, through corruption, 
to non-existence again. The presence and love of the Word had called them into 
being; inevitably, therefore when they lost the knowledge of God, they lost 
existence with it; for it is God alone Who exists, evil is non-being, the 
negation and antithesis of good. By nature, of course, man is mortal, since he 
was made from nothing; but he bears also the Likeness of Him Who is, and if he 
preserves that Likeness through constant contemplation, then his nature is 
deprived of its power and he remains incorrupt. So is it affirmed in Wisdom: 
"The keeping of His laws is the assurance of 
incorruption."<note n="8" id="ii-p8.1"><scripRef passage="Wisdom 6:18 " id="ii-p8.2" parsed="|Wis|6|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Wis.6.18">Wisdom vi. 18</scripRef></note> 
And being incorrupt, he would be henceforth as God, as Holy Scripture says, 
"I have said, Ye are gods and sons of the Highest all 
of you: but ye die as men and fall as one of the princes."<note n="9" id="ii-p8.3"><scripRef passage="Psalm 82:6" id="ii-p8.4" parsed="|Ps|82|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.82.6">Psalm  lxxxii. 6 f.</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="ii-p9"><b>(5)</b> This, then, was the plight of men. God had not only 
made them out of nothing, but had also graciously bestowed on them His own life 
by the grace of the Word. Then, turning from eternal things to things 
corruptible, by counsel of the devil, they had become the cause of their own 
corruption in death; for, as I said before, though they were by nature subject 
to corruption, the grace of their union with the Word made them capable of 
escaping from the natural law, provided that they retained the beauty of 
innocence with which they were created. That is to say, the presence of the Word 
with them shielded them even from natural corruption, as also Wisdom says: 
"God created man for incorruption and as an image of 
His own eternity; but by envy of the devil death entered into the world."<note n="10" id="ii-p9.1"><scripRef passage="Wisdom 2:23" id="ii-p9.2" parsed="|Wis|2|23|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Wis.2.23">Wisdom ii. 23 f.</scripRef></note> 
When this happened, men began to die, and corruption ran riot among them and held 
sway over them to an even more than natural degree, because it was the penalty 
of which God had forewarned them for transgressing the commandment. Indeed, they 
had in their sinning surpassed all limits; for, having invented wickedness in 
the beginning and so involved themselves in death and corruption, they had gone 
on gradually from bad to worse, not stopping at any one kind of evil, but 
continually, as with insatiable appetite, devising new kinds of sins. Adulteries 
and thefts were everywhere, murder and raping filled the earth, law was 
disregarded in corruption and injustice, all kinds of iniquities were 
perpetrated by all, both singly and in common. Cities were warring with cities, 
nations were rising against nations, and the whole earth was rent with factions 
and battles, while each strove to outdo the other in wickedness. Even crimes 
contrary to nature were not unknown, but as the martyr-apostle of Christ says: 
"Their women changed the natural use into that which 
is against nature; and the men also, leaving the natural use of the woman, 
flamed out in lust towards each other, perpetrating shameless acts with their 
own sex, and receiving in their own persons the due recompense of their 
pervertedness."<note n="11" id="ii-p9.3"><scripRef passage="Romans 1:26" id="ii-p9.4" parsed="|Rom|1|26|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.1.26">Rom.   i. 26 f.</scripRef></note></p>


</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 2. The Divine Dilemma and Its Solution in the Incarnation" progress="9.43%" prev="ii" next="iv" id="iii">

<h2 id="iii-p0.1">Chapter 2</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="iii-p1"><i>The Divine Dilemma 
and its Solution in the Incarnation</i></p>

<p id="iii-p2"><b>(6)</b> We saw in the last chapter that, because death and 
corruption were gaining ever firmer hold on them, the human race was in process 
of destruction. Man, who was created in God's image and in his possession of 
reason reflected the very Word Himself, was disappearing, and the work of God 
was being undone. The law of death, which followed from the Transgression, 
prevailed upon us, and from it there was no escape. The thing that was happening 
was in truth both monstrous and unfitting. It would, of course, have been 
unthinkable that God should go back upon His word and that man, having 
transgressed, should not die; but it was equally monstrous that beings which 
once had shared the nature of the Word should perish and turn back again into 
non-existence through corruption. It was unworthy of the goodness of God that 
creatures made by Him should be brought to nothing through the deceit wrought 
upon man by the devil; and it was supremely unfitting that the work of God in 
mankind should disappear, either through their own negligence or through the 
deceit of evil spirits. As, then, the creatures whom He had created reasonable, 
like the Word, were in fact perishing, and such noble works were on the road to 
ruin, what then was God, being Good, to do? Was He to let corruption and death 
have their way with them? In that case, what was the use of having made them in 
the beginning? Surely it would have been better never to have been created at 
all than, having been created, to be neglected and perish; and, besides that, 
such indifference to the ruin of His own work before His very eyes would argue 
not goodness in God but limitation, and that far more than if He had never 
created men at all. It was impossible, therefore, that God should leave man to 
be carried off by corruption, because it would be unfitting and unworthy of 
Himself.</p>
<p id="iii-p3"><b>(7)</b> Yet, true though this is, it is not the whole 
matter. As we have already 
noted, it was unthinkable that God, the Father of 
Truth, should go back upon His word regarding death in order to ensure our 
continued existence. He could not falsify Himself; what, then, was God to do? 
Was He to demand repentance from men for their transgression? You might say that 
that was worthy of God, and argue further that, as through the Transgression 
they became subject to corruption, so through repentance they might return to 
incorruption again. But repentance would not guard the Divine consistency, for, 
if death did not hold dominion over men, God would still remain untrue. Nor does 
repentance recall men from what is according to their nature; all that it does 
is to make them cease from sinning. Had it been a case of a trespass only, and 
not of a subsequent corruption, repentance would have been well enough; but when 
once transgression had begun men came under the power of the corruption proper 
to their nature and were bereft of the grace which belonged to them as creatures 
in the Image of God. No, repentance could not meet the case. What—or rather Who 
was it that was needed for such grace and such recall as we required? Who, save 
the Word of God Himself, Who also in the beginning had made all things out of 
nothing? His part it was, and His alone, both to bring again the corruptible to 
incorruption and to maintain for the Father His consistency of character with 
all. For He alone, being Word of the Father and above all, was in consequence 
both able to recreate all, and worthy to suffer on behalf of all and to be an 
ambassador for all with the Father.</p>
<p id="iii-p4"><b>(8)</b> For this purpose, then, the incorporeal and 
incorruptible and immaterial Word of God entered our world. In one sense, 
indeed, He was not far from it before, for no part of creation had ever been 
without Him Who, while ever abiding in union with the Father, yet fills all 
things that are. But now He entered the world in a new way, stooping to our 
level in His love and Self-revealing to us. He saw the reasonable race, the race 
of men that, like Himself, expressed the Father's Mind, wasting out of 
existence, and death reigning over all in corruption. He saw that corruption 
held us all the closer, because it was the penalty for the Transgression; He 
saw, too, how unthinkable it would be for the law to be repealed before it was 
fulfilled. He saw how unseemly it was that the very things of which He Himself 
was the Artificer should be disappearing. He saw how the surpassing wickedness 
of men was mounting up against them; He saw also their universal liability to 
death. All this He saw and, pitying our race, moved with compassion for our 
limitation, unable to endure that death should have the mastery, rather than 
that His creatures should perish and the work of His Father for us men come to 
nought, He took to Himself a body, a human body even as our own. Nor did He will 
merely to become embodied or merely to appear; had that been so, He could have 
revealed His divine majesty in some other and better way. No, He took our body, 
and not only so, but He took it directly from a spotless, stainless virgin, 
without the agency of human father—a pure body, untainted by intercourse with 
man. He, the Mighty One, the Artificer of all, Himself prepared this body in the 
virgin as a temple for Himself, and took it for His very own, as the instrument 
through which He was known and in which He dwelt. Thus, taking a body like our 
own, because all our bodies were liable to the corruption of death, He 
surrendered His body to 
death instead of all, and offered it to the Father. This 
He did out of sheer love for us, so that in His death all might die, and the law 
of death thereby be abolished because, having fulfilled in His body that for 
which it was appointed, it was thereafter voided of its power for men. This He 
did that He might turn again to incorruption men who had turned back to 
corruption, and make them alive through death by the appropriation of His body 
and by the grace of His resurrection. Thus He would make death to disappear from 
them as utterly as straw from fire.</p>
<p id="iii-p5"><b>(9)</b> The Word perceived that corruption could not be got 
rid of otherwise than through death; yet He Himself, as the Word, being immortal 
and the Father's Son, was such as could not die. For this reason, therefore, He 
assumed a body capable of death, in order that it, through belonging to the Word 
Who is above all, might become in dying a sufficient exchange for all, and, 
itself remaining incorruptible through His indwelling, might thereafter put an 
end to corruption for all others as well, by the grace of the resurrection. It 
was by surrendering to death the body which He had taken, as an offering and 
sacrifice free from every stain, that He forthwith abolished death for His human 
brethren by the offering of the equivalent. For naturally, since the Word of God 
was above all, when He offered His own temple and bodily instrument as a 
substitute for the life of all, He fulfilled in death all that was required. 
Naturally also, through this union of the immortal Son of God with our human 
nature, all men were clothed with incorruption in the promise of the 
resurrection. For the solidarity of mankind is such that, by virtue of the 
Word's indwelling in a single human body, the corruption which goes with death 
has lost its power over all. You know how it is when some great king enters a 
large city and dwells in one of its houses; because of his dwelling in that 
single house, the whole city is honored, and enemies and robbers cease to molest 
it. Even so is it with the King of all; He has come into our country and dwelt 
in one body amidst the many, and in consequence the designs of the enemy against 
mankind have been foiled and the corruption of death, which formerly held them 
in its power, has simply ceased to be. For the human race would have perished 
utterly had not the Lord and Savior of all, the Son of God, come among us to put 
an end to death.</p>
<p id="iii-p6"><b>(10)</b> This great work was, indeed, supremely worthy of 
the goodness of God. A king who has founded a city, so far from neglecting it 
when through the carelessness of the inhabitants it is attacked by robbers, 
avenges it and saves it from destruction, having regard rather to his own honor 
than to the people's neglect. Much more, then, the Word of the All-good Father 
was not unmindful of the human race that He had called to be; but rather, by the 
offering of His own body He abolished the death which they had incurred, and 
corrected their neglect by His own teaching. Thus by His own power He restored 
the whole nature of man. The Savior's own inspired disciples assure us of this. 
We read in one place: "For the love of Christ constraineth us, because we 
thus judge that, if One died on behalf of all, then all died, and He died for 
all that we should no longer live unto ourselves, but unto Him who died 
and 
rose again from the dead, even our Lord Jesus Christ."<note n="12" id="iii-p6.1"><scripRef passage="2 Corinthians 5:14" id="iii-p6.2" parsed="|2Cor|5|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.5.14">2 Cor.  v. 14 f.</scripRef></note> 
And again another says: 
"But we behold Him Who hath been made a little lower than the 
angels, even Jesus, because of the suffering of death crowned with glory and 
honor, that by the grace of God He should taste of death on behalf of every man." 
The same writer goes on to point out why it was necessary for 
God the Word and none other to become Man: 
"For it became Him, for Whom are all things and through 
Whom are all things, in bringing many sons unto glory, to make the Author of 
their salvation perfect through suffering."<note n="13" id="iii-p6.3"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 2:9" id="iii-p6.4" parsed="|Heb|2|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.2.9">Heb. ii. 9 ff.</scripRef></note>  

He means that the rescue of mankind from corruption was the proper 
part only of Him Who made them in the beginning. He points out also that the 
Word assumed a human body, expressly in order that He might offer it in 
sacrifice for other like bodies: 
"Since then the children are sharers in flesh and 
blood, He also Himself assumed the same, in order that through death He might 
bring to nought Him that hath the power of death, that is to say, the Devil, 
and might rescue those who all their lives were enslaved by the fear of 
death."<note n="14" id="iii-p6.5"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 2:14" id="iii-p6.6" parsed="|Heb|2|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.2.14">Heb. ii. 14 f.</scripRef></note> 
For by the sacrifice of His own body He did two things: He put an 
end to the law of death which barred our way; and He made a new beginning of 
life for us, by giving us the hope of resurrection. By man death has gained its 
power over men; by the Word made Man death has been destroyed and life raised up 
anew. That is what Paul says, that true servant of Christ: 
"For since by man came death, by man came also the 
resurrection of the dead. Just as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all 
be made alive,"<note n="15" id="iii-p6.7"><scripRef passage="1 Corinthians 15:21" id="iii-p6.8" parsed="|1Cor|15|21|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.15.21">1 Cor. xv. 21 f.</scripRef></note> 
and so forth. Now, therefore, when we die we no longer do so as men 
condemned to death, but as those who are even now in process of rising we await 
the general resurrection of all, "which in its own times He shall 
show,"<note n="16" id="iii-p6.9"><scripRef passage="1 Timothy 6:15" id="iii-p6.10" parsed="|1Tim|6|15|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Tim.6.15">1 Tim. vi. 15</scripRef></note> 
even God Who wrought it and bestowed it on us.</p>
<p id="iii-p7">This, then, is the first cause of the Savior's becoming Man. There are, 
however, other things which show how wholly fitting is His blessed presence in 
our midst; and these we must now go on to consider.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 3. The Divine Dilemma and Its Solution in the Incarnation—Continued" progress="17.87%" prev="iii" next="v" id="iv">

<h2 id="iv-p0.1">Chapter 3</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="iv-p1"><i>The Divine Dilemma and its Solution in the Incarnation — continued</i></p>

<p id="iv-p2"><b>(11)</b> When God the Almighty was making mankind through 
His own Word, He perceived that they, owing to the limitation of their nature, 
could not of themselves have any knowledge of their Artificer, the Incorporeal 
and Uncreated. He took pity on them, therefore, and did not leave them destitute 
of the knowledge of Himself, lest their very existence should prove purposeless. 
For of what use is existence to the creature if it cannot know its Maker? How 
could men be reasonable beings if they had no knowledge of the Word and Reason 
of the Father, through Whom they had received their being? They would be no 
better than the beasts, had they no knowledge save of earthly things; and why 
should God have made them at all, if He had not intended them to know Him? But, 
in fact, the good God has given them a share in His own Image, that is, in our 
Lord Jesus Christ, and has made even themselves after the same Image and 
Likeness. Why? Simply in order that through this gift of Godlikeness in 
themselves they may be able to perceive the Image Absolute, that is the Word 
Himself, and through Him to apprehend the Father; which knowledge of their Maker 
is for men the only really happy and blessed life.</p>
<p id="iv-p3">But, as we have already seen, men, foolish as they are, thought little of the 
grace they had received, and turned away from God. They defiled their own soul 
so completely that they not only lost their apprehension of God, but invented 
for themselves other gods of various kinds. They fashioned idols for themselves 
in place of the truth and reverenced things that are not, rather than God Who 
is, as St. Paul says, "worshipping the creature rather than the 
Creator."<note n="17" id="iv-p3.1"><scripRef passage="Romans 1:25" id="iv-p3.2" parsed="|Rom|1|25|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.1.25">Rom. i. 25</scripRef></note> 
Moreover, and much worse, they transferred the honor which is due to God to 
material objects such as wood and stone, and also to man; and further 
even than 
that they went, as we said in our former book. Indeed, so impious were they that 
they worshipped evil spirits as gods in satisfaction of their lusts. They 
sacrificed brute beasts and immolated men, as the just due of these deities, 
thereby bringing themselves more and more under their insane control. Magic arts 
also were taught among them, oracles in sundry places led men astray, and the 
cause of everything in human life was traced to the stars as though nothing 
existed but that which could be seen. In a word, impiety and lawlessness were 
everywhere, and neither God nor His Word was known. Yet He had not hidden 
Himself from the sight of men nor given the knowledge of Himself in one way 
only; but rather He had unfolded it in many forms and by many ways.</p>
<p id="iv-p4"><b>(12)</b> God knew the limitation of mankind, you see; and 
though the grace of being made in His Image was sufficient to give them 
knowledge of the Word and through Him of the Father, as a safeguard against 
their neglect of this grace, He provided the works of creation also as means by 
which the Maker might be known. Nor was this all. Man's neglect of the 
indwelling grace tends ever to increase; and against this further frailty also 
God made provision by giving them a law, and by sending prophets, men whom they 
knew. Thus, if they were tardy in looking up to heaven, they might still gain 
knowledge of their Maker from those close at hand; for men can learn directly 
about higher things from other men. Three ways thus lay open to them, by which 
they might obtain the knowledge of God. They could look up into the immensity of 
heaven, and by pondering the harmony of creation come to know its Ruler, the 
Word of the Father, Whose all-ruling providence makes known the Father to all. 
Or, if this was beyond them, they could converse with holy men, and through them 
learn to know God, the Artificer of all things, the Father of Christ, and to 
recognize the worship of idols as the negation of the truth and full of all 
impiety. Or else, in the third place, they could cease from lukewarmness and 
lead a good life merely by knowing the law. For the law was not given only for 
the Jews, nor was it solely for their sake that God sent the prophets, though it 
was to the Jews that they were sent and by the Jews that they were persecuted. 
The law and the prophets were a sacred school of the knowledge of God and the 
conduct of the spiritual life for the whole world.</p>
<p id="iv-p5">So great, indeed, were the goodness and the love of God. Yet men, bowed down 
by the pleasures of the moment and by the frauds and illusions of the evil 
spirits, did not lift up their heads towards the truth. So burdened were they 
with their wickednesses that they seemed rather to be brute beasts than 
reasonable men, reflecting the very Likeness of the Word.</p>
<p id="iv-p6"><b>(13)</b> What was God to do in face of this dehumanising of 
mankind, this universal hiding of the knowledge of Himself by the wiles of evil 
spirits? Was He to keep silence before so great a wrong and let men go on being 
thus deceived and kept in ignorance of Himself? If so, what was the use of 
having made them in His own Image originally? It would surely have been better 
for them always to have been brutes, rather than to revert to that condition 
when once they had shared the nature of the Word. Again, things being as they 
were, what was the use of their ever having had the knowledge of God? Surely it 
would have been better for God never to have bestowed it, than that men should 
subsequently be 
found unworthy to receive it. Similarly, what possible profit 
could it be to God Himself, Who made men, if when made they did not worship Him, 
but regarded others as their makers? This would be tantamount to His having made 
them for others and not for Himself. Even an earthly king, though he is only a 
man, does not allow lands that he has colonized to pass into other hands or to 
desert to other rulers, but sends letters and friends and even visits them 
himself to recall them to their allegiance, rather than allow His work to be 
undone. How much more, then, will God be patient and painstaking with His 
creatures, that they be not led astray from Him to the service of those that are 
not, and that all the more because such error means for them sheer ruin, and 
because it is not right that those who had once shared His Image should be 
destroyed.</p>
<p id="iv-p7">What, then, was God to do? What else could He possibly do, being God, but 
renew His Image in mankind, so that through it men might once more come to know 
Him? And how could this be done save by the coming of the very Image Himself, 
our Savior Jesus Christ? Men could not have done it, for they are only made 
after the Image; nor could angels have done it, for they are not the images of 
God. The Word of God came in His own Person, because it was He alone, the Image 
of the Father Who could recreate man made after the Image.</p>
<p id="iv-p8">In order to effect this re-creation, however, He had first to do away with 
death and corruption. Therefore He assumed a human body, in order that in it 
death might once for all be destroyed, and that men might be renewed according 
to the Image. The Image of the Father only was sufficient for this need. Here is 
an illustration to prove it.</p>
<p id="iv-p9"><b>(14)</b> You know what happens when a portrait that has 
been painted on a panel becomes obliterated through external stains. The artist 
does not throw away the panel, but the subject of the portrait has to come and 
sit for it again, and then the likeness is re-drawn on the same material. Even 
so was it with the All-holy Son of God. He, the Image of the Father, came and 
dwelt in our midst, in order that He might renew mankind made after Himself, and 
seek out His lost sheep, even as He says in the Gospel: 
"I came to seek and to save that which was lost.<note n="18" id="iv-p9.1"><scripRef passage="Luke 19:10" id="iv-p9.2" parsed="|Luke|19|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.19.10">Luke xix. 10</scripRef></note> 
This also explains His saying to the Jews: "<i>Except a man be born 
anew . . .</i>"<note n="19" id="iv-p9.3"><scripRef passage="John 3:3" id="iv-p9.4" parsed="|John|3|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.3.3">John iii. 3</scripRef></note> 
a He was not referring to a man's natural birth from his mother, as they thought, 
but to the re-birth and re-creation of the soul in the Image of God.</p>
<p id="iv-p10">Nor was this the only thing which only the Word could do. When the madness of 
idolatry and irreligion filled the world and the knowledge of God was hidden, 
whose part was it to teach the world about the Father? Man's, would you say? But 
men cannot run everywhere over the world, nor would their words carry sufficient 
weight if they did, nor would they be, unaided, a match for the evil spirits. 
Moreover, since even the best of men were confused and blinded by evil, how 
could they convert the souls and minds of others? You cannot put straight in 
others what is warped in yourself. Perhaps you will say, then, that creation was 
enough to teach men about the Father. But if that had 
been so, such great evils 
would never have occurred. Creation was there all the time, but it did not 
prevent men from wallowing in error. Once more, then, it was the Word of God, 
Who sees all that is in man and moves all things in creation, Who alone could 
meet the needs of the situation. It was His part and His alone, Whose ordering 
of the universe reveals the Father, to renew the same teaching. But how was He 
to do it? By the same means as before, perhaps you will say, that is, through 
the works of creation. But this was proven insufficient. Men had neglected to 
consider the heavens before, and now they were looking in the opposite 
direction. Wherefore, in all naturalness and fitness, desiring to do good to 
men, as Man He dwells, taking to Himself a body like the rest; and through His 
actions done in that body, as it were on their own level, He teaches those who 
would not learn by other means to know Himself, the Word of God, and through Him 
the Father.</p>
<p id="iv-p11"><b>(15)</b> He deals with them as a good teacher with his 
pupils, coming down to their level and using simple means. St. Paul says as 
much: 
"Because in the wisdom of God the world in its wisdom 
knew not God, God thought fit through the simplicity of the News proclaimed to 
save those who believe."<note n="20" id="iv-p11.1"><scripRef passage="1 Corinthians 1:21 " id="iv-p11.2" parsed="|1Cor|1|21|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.1.21">1 Cor. i. 21</scripRef></note> 
Men had turned from the contemplation of God above, and were 
looking for Him in the opposite direction, down among created things and things 
of sense. The Savior of us all, the Word of God, in His great love took to 
Himself a body and moved as Man among men, meeting their senses, so to speak, 
half way. He became Himself an object for the senses, so that those who were 
seeking God in sensible things might apprehend the Father through the works 
which He, the Word of God, did in the body. Human and human minded as men were, 
therefore, to whichever side they looked in the sensible world they found 
themselves taught the truth. Were they awe-stricken by creation? They beheld it 
confessing Christ as Lord. Did their minds tend to regard men as Gods? The 
uniqueness of the Savior's works marked Him, alone of men, as Son of God. Were 
they drawn to evil spirits? They saw them driven out by the Lord and learned 
that the Word of God alone was God and that the evil spirits were not gods at 
all. Were they inclined to hero-worship and the cult of the dead? Then the fact 
that the Savior had risen from the dead showed them how false these other 
deities were, and that the Word of the Father is the one true Lord, the Lord 
even of death. For this reason was He both born and manifested as Man, for this 
He died and rose, in order that, eclipsing by His works all other human deeds, 
He might recall men from all the paths of error to know the Father. As He says 
Himself, 
"I came to seek and to save that which was lost."<note n="21" id="iv-p11.3"><scripRef passage="Luke 19:10" id="iv-p11.4" parsed="|Luke|19|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.19.10">Luke xix. 10</scripRef></note></p> 
<p id="iv-p12"><b>(16)</b> When, then, the minds of men had fallen finally to 
the level of sensible things, the Word submitted to appear in a body, in order 
that He, as Man, might center their senses on Himself, and convince them through 
His human acts that He Himself is not man only but also God, the Word and Wisdom of 
the true God. This is what Paul wants to tell us when he says: 
"That ye, being rooted and grounded in love, may be 
strong to apprehend with all the saints what is the length and breadth and 
height and depth, and to know the love of God that surpasses knowledge, so 
that ye may be filled unto all the fullness of God."<note n="22" id="iv-p12.1"><scripRef passage="Ephesians 3:17" id="iv-p12.2" parsed="|Eph|3|17|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eph.3.17">Eph. iii. 17 ff.</scripRef></note>  
The Self-revealing of the Word is in every dimension—above, in 
creation; below, in the Incarnation; in the depth, in Hades; in the breadth, 
throughout the world. All things have been filled with the knowledge of God.</p>
<p id="iv-p13">For this reason He did not offer the sacrifice on behalf of all immediately 
He came, for if He had surrendered His body to death and then raised it again at 
once He would have ceased to be an object of our senses. Instead of that, He 
stayed in His body and let Himself be seen in it, doing acts and giving signs 
which showed Him to be not only man, but also God the Word. There were thus two 
things which the Savior did for us by becoming Man. He banished death from us 
and made us anew; and, invisible and imperceptible as in Himself He is, He 
became visible through His works and revealed Himself as the Word of the Father, 
the Ruler and King of the whole creation.</p>
<p id="iv-p14"><b>(17)</b> There is a paradox in this last statement which we 
must now examine. The Word was not hedged in by His body, nor did His presence 
in the body prevent His being present elsewhere as well. When He moved His body 
He did not cease also to direct the universe by His Mind and might. No. The 
marvelous truth is, that being the Word, so far from being Himself contained by 
anything, He actually contained all things Himself. In creation He is present 
everywhere, yet is distinct in being from it; ordering, directing, giving life 
to all, containing all, yet is He Himself the Uncontained, existing solely in 
His Father. As with the whole, so also is it with the part. Existing in a human 
body, to which He Himself gives life, He is still Source of life to all the 
universe, present in every part of it, yet outside the whole; and He is revealed 
both through the works of His body and through His activity in the world. It is, 
indeed, the function of soul to <i>behold</i> things that are outside the body, but it 
cannot energize or move them. A man cannot transport things from one place to 
another, for instance, merely by thinking about them; nor can you or I move the 
sun and the stars just by sitting at home and looking at them. With the Word of 
God in His human nature, however, it was otherwise. His body was for Him not a 
limitation, but an instrument, so that He was both in it and in all things, and 
outside all things, resting in the Father alone. At one and the same time—this 
is the wonder—as Man He was living a human life, and as Word He was sustaining 
the life of the universe, and as Son He was in constant union with the Father. 
Not even His birth from a virgin, therefore, changed Him in any way, nor was He 
defiled by being in the body. Rather, He sanctified the body by being in it. For 
His being in everything does not mean that He shares the nature of everything, 
only that He gives all things their being and sustains them in it. Just as the 
sun is not defiled by the contact of its rays with earthly objects, but rather 
enlightens and purifies them, so He Who made the sun is not defiled by being 
made known in 
a body, but rather the body is cleansed and quickened by His 
indwelling, 
"Who did no sin, neither was guile found in His 
mouth."<note n="23" id="iv-p14.1"><scripRef passage="1 Peter " id="iv-p14.2">1 Peter ii. 22</scripRef></note></p> 
<p id="iv-p15"><b>(18)</b> You must understand, therefore, that when writers 
on this sacred theme speak of Him as eating and drinking and being born, they 
mean that the body, as a body, was born and sustained with the food proper to 
its nature; while God the Word, Who was united with it, was at the same time 
ordering the universe and revealing Himself through His bodily acts as not man 
only but God. Those acts are rightly said to be His acts, because the body which 
did them did indeed belong to Him and none other; moreover, it was right that 
they should be thus attributed to Him as Man, in order to show that His body was 
a real one and not merely an appearance. From such ordinary acts as being born 
and taking food, He was recognized as being actually present in the body; but by 
the extraordinary acts which He did through the body He proved Himself to be the 
Son of God. That is the meaning of His words to the unbelieving Jews: 
"If I do not the works of My Father, believe Me not; 
but if I do, even if ye believe not Me, believe My works, that ye may know 
that the Father is in Me and I in the Father."<note n="24" id="iv-p15.1"><scripRef passage="John 10:37-38" id="iv-p15.2" parsed="|John|10|37|10|38" osisRef="Bible:John.10.37-John.10.38">John x. 37–38</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="iv-p16">Invisible in Himself, He is known from the works of creation; so also, when 
His Godhead is veiled in human nature, His bodily acts still declare Him to be 
not man only, but the Power and Word of God. To speak authoritatively to evil 
spirits, for instance, and to drive them out, is not human but divine; and who 
could see-Him curing all the diseases to which mankind is prone, and still deem 
Him mere man and not also God? He cleansed lepers, He made the lame to walk, He 
opened the ears of the deaf and the eyes of the blind, there was no sickness or 
weakness that He did not drive away. Even the most casual observer can see that 
these were acts of God. The healing of the man born blind, for instance, who but 
the Father and Artificer of man, the Controller of his whole being, could thus 
have restored the faculty denied at birth? He Who did thus must surely be 
Himself the Lord of birth. This is proved also at the outset of His becoming 
Man. He formed His own body from the virgin; and that is no small proof of His 
Godhead, since He Who made that was the Maker of all else. And would not anyone 
infer from the fact of that body being begotten of a virgin only, without human 
father, that He Who appeared in it was also the Maker and Lord of all beside?</p>
<p id="iv-p17">Again, consider the miracle at Cana. Would not anyone who saw the substance 
of water transmuted into wine understand that He Who did it was the Lord and 
Maker of the water that He changed? It was for the same reason that He walked on 
the sea as on dry land—to prove to the onlookers that He had mastery over all. 
And the feeding of the multitude, when He made little into much, so that from 
five loaves five thousand mouths were filled—did not that prove Him none other 
than the very Lord Whose Mind is over all?</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 4. The Death of Christ" progress="31.71%" prev="iv" next="vi" id="v">

<h2 id="v-p0.1">Chapter 4</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="v-p1"><i>The Death of Christ</i></p>

<p id="v-p2"><b>(19)</b> All these things the Savior thought fit to do, so 
that, recognizing His bodily acts as works of God, men who were blind to His 
presence in creation might regain knowledge of the Father. For, as I said 
before, who that saw His authority over evil spirits and their response to it 
could doubt that He was, indeed, the Son, the Wisdom and the Power of God? Even 
the very creation broke silence at His behest and, marvelous to relate, 
confessed with one voice before the cross, that monument of victory, that He Who 
suffered thereon in the body was not man only, but Son of God and Savior of all. 
The sun veiled his face, the earth quaked, the mountains were rent asunder, all 
men were stricken with awe. These things showed that Christ on the cross was 
God, and that all creation was His slave and was bearing witness by its fear to 
the presence of its Master.</p>
<p id="v-p3">Thus, then, God the Word revealed Himself to men through His works. We must 
next consider the end of His earthly life and the nature of His bodily death. 
This is, indeed, the very center of our faith, and everywhere you hear men speak 
of it; by it, too, no less than by His other acts, Christ is revealed as God and 
Son of God.</p>
<p id="v-p4"><b>(20)</b> We have dealt as far as circumstances and our own 
understanding permit with the reason for His bodily manifestation. We have seen 
that to change the corruptible to incorruption was proper to none other than the 
Savior Himself, Who in the beginning made all things out of nothing; that only 
the Image of the Father could re-create the likeness of the Image in men, that 
none save our Lord Jesus Christ could give to mortals immortality, and that only 
the Word Who orders all things and is alone the Father's true and sole-begotten 
Son could teach men about Him and abolish the worship of idols. But beyond all 
this, there was a debt owing which must needs be paid; for, as I said before, 
all men were due to die. Here, then, is the second reason why the Word dwelt 
among us, namely that having proved His Godhead by His works, He might offer the 
sacrifice on behalf of all, surrendering His own temple to death in place of 
all, to settle man's account with death and free him from the primal 
transgression. In the same act also He showed Himself mightier than death, 
displaying His own 
body incorruptible as the first-fruits of the resurrection.</p>

<p id="v-p5">You must not be surprised if we repeat ourselves in dealing with this 
subject. We are speaking of the good pleasure of God and of the things which He 
in His loving wisdom thought fit to do, and it is better to put the same thing 
in several ways than to run the risk of leaving something out. The body of the 
Word, then, being a real human body, in spite of its having been uniquely formed 
from a virgin, was of itself mortal and, like other bodies, liable to death. But 
the indwelling of the Word loosed it from this natural liability, so that 
corruption could not touch it. Thus it happened that two opposite marvels took 
place at once: the death of all was consummated in the Lord's body; yet, because 
the Word was in it, death and corruption were in the same act utterly abolished. 
Death there had to be, and death for all, so that the due of all might be paid. 
Wherefore, the Word, as I said, being Himself incapable of death, assumed a 
mortal body, that He might offer it as His own in place of all, and suffering 
for the sake of all through His union with it, 
" might bring to nought Him that had the power of 
death, that is, the devil, and might deliver them who all their lifetime were 
enslaved by the fear of death."<note n="25" id="v-p5.1"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 2:14" id="v-p5.2" parsed="|Heb|2|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.2.14">Heb. ii. 14 f.</scripRef></note></p> 
<p id="v-p6"><b>(21)</b> Have no fears then. Now that the common Savior of 
all has died on our behalf, we who believe in Christ no longer die, as men died 
aforetime, in fulfillment of the threat of the law. That condemnation has come 
to an end; and now that, by the grace of the resurrection, corruption has been 
banished and done away, we are loosed from our mortal bodies in God's good time 
for each, so that we may obtain thereby a better resurrection. Like seeds cast 
into the earth, we do not perish in our dissolution, but like them shall rise 
again, death having been brought to nought by the grace of the Savior. That is 
why blessed Paul, through whom we all have surety of the resurrection, says: 
"This corruptible must put on incorruption and this 
mortal must put on immortality; but when this corruptible shall have put on 
incorruption and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be 
brought to pass the saying that is written, 'Death is swallowed up in victory. 
O Death, where is thy sting? O Grave, where is thy victory?'"<note n="26" id="v-p6.1"><scripRef passage="1 Corinthians 15:53" id="v-p6.2" parsed="|1Cor|15|53|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.15.53">1 Cor. xv. 53 ff.</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="v-p7">"Well then," some people may say, "if the essential thing was that 
He should surrender His body to death in place of all, why did He not do so as 
Man privately, without going to the length of public crucifixion? Surely it 
would have been more suitable for Him to have laid aside His body with honor 
than to endure so shameful a death." But look at this argument closely, and see 
how merely human it is, whereas what the Savior did was truly divine and worthy 
of His Godhead for several reasons. The first is this. The death of men under 
ordinary circumstances is the result of their natural weakness. They are 
essentially impermanent, so after a time they fall ill and when worn out they 
die. But the Lord is not like that. He is not weak, He is the Power of God and 
Word of God and Very Life Itself. If He had died quietly in His bed like other 
men it would have looked as if He did so in accordance with His nature, and as 
though He was indeed no more than other men. But because He was Himself Word and 
Life and Power His body was made strong, and because the death had to be 
accomplished, He took the occasion of perfecting His sacrifice not from Himself, 
but from others. How could He fall sick, Who had healed others? Or how could 
that body weaken and fail by means of which others are made strong? Here, again, 
you may say, "Why did He not prevent death, as He did sickness?" Because it was 
precisely in order to be able to die that He had taken a body, and to prevent 
the death would have been to impede the resurrection. And as to the 
unsuitability of sickness for His body, as arguing weakness, you may say, 
"<i>Did He then not hunger</i>?" Yes, He hungered, because that was 
the property of His body, but He did not die of hunger because He Whose body 
hungered was the Lord. Similarly, though He died to ransom all, He did not see 
corruption. His body rose in perfect soundness, for it was the body of none 
other than the Life Himself.</p>
<p id="v-p8"><b>(22)</b> Someone else might say, perhaps, that it would 
have been better for the Lord to have avoided the designs of the Jews against 
Him, and so to have guarded His body from death altogether. But see how 
unfitting this also would have been for Him. Just as it would not have been 
fitting for Him to give His body to death by His own hand, being Word and being 
Life, so also it was not consonant with Himself that He should avoid the death 
inflicted by others. Rather, He pursued it to the uttermost, and in pursuance of 
His nature neither laid aside His body of His own accord nor escaped the 
plotting Jews. And this action showed no limitation or weakness in the Word; for 
He both waited for death in order to make an end of it, and hastened to 
accomplish it as an offering on behalf of all. Moreover, as it was the death of 
all mankind that the Savior came to accomplish, not His own, He did not lay 
aside His body by an individual act of dying, for to Him, as Life, this simply 
did not belong; but He accepted death at the hands of men, thereby completely to 
destroy it in His own body.</p>
<p id="v-p9">There are some further considerations which enable one to understand why the 
Lord's body had such an end. The supreme object of His coming was to bring about 
the resurrection of the body. This was to be the monument to His victory over 
death, the assurance to all that He had Himself conquered corruption and that 
their own bodies also would eventually be incorrupt; and it was in token of that 
and as a pledge of the future resurrection that He kept His body incorrupt. But 
there again, if His body had fallen sick and the Word had left it in that 
condition, how unfitting it would have been! Should He Who healed the bodies of 
others neglect to keep His own in health? How would His miracles of healing be 
believed, if this were so? Surely people would either laugh at Him as unable to 
dispel disease or else consider Him lacking in proper human feeling because He 
could do so, but did not.</p>
<p id="v-p10"><b>(23)</b> Then, again, suppose without any illness He had 
just concealed His body somewhere, and then suddenly reappeared and said that He 
had risen from the dead. He would have been regarded merely as a teller of 
tales, and because there was no witness of His death, nobody would believe His 
resurrection. Death had to precede resurrection, for there could be no 
resurrection without it. A 
secret and unwitnessed death would have left the 
resurrection without any proof or evidence to support it. Again, why should He 
die a secret death, when He proclaimed the fact of His rising openly? Why should 
He drive out evil spirits and heal the man blind from birth and change water 
into wine, all publicly, in order to convince men that He was the Word, and not 
also declare publicly that incorruptibility of His mortal body, so that He might 
Himself be believed to be the Life? And how could His disciples have had 
boldness in speaking of the resurrection unless they could state it as a fact 
that He had first died? Or how could their hearers be expected to believe their 
assertion, unless they themselves also had witnessed His death? For if the 
Pharisees at the time refused to believe and forced others to deny also, though 
the things had happened before their very eyes, how many excuses for unbelief 
would they have contrived, if it had taken place secretly? Or how could the end 
of death and the victory over it have been declared, had not the Lord thus 
challenged it before the sight of all, and by the incorruption of His body 
proved that henceforward it was annulled and void?</p>
<p id="v-p11"><b>(24)</b> There are some other possible objections that must 
be answered. Some might urge that, even granting the necessity of a public death 
for subsequent belief in the resurrection, it would surely have been better for 
Him to have arranged an honorable death for Himself, and so to have avoided the 
ignominy of the cross. But even this would have given ground for suspicion that 
His power over death was limited to the particular kind of death which He chose 
for Himself; and that again would furnish excuse for disbelieving the 
resurrection. Death came to His body, therefore, not from Himself but from enemy 
action, in order that the Savior might utterly abolish death in whatever form 
they offered it to Him. A generous wrestler, virile and strong, does not himself 
choose his antagonists, lest it should be thought that of some of them he is 
afraid. Rather, he lets the spectators choose them, and that all the more if 
these are hostile, so that he may overthrow whomsoever they match against him 
and thus vindicate his superior strength. Even so was it with Christ. He, the 
Life of all, our Lord and Savior, did not arrange the manner of his own death 
lest He should seem to be afraid of some other kind. No. He accepted and bore 
upon the cross a death inflicted by others, and those others His special 
enemies, a death which to them was supremely terrible and by no means to be 
faced; and He did this in order that, by destroying even this death, He might 
Himself be believed to be the Life, and the power of death be recognized as 
finally annulled. A marvelous and mighty paradox has thus occurred, for the 
death which they thought to inflict on Him as dishonor and disgrace has become 
the glorious monument to death's defeat. Therefore it is also, that He neither 
endured the death of John, who was beheaded, nor was He sawn asunder, like 
Isaiah: even in death He preserved His body whole and undivided, so that there 
should be no excuse hereafter for those who would divide the Church.</p>
<p id="v-p12"><b>(25)</b> So much for the objections of those outside the 
Church. But if any honest Christian wants to know why He suffered death on the 
cross and not in some other way, we answer thus: in no other way was it 
expedient for us, indeed the Lord offered for our sakes the one death that was 
supremely good. He had come to bear the curse that lay on us; and how could He 
"become a curse"<note n="27" id="v-p12.1"><scripRef passage="Galatians 3:13" id="v-p12.2" parsed="|Gal|3|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gal.3.13">Gal. iii. 13</scripRef></note> 
otherwise than by accepting the accursed death? And that death is the cross, for 
it is written "Cursed is every one that hangeth on 
tree."<note n="28" id="v-p12.3"><scripRef passage="Galatians 3:13" id="v-p12.4" parsed="|Gal|3|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gal.3.13">Gal. iii. 13</scripRef></note> 
Again, the death of the Lord is the ransom of all, and by it "the middle wall of 
partition"<note n="29" id="v-p12.5"><scripRef passage="Ephesians 2:14" id="v-p12.6" parsed="|Eph|2|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eph.2.14">Eph. ii. 14</scripRef></note> is 
broken down and the call of the Gentiles comes about. How could He have called 
us if He had not been crucified, for it is only on the cross that a man dies 
with arms outstretched? Here, again, we see the fitness of His death and of 
those outstretched arms: it was that He might draw His ancient people with the 
one and the Gentiles with the other, and join both together in Himself. Even so, 
He foretold the manner of His redeeming death, 
"I, if I be lifted up, will draw all men unto 
Myself."<note n="30" id="v-p12.7"><scripRef passage="John 12:32" id="v-p12.8" parsed="|John|12|32|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.12.32">John xii. 32</scripRef></note> 
Again, the air is the sphere of the devil, the enemy of our race 
who, having fallen from heaven, endeavors with the other evil spirits who shared 
in his disobedience both to keep souls from the truth and to hinder the progress 
of those who are trying to follow it. The apostle refers to this when he says, 
"According to the prince of the power of the air, of 
the spirit that now worketh in the sons of disobedience."<note n="31" id="v-p12.9"><scripRef passage="Ephesians 2:2" id="v-p12.10" parsed="|Eph|2|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eph.2.2">Eph. ii. 2</scripRef></note> 
But the Lord came to overthrow the devil and to purify the air and 
to make "a way" for us up to heaven, as the apostle says, 
"through the veil, that is to say, His flesh."<note n="32" id="v-p12.11"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 10:20" id="v-p12.12" parsed="|Heb|10|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.10.20">Heb. x. 20</scripRef></note> 
This had to be done through death, and by what other kind of death could it be 
done, save by a death in the air, that is, on the cross? Here, again, you see 
how right and natural it was that the Lord should suffer thus; for being thus "lifted up," 
He cleansed the air from all the evil influences of the enemy. 
"I beheld Satan as lightning falling,"<note n="33" id="v-p12.13"><scripRef passage="Luke 10:18" id="v-p12.14" parsed="|Luke|10|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.10.18">Luke x. 18</scripRef></note> 
He says; and thus He re-opened the road to heaven, saying again, 
"Lift up your gates, O ye princes, and be ye lift up, ye 
everlasting doors."<note n="34" id="v-p12.15"><scripRef passage="Psalm 24:7" id="v-p12.16" parsed="|Ps|24|7|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.24.7">Psalm  xxiv. 7</scripRef></note> 
For it was not the Word Himself Who needed an opening of the gates, 
He being Lord of all, nor was any of His works closed to their Maker. No, it was 
we who needed it, we whom He Himself upbore in His own body—that body which He 
first offered to death on behalf of all, and then made through it a path to 
heaven.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 5. The Resurrection" progress="42.99%" prev="v" next="vii" id="vi">
<h2 id="vi-p0.1">Chapter 5</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="vi-p1"><i>The Resurrection</i></p>

<p id="vi-p2"><b>(26)</b> Fitting indeed, then, and wholly consonant was the 
death on the cross for us; and we can see how reasonable it was, and why it is 
that the salvation of the world could be accomplished in no other way. Even on 
the cross He did not hide Himself from sight; rather, He made all creation 
witness to the presence of its Maker. Then, having once let it be seen that it 
was truly dead, He did not allow that temple of His body to linger long, but 
forthwith on the third day raised it up, impassable and incorruptible, the 
pledge and token of His victory.</p>
<p id="vi-p3">It was, of course, within His power thus to have raised His body and 
displayed it as alive directly after death. But the all-wise Savior did not do 
this, lest some should deny that it had really or completely died. Besides this, 
had the interval between His death and resurrection been but two days, the glory 
of His incorruption might not have appeared. He waited one whole day to show 
that His body was really dead, and then on the third day showed it incorruptible 
to all. The interval was no longer, lest people should have forgotten about it 
and grown doubtful whether it were in truth the same body. No, while the affair 
was still ringing in their ears and their eyes were still straining and their 
minds in turmoil, and while those who had put Him to death were still on the 
spot and themselves witnessing to the fact of it, the Son of God after three 
days showed His once dead body immortal and incorruptible; and it was evident to 
all that it was from no natural weakness that the body which the Word indwelt 
had died, but in order that in it by the Savior's power death might be done 
away.</p>
<p id="vi-p4"><b>(27)</b> A very strong proof of this destruction of death 
and its conquest by the cross is supplied by a present fact, namely this. All 
the disciples of Christ despise death; they take the offensive against it and, 
instead of fearing it, by the sign of the cross and by faith in Christ trample 
on it as on something dead. Before the divine sojourn of the Savior, even the 
holiest of men were afraid of death, and mourned the dead as those who perish. 
But now that the Savior has raised His body, death is no longer terrible, but 
all those who believe in Christ tread it underfoot as nothing, and prefer to die 
rather than to deny their faith in Christ, knowing full well that when they die 
they do not perish, but live indeed, and become incorruptible through the 
resurrection. But that devil who of old wickedly exulted in death, now that the 
pains of death are loosed, he alone it is who remains truly dead. There is proof 
of this too; for men who, before they believe in Christ, think death horrible 
and are afraid of it, once they are converted despise it so completely that they 
go eagerly to meet it, and themselves become witnesses of the Savior's 
resurrection from it. Even children hasten thus to die, and not men only, but 
women train themselves by bodily discipline to meet it. So weak has death become 
that even women, who used to be taken in by it, mock at it now as a dead thing 
robbed of all its strength. Death has become like a tyrant who has been 
completely conquered by the legitimate monarch; bound hand and foot the 
passers-by sneer at him, hitting him and abusing him, no longer afraid of his 
cruelty and rage, because of the king who has conquered him. So has death been 
conquered and branded for what it is by the Savior on the cross. It is bound 
hand and foot, all who are in Christ trample it as they pass and as witnesses to 
Him deride it, scoffing and saying, "O Death, where is thy 
victory? O Grave, where is thy sting?"<note n="35" id="vi-p4.1"><scripRef passage="1 Corinthians 15:55" id="vi-p4.2" parsed="|1Cor|15|55|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.15.55">I Cor. xv. 55</scripRef></note> 
</p>
<p id="vi-p5"><b>(28)</b> Is this a slender proof of the impotence of death, 
do you think? Or is it a slight indication of the Savior's victory over it, when 
boys and young girls who are in Christ look beyond this present life and train 
themselves to die? Every one is by nature afraid of death and of bodily 
dissolution; the marvel of marvels is that he who is enfolded in the faith of 
the cross despises this natural fear and for the sake of the cross is no longer 
cowardly in face of it. The natural property of fire is to burn. Suppose, then, 
that there was a substance such as the Indian asbestos is said to be, which had 
no fear of being burnt, but rather displayed the impotence of the fire by 
proving itself unburnable. If anyone doubted the truth of this, all he need do 
would be to wrap himself up in the substance in question and then touch the 
fire. Or, again, to revert to our former figure, if anyone wanted to see the 
tyrant bound and helpless, who used to be such a terror to others, he could do 
so simply by going into the country of the tyrant's conqueror. Even so, if 
anyone still doubts the conquest of death, after so many proofs and so many 
martyrdoms in Christ and such daily scorn of death by His truest servants, he 
certainly does well to marvel at so great a thing, but he must not be obstinate 
in unbelief and disregard of plain facts. No, he must be like the man who wants 
to prove the property of the asbestos, and like him who enters the conqueror's 
dominions to see the tyrant bound. He must embrace the faith of Christ, this 
disbeliever in the conquest of death, and come to His teaching. Then he will see 
how impotent death is and how completely conquered. Indeed, there have been many 
former unbelievers and deriders who, after they became believers, so scorned 
death as even themselves to become martyrs for Christ's sake.</p>
<p id="vi-p6"><b>(29)</b> If, then, it is by the sign of the cross and by 
faith in Christ that death is trampled underfoot, it is clear that it is Christ 
Himself and none other Who is the Archvictor over death and has robbed it of its 
power. Death used to be strong and terrible, but now, since the sojourn of the 
Savior and the death and resurrection of His body, it is despised; and obviously 
it is by the very Christ Who mounted on the cross that it has been destroyed and 
vanquished finally. When the sun rises after the night and the whole world is 
lit up by it, nobody doubts that it is the sun which has thus shed its light 
everywhere and driven away the dark. Equally clear is it, since this utter 
scorning and trampling down of death has ensued upon the Savior's manifestation 
in the body and His death on the cross, that it is He Himself Who brought death 
to nought and daily raises monuments to His victory in His own disciples. How 
can you think otherwise, when you see men naturally weak hastening to death, 
unafraid at the prospect of corruption, fearless of the descent into Hades, even 
indeed with eager soul provoking it, not shrinking from tortures, but preferring 
thus to rush on death for Christ's sake, rather than to remain in this present 
life? If you see with your own eyes men and women and children, even, thus 
welcoming death for the sake of Christ's religion, how can you be so utterly 
silly and incredulous and maimed in your mind as not to realize that Christ, to 
Whom these all bear witness, Himself gives the victory to each, making death 
completely powerless for those who hold His faith and bear the sign of the 
cross? No one in his senses doubts that a snake is dead when he sees it trampled 
underfoot, especially when he knows how savage it used to be; nor, if he sees 
boys making fun of a lion, does he doubt that the brute is either dead or 
completely bereft of strength. These things can be seen with our own eyes, and 
it is the same with the conquest of death. Doubt no longer, then, when you see 
death mocked and scorned by those who believe in Christ, that by Christ death 
was destroyed, and the corruption that goes with it resolved and brought to end. 
</p>
<p id="vi-p7"><b>(30)</b> What we have said is, indeed, no small proof of 
the destruction of death and of the fact that the cross of the Lord is the 
monument to His victory. But the resurrection of the body to immortality, which 
results henceforward from the work of Christ, the common Savior and true Life of 
all, is more effectively proved by facts than by words to those whose mental 
vision is sound. For, if, as we have shown, death was destroyed and everybody 
tramples on it because of Christ, how much more did He Himself first trample and 
destroy it in His own body! Death having been slain by Him, then, what other 
issue could there be than the resurrection of His body and its open 
demonstration as the monument of His victory? How could the destruction of death 
have been manifested at all, had not the Lord's body been raised? But if anyone 
finds even this insufficient, let him find proof of what has been said in 
present facts. Dead men cannot take effective action; their power of influence 
on others lasts only till the grave. Deeds and actions that energize others 
belong only to the living. Well, then, look at the facts in this case. The 
Savior is working mightily among men, every day He is invisibly persuading 
numbers of people all over the world, both within and beyond the Greek-speaking 
world, to accept His faith and be obedient to His teaching. Can anyone, in face 
of this, still doubt that He has risen and lives, or rather that He is Himself 
the Life? Does a dead man prick the consciences of men, so that they throw all 
the traditions of their fathers to the winds and bow down before the teaching of 
Christ? If He is no longer active in the world, as He must needs be if He is 
dead, how is it that He makes the living to cease from their activities, the 
adulterer from his adultery, the murderer from murdering, the unjust from 
avarice, while the profane and godless man becomes religious? If He did not 
rise, but is still dead, how is it that He routs and persecutes and overthrows 
the false gods, whom unbelievers think to be alive, and the evil spirits whom 
they worship? For where Christ is named, idolatry is destroyed and the fraud of 
evil spirits is exposed; indeed, no such spirit can endure that Name, but takes 
to flight on sound of it. This is the work of One Who lives, not of one dead; 
and, more than that, it is the work of God. It would be absurd to say that the 
evil spirits whom He drives out and the idols which He destroys are alive, but 
that He Who drives out and destroys, and Whom they themselves acknowledge to be 
Son of God, is dead.</p>
<p id="vi-p8"><b>(31)</b> In a word, then, those who disbelieve in the 
resurrection have no support in facts, if their gods and evil spirits do not 
drive away the supposedly dead Christ. Rather, it is He Who convicts them of 
being dead. We are agreed that a dead person can do nothing: yet the Savior 
works mightily every day, drawing men to religion, persuading them to virtue, 
teaching them about immortality, quickening their thirst for heavenly things, 
revealing the knowledge of the Father, inspiring strength in face of death, 
manifesting Himself to each, and displacing the irreligion of idols; while the 
gods and evil spirits of the unbelievers can do none of these things, but rather 
become dead at Christ's presence, all their ostentation barren and void. By the 
sign of the cross, on the contrary, all magic is stayed, all sorcery confounded, 
all the idols are abandoned and deserted, and all senseless pleasure ceases, as 
the eye of faith looks up from earth to heaven. Whom, then, are we to call dead? 
Shall we call Christ dead, Who effects all this? But the dead have not the 
faculty to effect anything. Or shall we call death dead, which effects nothing 
whatever, but lies as lifeless and ineffective as are the evil spirits and the 
idols? The Son of God, "living and effective,"<note n="36" id="vi-p8.1"><scripRef passage="Hebrews 4:12" id="vi-p8.2" parsed="|Heb|4|12|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.4.12">Heb. iv. 12</scripRef></note> 
is active every day and effects the salvation of all; but death is daily proved to 
be stripped of all its strength, and it is the idols and the evil spirits who 
are dead, not He. No room for doubt remains, therefore, concerning the 
resurrection of His body.</p>
<p id="vi-p9">Indeed, it would seem that he who disbelieves this bodily rising of the Lord 
is ignorant of the power of the Word and Wisdom of God. If He took a body to 
Himself at all, and made it His own in pursuance of His purpose, as we have 
shown that He did, what was the Lord to do with it, and what was ultimately to 
become of that body upon which the Word had descended? Mortal and offered to 
death on behalf of all as it was, it could not but die; indeed, it was for that 
very purpose that the Savior had prepared it for Himself. But on the other hand 
it could not remain dead, because it had become the very temple of Life. It 
therefore died, as mortal, but lived again because of the Life within it; and 
its resurrection is made known through its works.</p>
<p id="vi-p10"><b>(32)</b> It is, indeed, in accordance with the nature of 
the invisible God that He should be thus known through His works; and those who 
doubt the Lord's resurrection because they do not now behold Him with their 
eyes, might as well deny the very laws of nature. They have ground for disbelief 
when works are lacking; but when the works cry out and prove the fact so 
clearly, why do they deliberately deny the risen life so manifestly shown? Even 
if their mental faculties are defective, surely their eyes can give them 
irrefragable proof of the power and Godhead of Christ. A blind man cannot see 
the sun, but he knows that it is above the earth from the warmth which it 
affords; similarly, let those who are still in the blindness of unbelief 
recognize the Godhead of Christ and the resurrection which He has brought about 
through His manifested power in others. Obviously He would not be expelling evil 
spirits and despoiling idols, if He were dead, for the evil spirits would not 
obey one who was dead. If, on the other hand, the very naming of Him drives them 
forth, He clearly is not dead; and the more so that the spirits, who perceive 
things unseen by men, would know if He were so and would refuse to obey Him. 
But, as a matter of fact, what profane persons doubt, the evil spirits 
know—namely that He is God; and for that reason they flee from Him and fall at 
His feet, crying out even as they cried when He was in the body, "We know Thee Who Thou art, the Holy One of God," and, 
"Ah, what have I in common with Thee, Thou Son of God? I implore Thee, 
torment me not."<note n="37" id="vi-p10.1">Cf. <scripRef passage="Luke 4:34" id="vi-p10.2" parsed="|Luke|4|34|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.4.34">Luke iv. 34</scripRef> and <scripRef passage="Mark 5:7" id="vi-p10.3" parsed="|Mark|5|7|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Mark.5.7">Mark v. 7</scripRef></note> 
</p>
<p id="vi-p11">Both from the confession of the evil spirits and from the daily witness of 
His works, it is manifest, then, and let none presume to doubt it, that the 
Savior has raised His own body, and that He is very Son of God, having His being 
from God as from a Father, Whose Word and Wisdom and Whose Power He is. He it is 
Who in these latter days assumed a body for the salvation of us all, and taught 
the world concerning the Father. He it is Who has destroyed death and freely 
graced us all with incorruption through the promise of the resurrection, having 
raised His own body as its first-fruits, and displayed it by the sign of the 
cross as the monument to His victory over death and its corruption.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 6. Refutation of the Jews" progress="54.33%" prev="vi" next="viii" id="vii">
<h2 id="vii-p0.1">Chapter 6</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="vii-p1"><i>Refutation of the Jews</i></p>

<p id="vii-p2"><b>(33)</b> We have dealt thus far with the Incarnation of our 
Savior, and have found clear proof of the resurrection of His Body and His 
victory over death. Let us now go further and investigate the unbelief and the 
ridicule with which Jews and Gentiles respectively regard these same facts. It 
seems that in both cases the points at issue are the same, namely the unfittingness or incongruity (as it seems to them) alike of the cross and of the 
Word's becoming man at all. But we have no hesitation in taking up the argument 
against these objectors, for the proofs on our side are extremely clear.</p>
<p id="vii-p3">First, then, we will consider the Jews. Their unbelief has its refutation in 
the Scriptures which even themselves read; for from cover to cover the inspired 
Book clearly teaches these things both in its entirety and in its actual words. 
Prophets foretold the marvel of the Virgin and of the Birth from her, saying, 
"Behold, a virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and 
they shall call his name '<i>Emmanuel</i>,' which means '<i>God is with us</i>.'"<note n="38" id="vii-p3.1"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 7:14" id="vii-p3.2" parsed="|Isa|7|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.7.14">Isaiah vii. 14</scripRef></note>  
And Moses, that truly great one in whose word the Jews trust so 
implicitly, he also recognized the importance and truth of the matter. He puts 
it thus: "There shall arise a star from Jacob and a man from 
Israel, and he shall break in pieces the rulers of Moab.<note n="39" id="vii-p3.3"><scripRef passage="Numbers 24:17" id="vii-p3.4" parsed="|Num|24|17|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Num.24.17">Numbers xxiv. 17</scripRef></note>  
And, again, 
"How lovely are thy dwellings, O Jacob, thy tents, O 
Israel! Like woodland valleys they give shade, and like parks by rivers, like 
tents which the Lord has pitched, like cedar-trees by streams. There shall 
come forth a Man from among his seed, and he shall rule over many peoples."<note n="40" id="vii-p3.5"><scripRef passage="Numbers 24:5-7" id="vii-p3.6" parsed="|Num|24|5|24|7" osisRef="Bible:Num.24.5-Num.24.7">Numbers xxiv. 5–7</scripRef></note>  
And, again, Isaiah says, 
"Before the Babe shall be old enough to call father or 
mother, he shall take the power of Damascus and the spoils of Samaria from 
under the eyes of the king of Assyria."<note n="41" id="vii-p3.7"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 8:4" id="vii-p3.8" parsed="|Isa|8|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.8.4">Isaiah viii. 4</scripRef></note> 
These words, then, foretell that a Man shall appear. And Scripture 
proclaims further that He that is to come is Lord of all. These are the words, 
"Behold, the Lord sitteth on an airy cloud and shall 
come into Egypt, and the man-made images of Egypt shall be shaken."<note n="42" id="vii-p3.9"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 19:1" id="vii-p3.10" parsed="|Isa|19|1|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.19.1">Isaiah xix. 1</scripRef></note>  
And it is from Egypt also that the Father calls him back, saying, 
"Out of Egypt have I called My Son."<note n="43" id="vii-p3.11"><scripRef passage="Hosea 11:1" id="vii-p3.12" parsed="|Hos|11|1|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Hos.11.1">Hosea xi. 1</scripRef></note></p> 
<p id="vii-p4"><b>(34)</b> Moreover, the Scriptures are not silent even about 
His death. On the contrary, they refer to it with the utmost clearness. They 
have not feared to speak also of the cause of it. He endures it, they say, not 
for His own sake, but for the sake of bringing immortality and salvation to all, 
and they record also the plotting of the Jews against Him and all the 
indignities which He suffered at their hands. Certainly nobody who reads the 
Scriptures can plead ignorance of the facts as an excuse for error! There is 
this passage, for instance: 
"A man that is afflicted and knows how to bear 
weakness, for His face is turned away. He was dishonored and not considered, 
He bears our sins and suffers for our sakes. And we for our part thought Him 
distressed and afflicted and ill-used; but it was for our sins that He was 
wounded and for our lawlessness that He was made weak. Chastisement for our 
peace was upon Him, and by His bruising we are healed."<note n="44" id="vii-p4.1"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 53:3-5" id="vii-p4.2" parsed="|Isa|53|3|53|5" osisRef="Bible:Isa.53.3-Isa.53.5">Isaiah liii. 3–5</scripRef></note>  
O marvel at the love of the Word for men, for it is on 
our account that He is dishonored, so that we may be brought to honor. 
"For all we," it goes on, "have strayed like sheep, man has 
strayed from his path, and the Lord has given Him up for our sins; and He 
Himself did not open His mouth at the ill-treatment. Like a sheep He was led 
to slaughter, and as a lamb is dumb before its shearer, so He opened not His 
mouth; in His humiliation His judgment was taken away."<note n="45" id="vii-p4.3"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 53:6-8" id="vii-p4.4" parsed="|Isa|53|6|53|8" osisRef="Bible:Isa.53.6-Isa.53.8">Isaiah liii. 6–8</scripRef></note>  
And then Scripture anticipates the surmises of any who might think 
from His suffering thus that He was just an ordinary man, and shows what power 
worked in His behalf. 
"Who shall declare of what lineage He comes?" it says, "for His life is exalted from the earth. By the lawlessnesses of the people 
was He brought to death, and I will give the wicked in return for His burial 
and the rich in return for His death. For He did no lawlessness, neither was 
deceit found in His mouth. And the Lord wills to heal Him of His 
affliction."<note n="46" id="vii-p4.5"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 53:8-10" id="vii-p4.6" parsed="|Isa|53|8|53|10" osisRef="Bible:Isa.53.8-Isa.53.10">Isaiah liii. 8–10</scripRef></note></p> 
<p id="vii-p5"><b>(35)</b> You have heard the prophecy of His death, and now, 
perhaps, you want to know what indications there are about the cross. Even this 
is not passed over in silence: on the contrary, the sacred writers proclaim it 
with the utmost plainness. Moses foretells it first, and that right loudly, when 
he says, 
"You shall see your Life hanging before your eyes, and 
shall not believe."<note n="47" id="vii-p5.1"><scripRef passage="Deuteronomy 28:66" id="vii-p5.2" parsed="|Deut|28|66|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Deut.28.66">Deut. xxviii. 66</scripRef></note> 
After him the prophets also give their witness, saying, 
"But I as an innocent lamb brought to be offered was 
yet ignorant of it. They plotted evil against Me, saying, 'Come, let us cast 
wood into His bread, and wipe Him out from the land of the living."<note n="48" id="vii-p5.3"><scripRef passage="Jeremiah 11:19" id="vii-p5.4" parsed="|Jer|11|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.11.19">Jer. xi. 19</scripRef></note> 
And, again, 
"They pierced My hands and My feet, they counted all 
My bones, they divided My garments for themselves and cast lots for My 
clothing."<note n="49" id="vii-p5.5"><scripRef passage="Psalm 22:16-18" id="vii-p5.6" parsed="|Ps|22|16|22|18" osisRef="Bible:Ps.22.16-Ps.22.18">Psalm  xxii. 16–18</scripRef></note>
Now a death lifted up and that takes place on wood can be none 
other than the death of the cross; moreover, it is only in that death that the 
hands and feet are pierced. Besides this, since the Savior dwelt among men, all 
nations everywhere have begun to know God; and this too Holy Writ expressly 
mentions. "There shall be the Root of Jesse," it says, 
"and he who rises up to rule the nations, on Him nations 
shall set their hope."<note n="50" id="vii-p5.7"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 11:10" id="vii-p5.8" parsed="|Isa|11|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.11.10">Isaiah xi. 10</scripRef></note></p>

<p id="vii-p6">These are just a few things in proof of what has taken place; but indeed all 
Scripture teems with disproof of Jewish unbelief. For example, which of the 
righteous men and holy prophets and patriarchs of whom the Divine Scriptures 
tell ever had his bodily birth from a virgin only? Was not Abel born of Adam, 
Enoch of Jared, Noah of Lamech, Abraham of Terah, Isaac of Abraham, and Jacob of 
Isaac? Was not Judah begotten by Jacob and Moses and Aaron by Ameram? Was not 
Samuel the son of Elkanah, David of Jesse, Solomon of David, Hezekiah of Ahaz, 
Josiah of Amon, Isaiah of Amos, Jeremiah of Hilkiah and Ezekiel of Buzi? Had not 
each of these a father as author of his being? So who is He that is born of a 
virgin only, that sign of which the prophet makes so much? Again, which of all 
those people had his birth announced to the world by a star in the heavens? When 
Moses was born his parents hid him. David was unknown even in his own 
neighborhood, so that mighty Samuel himself was ignorant of his existence and 
asked whether Jesse had yet another son. Abraham again became known to his 
neighbors as a great man only after his birth. But with Christ it was otherwise. 
The witness to His birth was not man, but a star shining in the heavens whence 
He was coming down.</p>
<p id="vii-p7"><b>(36)</b> Then, again, what king that ever was reigned and 
took trophies from his enemies before he had strength to call father or mother? 
Was not David thirty years old when he came to the throne and Solomon a grown 
young man? Did not Joash enter on his reign at the age of seven, and Josiah, 
some time after him, at about the same age, both of them fully able by that time 
to call father or mother? Who is there, then, that was reigning and despoiling 
his enemies almost before he was born? Let the Jews, who have investigated the 
matter, tell us if there was ever such a king in Israel or Judah—a king upon 
whom all the nations set their hopes and had peace, instead of being at enmity 
with him on every side! As long as Jerusalem stood there was constant war 
between them, and they all fought against Israel. The Assyrians oppressed 
Israel, the Egyptians persecuted them, the Babylonians fell upon them, and, 
strange to relate, even the Syrians their neighbors were at war with them. And 
did not David fight with Moab and smite the Syrians, and Hezekiah quail at the 
boasting of Sennacherib? Did not Amalek make war on Moses and the Amorites 
oppose him, and did not the inhabitants of Jericho array themselves against 
Joshua the son of Nun? Did not the nations always regard Israel with implacable 
hostility? Then it is worth inquiring who it is, on whom the nations are to set 
their hopes. Obviously there must be someone, for the prophet could not have 
told a lie. But did any of the holy prophets or of the early patriarchs die on 
the cross for the salvation of all? Was any of them wounded and killed for the 
healing of all? Did the idols of Egypt fall down before any righteous man or 
king that came there? Abraham came there certainly, but idolatry prevailed just 
the same; and Moses was born there, but the mistaken worship was unchanged.</p>
<p id="vii-p8"><b>(37)</b> Again, does Scripture tell of anyone who was 
pierced in hands and feet or hung upon a tree at all, and by means of a cross 
perfected his sacrifice for the salvation of all? It was not Abraham, for he 
died in his bed, as did also Isaac and Jacob. Moses and Aaron died in the 
mountain, and David ended his days in his house, without anybody having plotted 
against him. Certainly he had been sought by Saul, but he was preserved 
unharmed. Again Isaiah was sawn asunder, but he was not hung on a tree. Jeremiah 
was shamefully used, but he did not die under condemnation. Ezekiel suffered, 
but he did so, not on behalf of the people, but only to signify to them what was 
going to happen. Moreover, all these even when they suffered were but men, like 
other men; but He Whom the Scriptures declare to suffer on behalf of all is 
called not merely man but Life of all, although in point of fact He did share 
our human nature. "You shall see your Life hanging before your 
eyes," they say, and "Who shall declare of what lineage He 
comes?" With all the saints we can trace their descent from the 
beginning, and see exactly how each came to be; but the Divine Word maintains 
that we cannot declare the lineage of Him Who is the Life. Who is it, then, of 
Whom Holy Writ thus speaks? Who is there so great that even the prophets 
foretell of Him such mighty things? There is indeed no one in the Scriptures at 
all, save the common Savior of all, the Word of God, our Lord Jesus Christ. He 
it is that proceeded from a virgin, and appeared as man on earth, He it is Whose 
earthly lineage cannot be declared, because He alone derives His body from no 
human father, but from a virgin alone. We can trace the paternal descent of 
David and Moses and of all the patriarchs. But with the Savior we cannot do so, 
for it was He Himself Who caused the star to announce His bodily birth, and it 
was fitting that the Word, when He came down from heaven, should have His sign 
in heaven too, and fitting that the King of creation on His coming forth should 
be visibly recognized by all the world. He was actually born in Judea, yet men 
from Persia came to worship Him. He it is Who won victory from His demon foes 
and trophies from the idolaters even before His bodily appearing—namely, all 
the heathen who from every region have abjured the tradition of their fathers 
and the false worship of idols and are now placing their hope in Christ and 
transferring their allegiance to Him. The thing is happening before our very 
eyes, here in Egypt; and thereby another prophecy is fulfilled, for at no other 
time have the Egyptians ceased from their false worship save when the Lord of 
all, riding as on a cloud, came down here in the body and brought the error of 
idols to nothing and won over everybody to Himself and through Himself to the 
Father. He it is Who was crucified with the sun and moon as witnesses; and by 
His death salvation has come to all men, and all creation has been redeemed. He 
is the Life of all, and He it is Who like a sheep gave up His own body to death, 
His life for ours and our salvation.</p>
<p id="vii-p9"><b>(38)</b> Yet the Jews disbelieve this. This argument does 
not satisfy them. Well, then, let them be persuaded by other things in their own 
oracles. Of whom, for instance, do the prophets say 
"I was made manifest to those who did not seek Me, I 
was found by those who had not asked for Me? I said, 'See, here am I,' to the 
nation that had not called upon My Name. I stretched out My hands to a 
disobedient and gainsaying people."<note n="51" id="vii-p9.1"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 65:1,2" id="vii-p9.2" parsed="|Isa|65|1|65|2" osisRef="Bible:Isa.65.1-Isa.65.2">Isaiah lxv. 1, 2</scripRef></note> 
Who is this person that was made manifest, one might ask the Jews? 
If the prophet is speaking of himself, then they must tell us how he was first 
hidden, in order to be manifested afterwards. And, again, what kind of man is 
this prophet, who was not only revealed after being hidden, but also stretched 
out his hands upon the cross? Those things happened to none of those righteous 
men: they happened only to the Word of God Who, being by nature without body, on 
our account appeared in a body and suffered for us all. And if even this is not 
enough for them, there is other overwhelming evidence by which they may be 
silenced. The Scripture says, 
"Be strong, hands that hang down and feeble knees, 
take courage, you of little faith, be strong and do not fear. See, our God 
will recompense judgment, He Himself will come and save us. Then the eyes of 
blind men shall be opened and the ears of deaf men shall hear, and stammerers 
shall speak distinctly."<note n="52" id="vii-p9.3"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 35:3-6" id="vii-p9.4" parsed="|Isa|35|3|35|6" osisRef="Bible:Isa.35.3-Isa.35.6">Isaiah xxxv. 3–6</scripRef></note> 
What can they say to this, or how can they look it in the face at 
all? For the prophecy does not only declare that God will dwell here, it also 
makes known the signs and the time of His coming. When God comes, it says, the 
blind will see, the lame will walk, the deaf will hear and the stammerers will 
speak distinctly. Can the Jews tell us when such signs occurred in Israel, or 
when anything of the kind took place at all in Jewry? The leper Naaman was 
cleansed, it is true, but no deaf man heard nor did any lame man walk. Elijah 
raised a dead person and so did Elisha; but no one blind from birth received his 
sight. To raise a dead person is a great thing indeed, but it is not such as the 
Savior did. And surely, since the Scriptures have not kept silence about the 
leper and the dead son of the widow, if a lame man had walked and a blind man 
had received his sight, they would have mentioned these as well. Their silence 
on these points proves that the events never took place. When therefore did 
these things happen, unless when the Word of God Himself came in the body? Was 
it not when He came that lame men walked and stammerers spoke clearly and men 
blind from birth were given sight? And the Jews who saw it themselves testified 
to the fact that such things had never before occurred. "Since the world 
began," they said, 
"it has never been heard of that anyone should open 
the eyes of a man born blind. If this Man were not from God, He could do 
nothing."<note n="53" id="vii-p9.5"><scripRef passage="John 9:32,33" id="vii-p9.6" parsed="|John|9|32|9|33" osisRef="Bible:John.9.32-John.9.33">John ix. 32, 33</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="vii-p10"><b>(39)</b> But surely they cannot fight against plain facts. 
So it may be that, without denying what is written, they will maintain that they 
are still waiting for these things to happen, and that the Word of God is yet to 
come, for that is a theme on which they are always harping most brazenly, in 
spite of all the evidence against them. But they shall be refuted on this 
supreme point more clearly than on any, and that not by ourselves but by the 
most wise Daniel, for he signifies the actual date of the Savior's coming as 
well as His Divine sojourn in our midst. "Seventy weeks," he 
says, 
"are cut short upon thy people and upon the holy city, 
to make a complete end of sin and for sins to be sealed up and iniquities 
blotted out, and to make reconciliation for iniquity and to seal vision and 
prophet, and to anoint a Holy One of holies. And thou shalt know and 
understand from the going forth of the Word to answer,<note n="54" id="vii-p10.1">"Answer" is LXX misreading for Hebrew "restore."</note> 
and to build Jerusalem, until Christ the Prince."<note n="55" id="vii-p10.2"><scripRef passage="Daniel 9:24,25" id="vii-p10.3" parsed="|Dan|9|24|9|25" osisRef="Bible:Dan.9.24-Dan.9.25">Daniel ix. 24, 25</scripRef></note> 
In regard to the other prophecies, they may possibly be able to 
find excuses for deferring their reference to a future time, but what can they 
say to this one? How can they face it at all? Not only does it expressly mention 
the Anointed One, that is the Christ, it even declares that He Who is to be 
anointed is not man only, but the Holy One of holies! And it says that Jerusalem 
is to stand till His coming, and that after it prophet and vision shall cease in 
Israel! David was anointed of old, and Solomon, and Hezekiah; but then Jerusalem 
and the place stood, and prophets were prophesying, Gad and Asaph and Nathan, 
and later Isaiah and Hosea and Amos and others. Moreover, those men who were 
anointed were called holy certainly, but none of them was called the Holy of 
holies. Nor is it any use for the Jews to take refuge in the Captivity, and say 
that Jerusalem did not exist then, for what about the prophets? It is a fact 
that at the outset of the Exile Daniel and Jeremiah were there, and Ezekiel and 
Haggai and Zechariah also prophesied.</p>
<p id="vii-p11"><b>(40)</b> So the Jews are indulging in fiction, and 
transferring present time to future. When did prophet and vision cease from 
Israel? Was it not when Christ came, the Holy One of holies? It is, in fact, a 
sign and notable proof of the coming of the Word that Jerusalem no longer 
stands, neither is prophet raised up nor vision revealed among them. And it is 
natural that it should be so, for when He that was signified had come, what need 
was there any longer of any to signify Him? And when the Truth had come, what 
further need was there of the shadow? On His account only they prophesied 
continually, until such time as Essential Righteousness has come, Who was made 
the Ransom for the sins of all. For the same reason Jerusalem stood until the 
same time, in order that there men might premeditate the types before the Truth 
was known. So, of course, once the Holy One of holies had come, both vision and 
prophecy were sealed. And the kingdom of Jerusalem ceased at the same time, 
because kings were to be anointed among them only until the Holy of holies had 
been anointed. Moses also prophesies that the kingdom of the Jews shall stand 
until His time, saying, 
"A ruler shall not fail from Judah nor a prince from 
his loins, until the things laid up for him shall come and the Expectation of 
the nations Himself."<note n="56" id="vii-p11.1"><scripRef passage="Genesis 49:10" id="vii-p11.2" parsed="|Gen|49|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.49.10">Gen.  xlix. 10</scripRef></note>  
And that is why the Savior Himself was always proclaiming 
"The law and the prophets prophesied until John."<note n="57" id="vii-p11.3"><scripRef passage="Matthew 11:13" id="vii-p11.4" parsed="|Matt|11|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.11.13">Matt. xi. 13</scripRef></note> 
So if there is still king or prophet or vision among the <i>Jews</i>, they 
do well to deny that Christ is come; but if there is neither king nor vision, 
and since that time all prophecy has been sealed and city and temple taken, how 
can they be so irreligious, how can they so flaunt the facts, as to deny Christ 
Who has brought it all about? Again, they see the heathen forsaking idols and 
setting their hopes through Christ on the God of Israel; why do they yet deny 
Christ Who after the flesh was born of the root of Jesse and reigns 
henceforward? Of course, if the heathen were worshipping some other god, and not 
confessing the God of Abraham and Isaac and Jacob and Moses, then they would do 
well to argue that God had not come. But if the heathen are honoring the same 
God Who gave the law to Moses and the promises to Abraham—the God Whose word 
too the Jews dishonored, why do they not recognize or rather why do they 
deliberately refuse to see that the Lord of Whom the Scriptures prophesied has 
shone forth to the world and appeared to it in a bodily form? Scripture declares 
it repeatedly. "The Lord God has appeared to 
us,"<note n="58" id="vii-p11.5"><scripRef passage="Psalm 118:27" id="vii-p11.6" parsed="|Ps|118|27|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.118.27">Psalm  cxviii. 27</scripRef></note> 
and again, "He sent forth His Word and healed 
them."<note n="59" id="vii-p11.7"><scripRef passage="Psalm 107:20" id="vii-p11.8" parsed="|Ps|107|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.107.20">Psalm  cvii. 20</scripRef></note> 
And again, "It was no ambassador, no angel who saved us, but 
the Lord Himself."<note n="60" id="vii-p11.9"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 63:9" id="vii-p11.10" parsed="|Isa|63|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.63.9">Isaiah lxiii. 9</scripRef></note> 
The Jews are afflicted like some demented person who sees the earth lit up by 
the sun, but denies the sun that lights it up! What more is there for their 
Expected One to do when he comes? To call the heathen? But they are called 
already. To put an end to prophet and king and vision? But this too has already 
happened. To expose the Goddenyingness of idols? It is already exposed and 
condemned. Or to destroy death? It is already destroyed. What then has not come 
to pass that the Christ must do? What is there left out or unfulfilled that the 
Jews should disbelieve so light-heartedly? The plain fact is, as I say, that 
there is no longer any king or prophet nor Jerusalem nor sacrifice nor vision 
among them; yet the whole earth is filled with the knowledge of God, and the 
Gentiles, forsaking atheism, are now taking refuge with the God of Abraham 
through the Word, our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
<p id="vii-p12">Surely, then, it must be plain even to the most shameless that the Christ has 
come, and that He has enlightened all men everywhere, and given them the true 
and divine teaching about His Father.</p>
<p id="vii-p13">Thus the Jews may be refuted by these and other arguments from the Divine 
teaching.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 7. Refutation of the Gentiles" progress="70.15%" prev="vii" next="ix" id="viii">
<h2 id="viii-p0.1">Chapter 7</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="viii-p1"><i>Refutation of the Gentiles</i></p>

<p id="viii-p2"><b>(41)</b> We come now to the unbelief of the Gentiles; and 
this is indeed a matter for complete astonishment, for they laugh at that which 
is no fit subject for mockery, yet fail to see the shame and ridiculousness of 
their own idols. But the arguments on our side do not lack weight, so we will 
confute them too on reasonable grounds, chiefly from what we ourselves also see. 
</p>
<p id="viii-p3">First of all, what is there in our belief that is unfitting or ridiculous? Is 
it only that we say that the Word has been manifested in a body? Well, if they 
themselves really love the truth, they will agree with us that this involved no 
unfittingness at all. If they deny that there is a Word of God at all, that will 
be extraordinary, for then they will be ridiculing what they do not know. But 
suppose they confess that there is a Word of God, that He is the Governor of all 
things, that in Him the Father wrought the creation, that by His providence the 
whole receives light and life and being, and that He is King over all, so that 
He is known by means of the works of His providence, and through Him the Father. 
Suppose they confess all this, what then? Are they not unknowingly turning the 
ridicule against themselves? The Greek philosophers say that the universe is a 
great body, and they say truly, for we perceive the universe and its parts with 
our senses. But if the Word of God is in the universe, which is a body, and has 
entered into it in its every part, what is there surprising or unfitting in our 
saying that He has entered also into human nature? If it were unfitting for Him 
to have embodied Himself at all, then it would be unfitting for Him to have 
entered into the universe, and to be giving light and movement by His providence 
to all things in it, because the universe, as we have seen, is itself a body. 
But if it is right and fitting for Him to enter into the universe and to reveal 
Himself through it, then, because humanity is part of the universe along with 
the rest, it is no less fitting for Him to appear in a human body, and to 
enlighten and to work through that. And surely if it were wrong for a part of 
the universe to have been used to reveal His Divinity to men, it would be much 
more wrong that He should be so revealed by the whole!</p>
<p id="viii-p4"><b>(42)</b> Take a parallel case. A man's personality actuates 
and quickens his whole body. If anyone said it was unsuitable for the man's 
power to be in the toe, he would be thought silly, because, while granting that 
a man penetrates and actuates the whole of his body, he denied his presence in 
the part. Similarly, no one who admits the presence of the Word of God in the 
universe as a whole should think it unsuitable for a single human body to be by 
Him actuated and enlightened.</p>
<p id="viii-p5">But is it, perhaps, because humanity is a thing created and brought into 
being out of non-existence that they regard as unfitting the manifestation of 
the Savior in our nature? If so, it is high time that they spurned Him from 
creation too; for it, too, has been brought out of non-being into being by the 
Word. But if, on the other hand, although creation is a thing that has been 
made, it is not unsuitable for the Word to be present in it, then neither is it 
unsuitable for Him to be in man. Man is a part of the creation, as I said 
before; and the reasoning which applies to one applies to the other. All things 
derive from the Word their light and movement and life, as the Gentile authors 
themselves say, "In Him we live and move and have our 
being."<note n="61" id="viii-p5.1">See <scripRef passage="Acts 17:28" id="viii-p5.2" parsed="|Acts|17|28|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.17.28">Acts xvii. 28</scripRef></note> 
Very well then. That being so, it is by no means unbecoming that the Word should 
dwell in man. So if, as we say, the Word has used that in which He is as the 
means of His self-manifestation, what is there ridiculous in that? He could not 
have used it had He not been present in it; but we have already admitted that He 
is present both in the whole and in the parts. What, then, is there incredible 
in His manifesting Himself through that in which He is? By His own power He 
enters completely into each and all, and orders them throughout ungrudgingly; 
and, had He so willed, He could have revealed Himself and His Father by means of 
sun or moon or sky or earth or fire or water. Had He done so, no one could 
rightly have accused Him of acting unbecomingly, for He sustains in one whole 
all things at once, being present and invisibly revealed not only in the whole, 
but also in each particular part. This being so, and since, moreover, He has 
willed to reveal Himself through men, who are part of the whole, there can be 
nothing ridiculous in His using a human body to manifest the truth and knowledge 
of the Father. Does not the mind of man pervade his entire being, and yet find 
expression through one part only, namely the tongue? Does anybody say on that 
account that Mind has degraded itself? Of course not. Very well, then, no more 
is it degrading for the Word, Who pervades all things, to have appeared in a 
human body. For, as I said before, if it were unfitting for Him thus to indwell 
the part, it would be equally so for Him to exist within the whole.</p>
<p id="viii-p6"><b>(43)</b> Some may then ask, why did He not manifest Himself 
by means of other and nobler parts of creation, and use some nobler instrument, 
such as sun or moon or stars or fire or air, instead of mere man? The answer is 
this. The Lord did not come to make a display. He came to heal and to teach 
suffering men. For one who wanted to make a display the thing would have been 
just to appear and dazzle the beholders. But for Him Who came to heal and to 
teach the way was not merely to dwell here, but to put Himself at the disposal 
of those who needed Him, and to be manifested according as they could bear it, 
not vitiating the value of the Divine appearing by exceeding their capacity to 
receive it.</p>
<p id="viii-p7">Moreover, nothing in creation had erred from the path of God's purpose for 
it, save only man. Sun, moon, heaven, stars, water, air, none of these had 
swerved from their order, but, knowing the Word as their Maker and their King, 
remained as they were made. Men alone having rejected what is good, have 
invented nothings instead of the truth, and have ascribed the honor due to God 
and the knowledge concerning Him to demons and men in the form of stones. 
Obviously the Divine goodness could not overlook so grave a matter as this. But 
men could not recognize Him as ordering and ruling creation as a whole. So what 
does He do? He takes to Himself for instrument a part of the whole, namely a 
human body, and enters into that. Thus He ensured that men should recognize Him 
in the part who could not do so in the whole, and that those who could not lift 
their eyes to His unseen power might recognize and behold Him in the likeness of 
themselves. For, being men, they would naturally learn to know His Father more 
quickly and directly by means of a body that corresponded to their own and by 
the Divine works done through it; for by comparing His works with their own they 
would judge His to be not human but Divine. And if, as they say, it were 
unsuitable for the Word to reveal Himself through bodily acts, it would be 
equally so for Him to do so through the works of the universe. His being in 
creation does not mean that He shares its nature; on the contrary, all created 
things partake of His power. Similarly, though He used the body as His 
instrument, He shared nothing of its defect,<note n="62" id="viii-p7.1">Literally, "He shared nothing of the things of the body."</note> 
but rather sanctified it by His indwelling. Does not even Plato, 
of whom the Greeks think so much, say that the Author of the Universe, seeing it 
storm-tossed and in danger of sinking into the state of dissolution, takes his 
seat at the helm of the Life-force of the universe, and comes to the rescue and 
puts everything right? What, then, is there incredible in our saying that, 
mankind having gone astray, the Word descended upon it and was manifest as man, 
so that by His intrinsic goodness and His steersmanship He might save it from 
the storm?</p>
<p id="viii-p8"><b>(44)</b> It may be, however, that, though shamed into 
agreeing that this objection is void, the Greeks will want to raise another. 
They will say that, if God wanted to instruct and save mankind, He might have 
done so, not by His Word's assumption of a body, but, even as He at first 
created them, by the mere signification of His will. The reasonable reply to 
that is that the circumstances in the two cases are quite different. In the 
beginning, nothing as yet existed at all; all that was needed, therefore, in 
order to bring all things into being, was that His will to do so should be 
signified. But once man was in existence, and things that were, not things that 
were not, demanded to be healed, it followed as a matter of course that the 
Healer and Savior should align Himself with those things that existed already, 
in order to heal the existing evil. For that reason, therefore, He was made man, 
and used the body as His human instrument. If this were not the fitting way, and 
He willed to use an instrument at all, how otherwise was the Word to come? And 
whence could He take His instrument, save from among those already in existence 
and needing His Godhead through One like themselves? It was not things 
non-existent that needed salvation, for which a bare creative word might have 
sufficed, but man—man already in existence and already in process of corruption 
and ruin. It was natural and right, therefore, for the Word to use a human 
instrument and by that means unfold Himself to all.</p>
<p id="viii-p9">You must know, moreover, that the corruption which had set in was not 
external to the body but established within it. The need, therefore, was that 
life should cleave to it in corruption's place, so that, just as death was 
brought into being in the body, life also might be engendered in it. If death 
had been exterior to the body, life might fittingly have been the same. But if 
death was within the body, woven into its very substance and dominating it as 
though completely one with it, the need was for Life to be woven into it 
instead, so that the body by thus enduing itself with life might cast corruption 
off. Suppose the Word had come outside the body instead of in it, He would, of 
course, have defeated death, because death is powerless against the Life. But 
the corruption inherent in the body would have remained in it none the less. 
Naturally, therefore, the Savior assumed a body for Himself, in order that the 
body, being interwoven as it were with life, should no longer remain a mortal 
thing, in thrall to death, but as endued with immortality and risen from death, 
should thenceforth remain immortal. For once having put on corruption, it could 
not rise, unless it put on life instead; and besides this, death of its very 
nature could not appear otherwise than in a body. Therefore He put on a body, so 
that in the body He might find death and blot it out. And, indeed, how could the 
Lord have been proved to be the Life at all, had He not endued with life that 
which was subject to death? Take an illustration. Stubble is a substance 
naturally destructible by fire; and it still remains stubble, fearing the menace 
of fire which has the natural property of consuming it, even if fire is kept 
away from it, so that it is not actually burnt. But suppose that, instead of 
merely keeping the fire from it somebody soaks the stubble with a quantity of 
asbestos, the substance which is said to be the antidote to fire. Then the 
stubble no longer fears the fire, because it has put on that which fire cannot 
touch, and therefore it is safe. It is just the same with regard to the body and 
death. Had death been kept from it by a mere command, it would still have 
remained mortal and corruptible, according to its nature. To prevent this, it 
put on the incorporeal Word of God, and therefore fears neither death nor 
corruption any more, for it is clad with Life as with a garment and in it 
corruption is clean done away.</p>
<p id="viii-p10"><b>(45)</b> The Word of God thus acted consistently in 
assuming a body and using a human instrument to vitalize the body. He was 
consistent in working through man to reveal Himself everywhere, as well as 
through the other parts of His creation, so that nothing was left void of His 
Divinity and knowledge. For I take up now the point I made before, namely that 
the Savior did this in order that He might fill all things everywhere with the 
knowledge of Himself, just as they are already filled with His presence, even as 
the Divine Scripture says, 
"The whole universe was filled with the knowledge of 
the Lord."<note n="63" id="viii-p10.1"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 11:9" id="viii-p10.2" parsed="|Isa|11|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.11.9">Isaiah xi. 9</scripRef></note> 
If a man looks up to heaven he sees there His ordering; but if he 
cannot look so high as heaven, but only so far as men, through His works he sees 
His power, incomparable with human might, and learns from them that He alone 
among men is God the Word. Or, if a man has gone astray among demons and is in 
fear of them, he may see this Man drive them out and judge therefrom that He is 
indeed their Master. Again, if a man has been immersed in the element of water 
and thinks that it is God—as indeed the Egyptians do worship water—he may see 
its very nature changed by Him and learn that the Lord is Creator of all. And if 
a man has gone down even to Hades, and stands awestruck before the heroes who 
have descended thither, regarding them as gods, still he may see the fact of 
Christ's resurrection and His victory over death, and reason from it that, of 
all these, He alone is very Lord and God.</p>
<p id="viii-p11">For the Lord touched all parts of creation, and freed and undeceived them all 
from every deceit. As St. Paul says, 
"Having put off from Himself the principalities and the 
powers, He triumphed on the cross,"<note n="64" id="viii-p11.1"><scripRef passage="Colossians 2:15" id="viii-p11.2" parsed="|Col|2|15|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Col.2.15">Col. ii. 15</scripRef></note> 

so that no one could possibly be any longer deceived, but 
everywhere might find the very Word of God. For thus man, enclosed on every side 
by the works of creation and everywhere—in heaven, in Hades, in men and on the 
earth, beholding the unfolded Godhead of the Word, is no longer deceived 
concerning God, but worships Christ alone, and through Him rightly knows the 
Father.</p>
<p id="viii-p12">On these grounds, then, of reason and of principle, we will fairly silence 
the Gentiles in their turn. But if they think these arguments insufficient to 
confute them, we will go on in the next chapter to prove our point from facts.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 8. Refutation of the Gentiles—Continued" progress="81.06%" prev="viii" next="x" id="ix">
<h2 id="ix-p0.1">Chapter 8</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="ix-p1"><i>Refutation of the Gentiles—continued</i></p>

<p id="ix-p2"><b>(46)</b> When did people begin to abandon the worship of 
idols, unless it were since the very Word of God came among men? When have 
oracles ceased and become void of meaning, among the Greeks and everywhere, 
except since the Savior has revealed Himself on earth? When did those whom the 
poets call gods and heroes begin to be adjudged as mere mortals, except when the 
Lord took the spoils of death and preserved incorruptible the body He had taken, 
raising it from among the dead? Or when did the deceitfulness and madness of 
demons fall under contempt, save when the Word, the Power of God, the Master of 
all these as well, condescended on account of the weakness of mankind and 
appeared on earth? When did the practice and theory of magic begin to be spurned 
under foot, if not at the manifestation of the Divine Word to men? In a word, 
when did the wisdom of the Greeks become foolish, save when the true Wisdom of 
God revealed Himself on earth? In old times the whole world and every place in 
it was led astray by the worship of idols, and men thought the idols were the 
only gods that were. But now all over the world men are forsaking the fear of 
idols and taking refuge with Christ; and by worshipping Him as God they come 
through Him to know the Father also, Whom formerly they did not know. The 
amazing thing, moreover, is this. The objects of worship formerly were varied 
and countless; each place had its own idol and the so-called god of one place 
could not pass over to another in order to persuade the people there to worship 
him, but was barely reverenced even by his own. Indeed no! Nobody worshipped his 
neighbor's god, but every man had his own idol and thought that it was lord of 
all. But now Christ alone is worshipped, as One and the Same among all peoples 
everywhere; and what the feebleness of idols could not do, namely, convince even 
those dwelling close at hand, He has effected. He has persuaded not only those 
close at hand, but literally the entire world to worship one and the same Lord 
and through Him the Father.</p>
<p id="ix-p3"><b>(47)</b> Again, in former times every place was full of the 
fraud of the oracles, and the utterances of those at Delphi and Dordona and in 
Boeotia and Lycia and Libya and Egypt and those of the Kabiri and the Pythoness 
were considered marvelous by the minds of men. But now, since Christ has been 
proclaimed everywhere, their madness too has ceased, and there is no one left 
among them to give oracles at all. Then, too, demons used to deceive men's minds 
by taking up their abode in springs or rivers or trees or stones and imposing 
upon simple people by their frauds. But now, since the Divine appearing of the 
Word, all this fantasy has ceased, for by the sign of the cross, if a man will 
but use it, he drives out their deceits. Again, people used to regard as gods 
those who are mentioned in the poets—Zeus and Kronos and Apollo and the 
heroes, and in worshipping them they went astray. But now that the Savior has 
appeared among men, those others have been exposed as mortal men, and Christ 
alone is recognized as true God, Word of God, God Himself. And what is one to 
say about the magic that they think so marvelous? Before the sojourn of the 
Word, it was strong and active among Egyptians and Chaldeans and Indians and 
filled all who saw it with terror and astonishment. But by the coming of the 
Truth and the manifestation of the Word it too has been confuted and entirely 
destroyed. As to Greek wisdom, however, and the philosophers' noisy talk, I 
really think no one requires argument from us; for the amazing fact is patent to 
all that, for all that they had written so much, the Greeks failed to convince 
even a few from their own neighborhood in regard to immortality and the virtuous 
ordering of life. Christ alone, using common speech and through the agency of 
men not clever with their tongues, has convinced whole assemblies of people all 
the world over to despise death, and to take heed to the things that do not die, 
to look past the things of time and gaze on things eternal, to think nothing of 
earthly glory and to aspire only to immortality.</p>
<p id="ix-p4"><b>(48)</b> These things which we have said are no mere words: 
they are attested by actual experience. Anyone who 
likes may see the proof of glory in the virgins of Christ, and in the young 
men who practice chastity as part of their religion, and in the assurance of 
immortality in so great and glad a company<note n="65" id="ix-p4.1">Literally, "so great a chorus . . .". "choros" being properly a band of dancers and singers.</note> 
of martyrs. Anyone, too, may put what we have said to the proof of 
experience in another way. In the very presence of the fraud of demons and the 
imposture of the oracles and the wonders of magic, let him use the sign of the 
cross which they all mock at, and but speak the Name of Christ, and he shall see 
how through Him demons are routed, oracles cease, and all magic and witchcraft 
is confounded.</p>
<p id="ix-p5">Who, then, is this Christ and how great is He, Who by His Name and presence 
overshadows and confounds all things on every side, Who alone is strong against 
all and has filled the whole world with His teaching? Let the Greeks tell us, 
who mock at Him without stint or shame. If He is a man, how is it that one man 
has proved stronger than all those whom they themselves regard as gods, and by 
His own power has shown them to be nothing? If they call Him a magician, how is 
it that by a magician all magic is destroyed, instead of being rendered strong? 
Had He conquered certain magicians or proved Himself superior to one of them 
only, they might reasonably think that He excelled the rest only by His greater 
skill. But the fact is that His cross has vanquished all magic entirely and has 
conquered the very name of it. Obviously, therefore, the Savior is no magician, 
for the very demons whom the magicians invoke flee from Him as from their 
Master. Who is He, then? Let the Greeks tell us, whose only serious pursuit is 
mockery! Perhaps they will say that He, too, is a demon, and that is why He 
prevailed. But even so the laugh is still on our side. for we can confute them 
by the same proofs as before. How could He be a demon, Who drives demons out? If 
it were only certain ones that He drove out, then they might reasonably think 
that He prevailed against them through the power of their Chief, as the Jews, 
wishing to insult Him, actually said. But since the fact is, here again, that at 
the mere naming of His Name all madness of the demons is rooted out and put to 
flight, obviously the Greeks are wrong here, too, and our Lord and Savior Christ 
is not, as they maintain, some demonic power.</p>
<p id="ix-p6">If, then, the Savior is neither a mere man nor a magician, nor one of the 
demons, but has by His Godhead confounded and overshadowed the opinions of the 
poets and the delusion of the demons and the wisdom of the Greeks, it must be 
manifest and will be owned by all that He is in truth Son of God, Existent Word 
and Wisdom and Power of the Father. This is the reason why His works are no mere 
human works, but, both intrinsically and by comparison with those of men, are 
recognized as being superhuman and truly the works of God.</p>
<p id="ix-p7"><b>(49)</b> What man that ever was, for instance, formed a 
body for himself from a virgin only? Or what man ever healed so many diseases as 
the common Lord of all? Who restored that which was lacking in man's nature or 
made one blind from birth to see? Aesculapius was deified by the Greeks because 
he practiced the art of healing and discovered herbs as remedies for bodily 
diseases, not, of course, forming them himself out of the earth, but finding 
them out by the study of nature. But what is that in comparison with what the 
Savior did when, instead of just healing a wound, He both fashioned essential 
being and restored to health the thing that He had formed? Hercules, too, is 
worshipped as a god by the Greeks because he fought against other men and 
destroyed wild animals by craft. But what is that to what the Word did, in 
driving away from men diseases and demons and even death itself? Dionysus is 
worshipped among them, because he taught men drunkenness; yet they ridicule the 
true Savior and Lord of all, Who taught men temperance.</p>
<p id="ix-p8">That, however, is enough on this point. What will they say to the other 
marvels of His Godhead? At what man's death was the sun darkened and the earth 
shaken? Why, even to this day men are dying, and they did so also before that 
time. When did any such marvels happen in their case? Now shall we pass over the 
deeds done in His earthly body and mention those after His resurrection? Has any 
man's teaching, in any place or at any time, ever prevailed everywhere as one 
and the same, from one end of the earth to the other, so that his worship has 
fairly flown through every land? Again, if, as they say, Christ is man only and 
not God the Word, why do not the gods of the Greeks prevent His entering their 
domains? Or why, on the other hand, does the Word Himself dwelling in our midst 
make an end of their worship by His teaching and put their fraud to shame?</p>
<p id="ix-p9"><b>(50)</b> Many before Him have been kings and tyrants of the 
earth, history tells also of many among the Chaldeans and Egyptians and Indians 
who were wise men and magicians. But which of those, I do not say after his 
death, but while yet in this life, was ever able so far to prevail as to fill 
the whole world with his teaching and retrieve so great a multitude from the 
craven fear of idols, as our Savior has won over from idols to Himself? The 
Greek philosophers have compiled many works with persuasiveness and much skill 
in words; but what fruit have they to show for this such as has the cross of 
Christ? Their wise thoughts were persuasive enough until they died; yet even in 
their life-time their seeming influence was counterbalanced by their rivalry 
with one another, for they were a jealous company and declaimed against each 
other. But the Word of God, by strangest paradox, teaching in meaner language, 
has put the choicest sophists in the shade, and by confounding their teachings 
and drawing all men to Himself He has filled His own assemblies. Moreover, and 
this is the marvelous thing by going down as Man to death He has confounded all 
the sounding utterances of the wise men about the idols. For whose death ever 
drove out demons, or whose death did ever demons fear, save that of Christ? For 
where the Savior is named, there every demon is driven out. Again, who has ever 
so rid men of their natural passions that fornicators become chaste and 
murderers no longer wield the sword and those who formerly were craven cowards 
boldly play the man? In a word, what persuaded the barbarians and heathen folk 
in every place to drop their madness and give heed to peace, save the faith of 
Christ and the sign of the cross? What other things have given men such certain 
faith in immortality as have the cross of Christ and the resurrection of His 
body? The Greeks told all sorts of false tales, but they could never pretend 
that their idols rose again from death: indeed it never entered their heads that 
a body could exist again after death at all. And one would be particularly ready 
to listen to them on this point, because by these opinions they have exposed the 
weakness of their own idolatry, at the same time yielding to Christ the 
possibility of bodily resurrection, so that by that means He might be recognized 
by all as Son of God.</p>
<p id="ix-p10"><b>(51)</b> Again, who among men, either after his death or 
while yet living, taught about virginity and did not account this virtue 
impossible for human beings? But Christ our Savior and King of all has so 
prevailed with His teaching on this subject that even children not yet of lawful 
age promise that virginity which transcends the law. And who among men has ever 
been able to penetrate even to Scythians and Ethiopians, or Parthians or 
Armenians or those who are said to live beyond Hyrcania, or even the Egyptians 
and Chaldeans, people who give heed to magic and are more than naturally 
enslaved by the fear of demons and savage in their habits, and to preach at all 
about virtue and self-control and against the worshipping of idols, as has the 
Lord of all, the Power of God, our Lord Jesus Christ? Yet He not only preached 
through His own disciples, but also wrought so persuasively on men's 
understanding that, laying aside their savage habits and forsaking the worship 
of their ancestral gods, they learnt to know Him and through Him to worship the 
Father. While they were yet idolaters, the Greeks and Barbarians were always at 
war with each other, and were even cruel to their own kith and kin. Nobody could 
travel by land or sea at all unless he was armed with swords, because of their 
irreconcilable quarrels with each other. Indeed, the whole course of their life 
was carried on with the weapons, and the sword with them replaced the staff and 
was the mainstay of all aid. All this time, as I said before, they were serving 
idols and offering sacrifices to demons, and for all the superstitious awe that 
accompanied this idol worship, nothing could wean them from that warlike spirit. 
But, strange to relate, since they came over to the school of Christ, as men 
moved with real compunction they have laid aside their murderous cruelty and are 
war-minded no more. On the contrary, all is peace among them and nothing remains 
save desire for friendship.</p>
<p id="ix-p11"><b>(52)</b> Who, then, is He Who has done these things and has 
united in peace those who hated each other, save the beloved Son of the Father, 
the common Savior of all, Jesus Christ, Who by His own love underwent all things 
for our salvation? Even from the beginning, moreover, this peace that He was to 
administer was foretold, for Scripture says, 
"They shall beat their swords into ploughshares and 
their spears into sickles, and nation shall not take sword against nation, 
neither shall they learn any more to wage war."<note n="66" id="ix-p11.1"><scripRef passage="Isaiah 2:4" id="ix-p11.2" parsed="|Isa|2|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.2.4">Isaiah ii. 4</scripRef></note> 

Nor is this by any means incredible.</p>
<p id="ix-p12">The barbarians of the present day are naturally savage in their habits, and 
as long as they sacrifice to their idols they rage furiously against each other 
and cannot bear to be a single hour without weapons. But when they hear the 
teaching of Christ, forthwith they turn from fighting to farming, and instead of 
arming themselves with swords extend their hands in prayer. In a word, instead 
of fighting each other, they take up arms against the devil and the demons, and 
overcome them by their selfcommand and integrity of soul. These facts are proof 
of the Godhead of the Savior, for He has taught men what they could never learn 
among the idols. It is also no small exposure of the weakness and nothingness of 
demons and idols, for it was because they knew their own weakness that the 
demons were always setting men to fight each other, fearing lest, if they ceased 
from mutual strife, they would turn to attack the demons themselves. For in 
truth the disciples of Christ, instead of fighting each other, stand arrayed 
against demons by their habits and virtuous actions, and chase them away and 
mock at their captain the devil. Even in youth they are chaste, they endure in 
times of testing and persevere in toils. When they are insulted, they are 
patient, when robbed they make light of it, and, marvelous to relate, they make 
light even of death itself, and become martyrs of Christ.</p>
<p id="ix-p13"><b>(53)</b> And here is another proof of the Godhead of the 
Savior, which is indeed utterly amazing. What mere man or magician or tyrant or 
king was ever able by himself to do so much? Did anyone ever fight against the 
whole system of idol-worship and the whole host of demons and all magic and all 
the wisdom of the Greeks, at a time when all of these were strong and 
flourishing and taking everybody in, as did our Lord, the very Word of God? Yet 
He is even now invisibly exposing every man's error, and single-handed is 
carrying off all men from them all, so that those who used to worship idols now 
tread them under foot, reputed magicians burn their books and the wise prefer to 
all studies the interpretation of the gospels. They are deserting those whom 
formerly they worshipped, they worship and confess as Christ and God Him Whom 
they used to ridicule as crucified. Their so-called gods are routed by the sign 
of the cross, and the crucified Savior is proclaimed in all the world as God and 
Son of God. Moreover, the gods worshipped among the Greeks are now falling into 
disrepute among them on account of the disgraceful things they did, for those 
who receive the teaching of Christ are more chaste in life than they. If these, 
and the like of them, are human works, let anyone who will show us similar ones 
done by men in former time, and so convince us. But if they are shown to be, and 
are the works not of men but of God, why are the unbelievers so irreligious as 
not to recognize the Master Who did them? They are afflicted as a man would be 
who failed to recognize God the Artificer through the works of creation. For 
surely if they had recognized His Godhead through His power over the universe, 
they would recognize also that the bodily works of Christ are not human, but are 
those of the Savior of all, the Word of God. And had they recognized this, as 
Paul says, "They would not have crucified the Lord of 
glory."<note n="67" id="ix-p13.1"><scripRef passage="Corinthians 2:8" id="ix-p13.2">Cor. ii. 8</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="ix-p14"><b>(54)</b> As, then, he who desires to see God Who by nature 
is invisible and not to be beheld, may yet perceive and know Him through His 
works, so too let him who does not see Christ with his understanding at least 
consider Him in His bodily works and test whether they be of man or God. If they 
be of man, then let him scoff; but if they be of God, let him not mock at things 
which are no fit subject for scorn, but rather let him recognize the fact and 
marvel that things divine have been revealed to us by such humble means, that 
through death deathlessness has been made known to us, and through the 
Incarnation of the Word the Mind whence all things proceed has been declared, 
and its Agent and Ordainer, the Word of God Himself. He, indeed, assumed 
humanity that we might become God. He manifested Himself by means of a body in 
order that we might perceive the Mind of the unseen Father. He endured shame 
from men that we might inherit immortality. He Himself was unhurt by this, for 
He is impassable and incorruptible; but by His own impassability He kept and 
healed the suffering men on whose account He thus endured. In short, such and so 
many are the Savior's achievements that follow from His Incarnation, that to try 
to number them is like gazing at the open sea and trying to count the waves. One 
cannot see all the waves with one's eyes, for when one tries to do so those that 
are following on baffle one's senses. Even so, when one wants to take in all the 
achievements of Christ in the body, one cannot do so, even by reckoning them up, 
for the things that transcend one's thought are always more than those one 
thinks that one has grasped.</p>
<p id="ix-p15">As we cannot speak adequately about even a part of His work, therefore, it 
will be better for us not to speak about it as a whole. So we will mention but 
one thing more, and then leave the whole for you to marvel at. For, indeed, 
everything about it is marvelous, and wherever a man turns his gaze he sees the 
Godhead of the Word and is smitten with awe.</p>
<p id="ix-p16"><b>(55)</b> The substance of what we have said so far may be 
summarized as follows. Since the Savior came to dwell among us, not only does 
idolatry no longer increase, but it is getting less and gradually ceasing to be. 
Similarly, not only does the wisdom of the Greeks no longer make any progress, 
but that which used to be is disappearing. And demons, so far from continuing to 
impose on people by their deceits and oracle-givings and sorceries, are routed 
by the sign of the cross if they so much as try. On the other hand, while 
idolatry and everything else that opposes the faith of Christ is daily dwindling 
and weakening and falling, see, the Savior's teaching is increasing everywhere! 
Worship, then, the Savior "Who is above all" and mighty, even 
God the Word, and condemn those who are being defeated and made to disappear by 
Him. When the sun has come, darkness prevails no longer; any of it that may be 
left anywhere is driven away. So also, now that the Divine epiphany of the Word 
of God has taken place, the darkness of idols prevails no more, and all parts of 
the world in every direction are enlightened by His teaching. Similarly, if a 
king be reigning somewhere, but stays in his own house and does not let himself 
be seen, it often happens that some insubordinate fellows, taking advantage of 
his retirement, will have themselves proclaimed in his stead; and each of them, 
being invested with the semblance of kingship, misleads the simple who, because 
they cannot enter the palace and see the real king, are led astray by just 
hearing a king named. When the real king emerges, however, and appears to view, 
things stand differently. The insubordinate impostors are shown up by his 
presence, and men, seeing the real king, forsake those who previously misled 
them. In the same way the demons used formerly to impose on men, investing 
themselves with the honor due to God. But since the Word of God has been 
manifested in a body, and has made known to us His own Father, the fraud of the 
demons is stopped and made to disappear; and men, turning their eyes to the true 
God, Word of the Father, forsake the idols and come to know the true God.</p>
<p id="ix-p17">Now this is proof that Christ is God, the Word and Power of God. For whereas 
human things cease and the fact of Christ remains, it is clear to all that the 
things which cease are temporary, but that He Who remains is God and very Son of 
God, the sole-begotten Word.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" title="Chapter 9. Conclusion" progress="97.67%" prev="ix" next="xi" id="x">
<h2 id="x-p0.1">Chapter 9</h2>
<p style="margin-left:-.25in; margin-bottom:24pt; text-align:center; font-size:large; font-weight:bold" id="x-p1"><i>Conclusion</i></p>

<p id="x-p2"><b>(56)</b> Here, then, Macarius, is our offering to you who 
love Christ, a brief statement of the faith of Christ and of the manifestation 
of His Godhead to us. This will give you a beginning, and you must go on to 
prove its truth by the study of the Scriptures. They were written and inspired 
by God; and we, who have learned from inspired teachers who read the Scriptures 
and became martyrs for the Godhead of Christ, make further contribution to your 
eagerness to learn. From the Scriptures you will learn also of His second 
manifestation to us, glorious and divine indeed, when He shall come not in 
lowliness but in His proper glory, no longer in humiliation but in majesty, no 
longer to suffer but to bestow on us all the fruit of His cross—the 
resurrection and incorruptibility. No longer will He then be judged, but rather 
will Himself be Judge, judging each and all according to their deeds done in the 
body, whether good or ill. Then for the good is laid up the heavenly kingdom, 
but for those that practice evil outer darkness and the eternal fire. So also 
the Lord Himself says, 
"I say unto you, hereafter ye shall see the Son of Man 
seated on the right hand of power, coming on the clouds of heaven in the glory 
of the Father."<note n="68" id="x-p2.1"><scripRef passage="Matthew 26:64" id="x-p2.2" parsed="|Matt|26|64|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.26.64">Matt.xxvi. 64</scripRef></note> 

For that Day we have one of His own sayings to prepare us, 
"Get ready and watch, for ye know not the hour in which 
He cometh"<note n="69" id="x-p2.3"><scripRef passage="Matthew 24:42" id="x-p2.4" parsed="|Matt|24|42|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.24.42">Matt. xxiv. 42</scripRef></note> 
And blessed Paul says, 
"We must all stand before the judgment seat of Christ, 
that each one may receive according as he practiced in the body, whether good 
or ill."<note n="70" id="x-p2.5"><scripRef passage="2 Corinthians 5:10" id="x-p2.6" parsed="|2Cor|5|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.5.10">2 Cor.  v. 10</scripRef></note></p>
<p id="x-p3"><b>(57)</b> But for the searching and right understanding of 
the Scriptures there is need of a good life and a pure soul, and for Christian 
virtue to guide the mind to grasp, so far as human nature can, the truth 
concerning God the Word. One cannot possibly understand the teaching of the 
saints unless one has a pure mind and is trying to imitate their life. Anyone 
who wants to look at sunlight naturally wipes his eye clear first, in order to 
make, at any rate, some approximation to the purity of that on which he looks; 
and a person wishing to see a city or country goes to the place in order to do 
so. Similarly, anyone who wishes to understand the mind of the sacred writers 
must first cleanse his own life, and approach the saints by copying their deeds. 
Thus united to them in the fellowship of life, he will both understand the 
things revealed to them by God and, thenceforth escaping the peril that 
threatens sinners in the judgment, will receive that which is laid up for the 
saints in the kingdom of heaven. Of that reward it is written: 
"Eye hath not seen nor ear heard, neither hath entered 
into the heart of man the things that God has prepared"<note n="71" id="x-p3.1"><scripRef passage="1 Corinthians 2:9" id="x-p3.2" parsed="|1Cor|2|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.2.9">1 Cor. ii. 9</scripRef></note>  
for them that live a godly life and love the God and Father in 
Christ Jesus our Lord, through Whom and with Whom be to the Father Himself, with 
the Son Himself, in the Holy Spirit, honor and might and glory to ages of ages. 
Amen.</p>

</div1>


<div1 title="Indexes" prev="x" next="xi.i" id="xi">
<h1 id="xi-p0.1">Indexes</h1>

<div2 title="Index of Scripture References" prev="xi" next="toc" id="xi.i">
  <h2 id="xi.i-p0.1">Index of Scripture References</h2>
  <insertIndex type="scripRef" id="xi.i-p0.2" />



<div class="Index">
<p class="bbook">Genesis</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=1#ii-p7.2">1:1</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=6#ii-p7.7">2:16</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=49&amp;scrV=10#vii-p11.2">49:10</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Numbers</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=24&amp;scrV=5#vii-p3.6">24:5-7</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=24&amp;scrV=17#vii-p3.4">24:17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Deuteronomy</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Deut&amp;scrCh=28&amp;scrV=66#vii-p5.2">28:66</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Psalms</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=16#vii-p5.6">22:16-18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=24&amp;scrV=7#v-p12.16">24:7</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=82&amp;scrV=6#ii-p8.4">82:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=107&amp;scrV=20#vii-p11.8">107:20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=118&amp;scrV=27#vii-p11.6">118:27</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Isaiah</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=4#ix-p11.2">2:4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=14#vii-p3.2">7:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=4#vii-p3.8">8:4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=9#viii-p10.2">11:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=10#vii-p5.8">11:10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=1#vii-p3.10">19:1</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=35&amp;scrV=3#vii-p9.4">35:3-6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=53&amp;scrV=3#vii-p4.2">53:3-5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=53&amp;scrV=6#vii-p4.4">53:6-8</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=53&amp;scrV=8#vii-p4.6">53:8-10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=63&amp;scrV=9#vii-p11.10">63:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=65&amp;scrV=1#vii-p9.2">65:1-2</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Jeremiah</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=19#vii-p5.4">11:19</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Daniel</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Dan&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=24#vii-p10.3">9:24-25</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Hosea</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Hos&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=1#vii-p3.12">11:1</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Matthew</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=13#vii-p11.4">11:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=4#ii-p6.2">19:4-6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=24&amp;scrV=42#x-p2.4">24:42</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=26&amp;scrV=64#x-p2.2">26:64</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Mark</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=7#vi-p10.3">5:7</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Luke</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=34#vi-p10.2">4:34</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=18#v-p12.14">10:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=10#iv-p9.2">19:10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=10#iv-p11.4">19:10</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">John</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=3#ii-p6.4">1:3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=3#iv-p9.4">3:3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=32#vii-p9.6">9:32-33</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=37#iv-p15.2">10:37-38</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=32#v-p12.8">12:32</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Acts</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=17&amp;scrV=28#viii-p5.2">17:28</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Romans</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=25#iv-p3.2">1:25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=26#ii-p9.4">1:26</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Corinthians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=21#iv-p11.2">1:21</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=9#x-p3.2">2:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=21#iii-p6.8">15:21</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=53#v-p6.2">15:53</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=55#vi-p4.2">15:55</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">2 Corinthians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=10#x-p2.6">5:10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=14#iii-p6.2">5:14</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Galatians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gal&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=13#v-p12.2">3:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gal&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=13#v-p12.4">3:13</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Ephesians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=2#v-p12.10">2:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=14#v-p12.6">2:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=17#iv-p12.2">3:17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Colossians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Col&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=15#viii-p11.2">2:15</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Timothy</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Tim&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=15#iii-p6.10">6:15</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Hebrews</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=9#iii-p6.4">2:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=14#iii-p6.6">2:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=14#v-p5.2">2:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=12#vi-p8.2">4:12</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=20#v-p12.12">10:20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=3#ii-p7.5">11:3</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Wisdom of Solomon</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Wis&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=23#ii-p9.2">2:23</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Wis&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=18#ii-p8.2">6:18</a> </p>
</div>




</div2>
</div1>




</ThML.body>
</ThML>
