<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ThML PUBLIC 
    "-//CCEL/DTD Theological Markup Language//EN"
    "http://www.ccel.org/dtd/ThML10.dtd">
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml"
    href="http://www.ccel.org/ss/thml.html.xsl" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl"
    href="http://www.ccel.org/ss/thml.html.xsl" ?>
-->
    
<!-- Copyright Christian Classics Ethereal Library -->
<ThML>
<ThML.head>

<generalInfo>
  <description><i>Grace Abounding To the Chief of Sinners</i> is 
John Bunyan's spiritual autobiography.  In it he tells of 
his conversion and struggle with faith.  He wrote it while he was 
imprisoned for preaching without a license.  His main issue was a kind 
of "spiritual obsessive compulsive disorder" as one reviewer puts it.  
Bunyan was constantly concerned about the state of his salvation and 
whether God deemed him worthy enough for eternal life.  This story 
communicates the author's anguish over his sin, his confession, and the 
life-changing impact of God's saving grace.  Bunyan's spiritual 
struggles will remind readers that even the great minds of faith had 
issues with belief, and his personal testimony will encourage anyone who 
is doubting the status of their salvation.<br /><br />Abby Zwart<br />CCEL 
Staff Writer 
</description>
  <firstPublished />
  <pubHistory />
  <comments />

</generalInfo>

<printSourceInfo>
  <published />
</printSourceInfo>

<electronicEdInfo>
  <publisherID>ccel</publisherID>
  <authorID>bunyan</authorID>
  <bookID>grace</bookID>
  <workID>grace</workID>
  <bkgID>grace_abounding_(bunyan)</bkgID>
  <version />
  <series />

  <DC>
    <DC.Title>Grace Abounding</DC.Title>
    <DC.Creator sub="Author" scheme="short-form">John Bunyan</DC.Creator>
    <DC.Creator sub="Author" scheme="file-as">Bunyan, John</DC.Creator>
    <DC.Publisher>Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library</DC.Publisher>
    <DC.Subject scheme="LCCN">BS2440.B7</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="lcsh1">The Bible</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="lcsh2">New Testament</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="lcsh3">Works about the New Testament</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="lcsh4">Biography</DC.Subject>
    <DC.Subject scheme="ccel">All; Biography; Biotarget=bunyan; </DC.Subject>
    <DC.Date sub="Created">2000-07-09</DC.Date>
    <DC.Type>Text.Monograph</DC.Type>
    <DC.Format scheme="IMT">text/html</DC.Format>
    <DC.Identifier scheme="URL">/ccel/bunyan/grace.html</DC.Identifier>
    <DC.Source />
    <DC.Source scheme="URL" />
    <DC.Language scheme="ISO639-3">eng</DC.Language>
    <DC.Rights />
  </DC>

</electronicEdInfo>







<style type="text/css">
p.normal	{ text-indent:0in; margin-top:9pt; text-align:justify }
</style>

<style type="text/xcss">
<selector element="p" class="normal">
  <property name="text-indent" value="0in" />
  <property name="margin-top" value="9pt" />
  <property name="text-align" value="justify" />
</selector>
</style>


</ThML.head>


	<ThML.body>

<div1 title="Title Page" progress="0.23%" prev="toc" next="ii" id="i">
<h1 id="i-p0.1">Grace Abounding</h1>
<h1 id="i-p0.2">To The Chief of Sinners</h1>
<h3 id="i-p0.3">Or,</h3>
<h3 id="i-p0.4">A Brief Relation of the Exceeding Mercy of God in Christ to His Poor Servant</h3>
<h3 id="i-p0.5">By</h3>
<h2 id="i-p0.6">John Bunyan</h2>

</div1>

<div1 title="Publisher’s Foreward" progress="0.24%" prev="i" next="iii" id="ii">
<h2 id="ii-p0.1">PUBLISHER’S FOREWORD </h2>
<p class="normal" id="ii-p1">John Bunyan was born at Elstow, near Bedford, England, sometime in the fall of 
1628, the first of three children born to Thomas and Margaret Bunyan. The parish 
register indicates that he was baptized on November 30, 1628.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p2">In Grace Abounding Bunyan describes his descent as “of a low and inconsiderable 
generation.” He had particular disdain for his father’s house; to him it was “of 
a rank that is meanest and most despised of all the families in the land.”</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p3">Sir Walter Scott thought John Bunyan was of gypsy descent, because his father 
was a traveling tinker, a mender of pots and pans. But historians view the occupation 
as somewhat like that of “village blacksmith.” The Bunyans were not homeless; they 
were landowners, but of peasant stock.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p4">Bunyan’s schooling was of brief duration, and it wasn’t long before he was assisting 
his father and learning the trade himself. On his sixteenth birthday Bunyan joined 
Cromwell’s New Model Army, introducing him to the Puritan movement. After this military 
stint, he settled down as a tinker (“brazier”) and married at the age of twenty.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p5">In 1653 Bunyan joined the Puritan Free Church in Bedford, and in 1657 he took 
on his first assignment as a “field preacher.” At this time there were scores of 
men, most with little education, who were preaching to Nonconformist audiences throughout 
England. With the restoration of Charles II to the throne, these preachers were 
suspect and subject to arrest. Refusing to refrain from preaching, Bunyan was arrested 
in 1660 and imprisoned for more than eleven years.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p6">Grace Abounding to the Chief of Sinners, written during this imprisonment, is 
the spiritual autobiography of Bunyan, the traveling tinker who became the eminent 
preacher and author. It is in the genre of Augustine’s Confessions and Thomas a 
Kempis’s Imitation of Christ. It is not a detailed account of Bunyan’s early life, 
for it tells us very little of his youth, education, military experiences, and marriages.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p7">Written in 1666, Grace Abounding chronicles Bunyan’s spiritual journey from a 
profane life filled with cursing, blasphemy, and Sabbath desecration to a new creation 
in Christ Jesus. Some commentators on Bunyan’s life and work are of the opinion 
that Bunyan wrote too disparagingly of his early life. George Offor, editor of a 
three volume compilation of Bunyan’s works, observes:</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p8">A great difference of opinion has been expressed by learned men as to whether 
Bunyan’s account of himself is to be understood literally, as it respects his bad 
conduct before his conversion. or whether he views himself through a glass, by which 
his evil habits are magnified. No one can doubt his perfect honesty. He plainly 
narrates his bad, as well as his redeeming qualities; nor does his narrative appear 
to be exaggerated.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p9">Grace Abounding is an autobiography that begins with guilt and despair and ends 
with a heart “full of comfort,” a thankful heart for “grace abounding.”</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p10">Those who have read both Grace Abounding and The Pilgrim’s Progress will realize 
that The Pilgrim’s Progress, in substantial measure, is the same life as that described 
in Grace Abounding, but in allegory rather than straightforward narrative. George 
Offor makes this point when he quotes a Dr. Cheever:</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p11">As you read the “Grace Abounding”, you are ready to say at every step, Here is 
the future author of the “Pilgrim’s Progress”. It is as if you stood beside some 
great sculptor, and watched every movement of the chisel, having seen his design; 
so that at every blow some new trait of beauty in the future comes clearly into 
view.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p12">Ernest W. Bacon, in a recent biography based on the latest historical research 
makes the same point:</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p13">The experiences he [Bunyan] records in Grace Abounding are seen in the characters 
of The Pilgrim’s Progress, and there is little doubt that he could not have written 
the great allegory had he not experienced God’s saving mercy recounted in the autobiography. 
It has an undying vitality and perpetual youth about it, is a record of Puritan 
experience unsurpassed, and a spiritual stimulus of great value.</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p14">The importance of Grace Abounding is summed up by Hugh Martin:</p>

<p class="normal" id="ii-p15">Grace Abounding is among the greatest stories of God’s dealings with the human 
soul—to be put on the shelf beside such treasures as Augustine’s Confessions, Law’s 
Serious Call, Baxter’s Autobiography, and Wesley’s account of his own spiritual 
travail.</p>

</div1>

<div1 title="A Preface, or Brief Account of the Publishing of This Work" progress="2.28%" prev="ii" next="iv" id="iii">
<h2 id="iii-p0.1">A PREFACE </h2>
<h2 id="iii-p0.2">OR BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE PUBLISHING OF THIS WORK </h2>

<h3 id="iii-p0.3">WRITTEN BY THE AUTHOR THEREOF, AND DEDICATED TO THOSE WHOM GOD HATH COUNTED HIM 
WORTHY TO BEGET TO FAITH, BY HIS MINISTRY IN THE WORD </h3>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p1">CHILDREN, grace be with you, Amen. I being taken from you in presence, and so 
tied up, that I cannot perform that duty that from God doth lie upon me to youward, 
for your further edifying and building up in faith and holiness, etc., yet that 
you may see my soul hath fatherly care and desire after your spiritual and everlasting 
welfare; I now once again, as before, from the top of Shenir and Hermon, so now 
from the lions’ dens, from the mountains of the leopards (<scripRef passage="Song 4:8" id="iii-p1.1" parsed="|Song|4|8|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Song.4.8">S.of Sol. 4.8</scripRef>), do look 
yet after you all, greatly longing to see your safe arrival into the desired haven.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p2">I thank God upon every remembrance of you; and rejoice, even while I stick between 
the teeth of the lions in the wilderness, at the grace, and mercy, and knowledge 
of Christ our Saviour, which God hath bestowed upon you, with abundance of faith 
and love. Your hungerings and thirstings also after further acquaintance with the 
Father, in His Son; your tenderness of heart, your trembling at sin, your sober 
and holy deportment also, before both God and men, is great refreshment to me; ‘For 
ye are my glory and joy’ (<scripRef passage="1Thessalonians 2:20" id="iii-p2.1" parsed="|1Thess|2|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Thess.2.20">1 Thess. 2.20</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p3">I have sent you here enclosed, a drop of that honey, that I have taken out of 
the carcase of a lion (<scripRef passage="Judges 14:5-9" id="iii-p3.1" parsed="|Judg|14|5|14|9" osisRef="Bible:Judg.14.5-Judg.14.9">Judg. 14.5-9</scripRef>). I have eaten thereof myself also, and am 
much refreshed thereby. (Temptations, when we meet them at first, are as the lion 
that roared upon Samson; but if we overcome them, the next time we see them, we 
shall find a nest of honey within them.) The Philistines understand me not. It is 
something of a relation of the work of God upon my own soul, even from the very 
first, till now; wherein you may perceive my castings down, and raisings up; for 
he woundeth, and his hands make whole. It is written in the Scripture (<scripRef passage="Isaiah 38:19" id="iii-p3.2" parsed="|Isa|38|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.38.19">Isa. 38.19</scripRef>), 
‘The father to the children shall make known the truth of God.’ Yea, it was for 
this reason I lay so long at Sinai (<scripRef passage="Deuteronomy 4:10,11" id="iii-p3.3" parsed="|Deut|4|10|4|11" osisRef="Bible:Deut.4.10-Deut.4.11">Deut. 4.10, 11</scripRef>), to see the fire, and the cloud, 
and the darkness, that I might fear the Lord all the days of my life upon earth, 
and tell of his wondrous works to my children (<scripRef passage="Psalm 78:3-5" id="iii-p3.4" parsed="|Ps|78|3|78|5" osisRef="Bible:Ps.78.3-Ps.78.5">Ps. 78.3-5</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p4">Moses (<scripRef passage="Num. 33:1-2" id="iii-p4.1" parsed="|Num|33|1|33|2" osisRef="Bible:Num.33.1-Num.33.2">Num. 33.1, 2</scripRef>) writ of the journeyings of the children of Israel, from 
Egypt to the land of Canaan; and commanded also, that they did remember their forty 
years’ travel in the wilderness. ‘Thou shalt remember all the way which the Lord 
thy God led thee these forty years in the wilderness, to humble thee, and to prove 
thee, to know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keep his commandments, 
or no’ (<scripRef passage="Deuteronomy 8:2" id="iii-p4.2" parsed="|Deut|8|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Deut.8.2">Deut. 8.2</scripRef>). Wherefore this I have endeavoured to do; and not only so, but 
to publish it also; that, if God will, others may be put in remembrance of what 
He hath done for their souls, by reading His work upon me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p5">It is profitable for Christians to be often calling to mind the very beginnings 
of grace with their souls. ‘It is a night to be much observed unto the Lord for 
bringing them out from the land of Egypt: this is that night of the Lord to be observed 
of all the children of Israel in their generations’ (<scripRef passage="Exodus 12:42" id="iii-p5.1" parsed="|Exod|12|42|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Exod.12.42">Ex. 12.42</scripRef>). ‘O my God,’ saith 
David (<scripRef passage="Psalm 42:6" id="iii-p5.2" parsed="|Ps|42|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.42.6">Ps. 42.6</scripRef>), ‘my soul is cast down within me; therefore will I remember thee 
from the land of Jordan, and of the Hermonites, from the hill Mizar.’ He remembered 
also the lion and the bear, when he went to fight with the giant of Gath (<scripRef passage="1Samuel 17:36,37" id="iii-p5.3" parsed="|1Sam|17|36|17|37" osisRef="Bible:1Sam.17.36-1Sam.17.37">I Sam. 
17.36, 37</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p6">It was Paul’s accustomed manner (<scripRef passage="Acts 22:1-30" id="iii-p6.1" parsed="|Acts|22|1|22|30" osisRef="Bible:Acts.22.1-Acts.22.30">Acts 22</scripRef>), and that when tried for his life 
(<scripRef passage="Acts 24:1-27" id="iii-p6.2" parsed="|Acts|24|1|24|27" osisRef="Bible:Acts.24.1-Acts.24.27">Acts 24</scripRef>), ever to open, before his judges, the manner of his conversion: he would 
think of that day, and that hour, in the which he first did meet with grace;<sup>4</sup> for 
he found it support unto him. When God had brought the children of Israel through 
the Red Sea, far into the wilderness, yet they must turn quite about thither again, 
to remember the drowning of their enemies there (<scripRef passage="Numbers 14:25" id="iii-p6.3" parsed="|Num|14|25|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Num.14.25">Num.14.25</scripRef>). For though they sang 
His praise before, yet ‘they soon forgat his works’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 106:11-13" id="iii-p6.4" parsed="|Ps|106|11|106|13" osisRef="Bible:Ps.106.11-Ps.106.13">Ps. 106.11-13</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p7">In this discourse of mine you may see much; much, I say, of the grace of God 
towards me. I thank God I can count it much, for it was above my sins and Satan’s 
temptations too. I can remember my fears, and doubts, and sad months with comfort; 
they are as the head of Goliath in my hand. There was nothing to David like Goliath’s 
sword, even that sword that should have been sheathed in his bowels; for the very 
sight and remembrance of that did preach forth God’s deliverance to him. Oh, the 
remembrance of my great sins, of my great temptations, and of my great fears of 
perishing for ever! They bring afresh into my mind the remembrance of my great help, 
my great support from heaven, and the great grace that God extended to such a wretch 
as I.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p8">My dear children, call to mind the former days, and the years of ancient times: 
remember also your songs in the night; and commune with your own heart (<scripRef passage="Psalm 77:5-12" id="iii-p8.1" parsed="|Ps|77|5|77|12" osisRef="Bible:Ps.77.5-Ps.77.12">Ps. 77.5-12</scripRef>). 
Yea, look diligently, and leave no corner therein unsearched, for there is treasure 
hid, even the treasure of your first and second experience of the grace of God toward 
you. Remember, I say, the word that first laid hold upon you; remember your terrors 
of conscience, and fear of death and hell; remember also your tears and prayers 
to God; yea, how you sighed under every hedge for mercy. Have you never a hill Mizar 
to remember? Have you forgot the close, the milk house, the stable, the barn, and 
the like, where God did visit your soul? Remember also the Word—the Word, I say, 
upon which the Lord hath caused you to hope. If you have sinned against light; if 
you are tempted to blaspheme; if you are down in despair; if you think God fights 
against you; or if heaven is hid from your eyes, remember it was thus with your 
father, but out of them all the Lord delivered me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p9">I could have enlarged much in this my discourse, of my temptations and troubles 
for sin; as also of the merciful kindness and working of God with my soul. I could 
also have stepped into a style much higher than this in which I have here discoursed, 
and could have adorned all things more than here I have seemed to do, but I dare 
not. God did not play in convincing of me, the devil did not play in tempting of 
me, neither did I play when I sunk as into a bottomless pit, when the pangs of hell 
caught hold upon me; wherefore I may not play in my relating of them, but be plain 
and simple, and lay down the thing as it was. He that liketh it, let him receive 
it; and he that does not, let him produce a better. Farewell.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iii-p10">My dear children, the milk and honey are beyond this wilderness, God be merciful 
to you, and grant that you be not slothful to go in to possess the land.</p>

</div1>

<div1 title="Grace Abounding to the Chief of Sinners; Or, a Brief Relation of the Exceeding Mercy of God in Christ, to His Poor Servant John Bunyan" progress="5.39%" prev="iii" next="v" id="iv">

<h2 id="iv-p0.1">GRACE ABOUNDING TO THE CHIEF OF SINNERS; </h2>

<h3 id="iv-p0.2">OR, A BRIEF RELATION OF THE EXCEEDING MERCY OF GOD IN CHRIST, TO HIS POOR SERVANT JOHN BUNYAN </h3>
<p class="normal" id="iv-p1">1. In this my relation of the merciful working of God upon my soul, it will not 
be amiss, if, in the first place, I do, in a few words, give you a hint of my pedigree, 
and manner of bringing up; that thereby the goodness and bounty of God towards me, 
may be the more advanced and magnified before the sons of men.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p2">2. For my descent then, it was, as is well known by many, of a low and inconsiderable 
generation; my father’s house being of that rank that is meanest and most despised 
of all the families in the land. Wherefore I have not here, as others, to boast 
of noble blood, or of a high-born state, according to the flesh; though, all things 
considered, I magnify the heavenly Majesty, for that by this door He brought me 
into this world, to partake of the grace and life that is in Christ by the gospel.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p3">3. But yet, notwithstanding the meanness and inconsiderableness of my parents, 
it pleased God to put it into their hearts to put me to school, to learn both to 
read and write; the which I also attained, according to the rate of other poor men’s 
children; though, to my shame I confess, I did soon lose that little I learned, 
and that even almost utterly, and that long before the Lord did work His gracious 
work of conversion upon my soul.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p4">4. As for my own natural life, for the time that I was without God in the world, 
it was indeed according to the course of this world, and ‘the spirit that now worketh 
in the children of disobedience’ (<scripRef passage="Ephesians 2:2,3" id="iv-p4.1" parsed="|Eph|2|2|2|3" osisRef="Bible:Eph.2.2-Eph.2.3">Eph. 2.2, 3</scripRef>). It was my delight to be ‘taken captive 
by the devil at his will’ (<scripRef passage="2Timothy 2:26" id="iv-p4.2" parsed="|2Tim|2|26|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Tim.2.26">II Tim. 2.26</scripRef>). Being filled with all unrighteousness, 
the which did also so strongly work and put forth itself, both in my heart and life, 
and that from a child, that I had but few equals, especially considering my years, 
which were tender, being few, both for cursing, swearing, lying, and blaspheming 
the holy name of God.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p5">5. Yea, so settled and rooted was I in these things, that they became as a second 
nature to me; the which, as I also have with soberness considered since, did so 
offend the Lord, that even in my childhood He did scare and affright me with fearful 
dreams, and did terrify me with dreadful visions; for often, after I had spent this 
and the other day in sin, I have in my bed been greatly afflicted, while asleep, 
with the apprehensions of devils and wicked spirits, who still, as I then thought, 
laboured to draw me away with them, of which I could never be rid.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p6">6. Also I should, at these years, be greatly afflicted and troubled with the 
thoughts of the day of judgment, and that both night and day, and should tremble 
at the thoughts of the fearful torments of hell fire; still fearing that it would 
be my lot to be found at last amongst those devils and hellish fiends, who are there 
bound down with the chains and bonds of eternal darkness, ‘unto the judgment of 
the great day.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p7">7. These things, I say, when I was but a child but nine or ten years old, did 
so distress my soul, that when in the midst of my many sports and childish vanities, 
amidst my vain companions, I was often much cast down and afflicted in my mind therewith, 
yet could I not let go my sins. Yea, I was also then so overcome with despair of 
life and heaven, that I should often wish either that there had been no hell, or 
that I had been a devil—supposing they were only tormentors; that if it must needs 
be that I went thither, I might be rather a tormentor, than be tormented myself.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p8">8. A while after, these terrible dreams did leave me, which also I soon forgot; 
for my pleasures did quickly cut off the remembrance of them, as if they had never 
been: wherefore, with more greediness, according to the strength of nature, I did 
still let loose the reins to my lusts, and delighted in all transgression against 
the law of God: so that, until I came to the state of marriage, I was the very ringleader 
of all the youth that kept me company, into all manner of vice and ungodliness.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p9">9. Yea, such prevalency had the lusts and fruits of the flesh in this poor soul 
of mine, that had not a miracle of precious grace prevented, I had not only perished 
by the stroke of eternal justice, but had also laid myself open, even to the stroke 
of those laws, which bring some to disgrace and open shame before the face of the 
world.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p10">10. In these days, the thoughts of religion were very grievous to me; I could 
neither endure it myself, nor that any other should; so that, when I have seen some 
read in those books that concerned Christian piety, it would be as it were a prison 
to me. Then I said unto God, ‘Depart from me, for I desire not the knowledge of 
thy ways’ (<scripRef passage="Job 21:14" id="iv-p10.1" parsed="|Job|21|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Job.21.14">Job 21.14</scripRef>). I was now void of all good consideration, heaven and hell 
were both out of sight and mind; and as for saving and damning, they were least 
in my thoughts. O Lord, thou knowest my life, and my ways were not hid from Thee.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p11">11. Yet this I well remember, that though I could myself sin with the greatest 
delight and ease, and also take pleasure in the vileness of my companions; yet, 
even then, if I have at any time seen wicked things, by those who professed goodness, 
it would make my spirit tremble. As once, above all the rest, when I was in my height 
of vanity, yet hearing one to swear that was reckoned for a religious man, it had 
so great a stroke upon my spirit, that it made my heart to ache.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p12">12. But God did not utterly leave me, but followed me still, not now with convictions, 
but judgments; yet, such as were mixed with mercy. For once I fell into a creek 
of the sea, and hardly escaped drowning. Another time I fell out of a boat into 
Bedford river, but mercy yet preserved me alive. Besides, another time, being in 
the field with one of my companions, it chanced that an adder passed over the highway; 
so I, having a stick in my hand, struck her over the back; and having stunned her, 
I forced open her mouth with my stick, and plucked her sting out with my fingers, 
by which act, had not God been merciful, I might, by my desperateness, have brought 
myself to mine end.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p13">13. This also have I taken notice of with thanksgiving; when I was a soldier, 
I, with others, were drawn out to go to such a place to besiege it; but when I was 
just ready to go, one of the company desired to go in my room; to which, when I 
had consented, he took my place; and coming to the siege, as he stood sentinel, 
he was shot into the head with a musket bullet, and died.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p14">14. Here, as I said, were judgments and mercy, but neither of them did awaken 
my soul to righteousness; wherefore I sinned still, and grew more and more rebellious 
against God, and careless of mine own salvation.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p15">15. Presently after this, I changed my condition into a married state, and my 
mercy was to light upon a wife whose father was counted godly. This woman and I, 
though we came together as poor as poor might be, not having so much household stuff 
as a dish or spoon betwixt us both, yet this she had for her part,<i>The Plain Man’s 
Pathway to Heaven</i>, and <i>The Practice of Piety</i>, which her father had left her when 
he died. In these two books I should sometimes read with her, wherein I also found 
some things that were somewhat pleasing to me; but all this while I met with no 
conviction. She also would be often telling of me, what a godly man her father was, 
and how he would reprove and correct vice, both in his house, and amongst his neighbours; 
what a strict and holy life he lived in his day, both in word and deed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p16">16. Wherefore these books with this relation, though they did not reach my heart, 
to awaken it about my sad and sinful state, yet they did beget within me some desires 
to religion: so that, because I knew no better, I fell in very eagerly with the 
religion of the times; to wit, to go to church twice a day, and that too with the 
foremost; and there should very devoutly, both say and sing as others did, yet retaining 
my wicked life; but withal, I was so overrun with a spirit of superstition, that 
I adored, and that with great devotion, even all things, both the high place, priest, 
clerk, vestment, service, and what else belonging to the church; counting all things 
holy that were therein contained, and especially the priest and clerk most happy, 
and without doubt, greatly blessed, because they were the servants, as I then thought, 
of God, and were principal in the holy temple, to do His work therein.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p17">17. This conceit grew so strong in little time upon my spirit, that had I but 
seen a priest, though never so sordid and debauched in his life, I should find my 
spirit fall under him, reverence him, and knit unto him: yea, I thought for the 
love I did bear unto them, supposing they were the ministers of God, I could have 
lain down at their feet, and have been trampled upon by them; their name, their 
garb, and work, did so intoxicate and bewitch me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p18">18. After I had been thus for some considerable time, another thought came into 
my mind; and that was, whether we were of the Israelites, or no? For finding in 
the Scriptures that they were once the peculiar people of God, thought I, if I were 
one of this race, my soul must needs be happy. Now again, I found within me a great 
longing to be resolved about this question, but could not tell how I should. At 
last I asked my father of it; who told me,—No, we were not. Wherefore then I fell 
in my spirit as to the hopes of that, and so remained.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p19">19. But all this while, I was not sensible of the danger and evil of sin; I was 
kept from considering that sin would damn me, what religion soever I followed, unless 
I was found in Christ. Nay, I never thought of Him, nor whether there was one, or 
no. Thus man, while blind, doth wander, but wearieth himself with vanity, for he 
knoweth not the way to the city of God (<scripRef passage="Ecclesiastes 10:15" id="iv-p19.1" parsed="|Eccl|10|15|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eccl.10.15">Eccl. 10.15</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p20">20. But one day, amongst all the sermons our parson made, his subject was, to 
treat of the Sabbath-day, and of the evil of breaking that, either with labour, 
sports or otherwise. Now I was, notwithstanding my religion, one that took much 
delight in all manner of vice, and especially that was the day that I did solace 
myself therewith, wherefore I fell in my conscience under his sermon, thinking and 
believing that he made that sermon on purpose to show me my evil doing; and at that 
time I felt what guilt was, though never before, that I can remember; but then I 
was, for the present, greatly loaden therewith, and so went home when the sermon 
was ended, with a great burden upon my spirit.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p21">21. This, for that instant, did benumb the sinews of my best delights, and did 
imbitter my former pleasures to me; but behold, it lasted not, for before I had 
well dined, the trouble began to go off my mind, and my heart returned to his old 
course: but oh! how glad was I, that this trouble was gone from me, and that the 
fire was put out, that I might sin again without control! Wherefore, when I had 
satisfied nature with my food, I shook the sermon out of my mind, and to my old 
custom of sports and gaming I returned with great delight.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p22">22. But the same day, as I was in the midst of a game at cat, and having struck 
it one blow from the hole, just as I was about to strike it the second time, a voice 
did suddenly dart from heaven into my soul, which said, “Wilt thou leave thy sins 
and go to heaven, or have thy sins and go to hell?” At this I was put to an exceeding 
maze; wherefore, leaving my cat upon the ground, I looked up to heaven, and was 
as if I had, with the eyes of my understanding, seen the Lord Jesus looking down 
upon me, as being very hotly displeased with me, and as if He did severely threaten 
me with some grievous punishment for these and other ungodly practices.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p23">23. I had no sooner thus conceived in my mind, but suddenly this conclusion was 
fastened on my spirit, for the former hint did set my sins again before my face, 
that I had been a great and grievous sinner, and that it was now too late for me 
to look after heaven; for Christ would not forgive me, nor pardon my transgressions. 
Then I fell to musing upon this also; and while I was thinking on it, and fearing 
lest it should be so, I felt my heart sink in despair, concluding it was too late; 
and therefore I resolved in my mind I would go on in sin; for, thought I, if the 
case be thus, my state is surely miserable; miserable if I leave my sins, and but 
miserable if I follow them; I can but be damned, and if I must be so, I had as good 
be damned for many sins, as to be damned for few.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p24">24. Thus I stood in the midst of my play, before all that then were present; 
but yet I told them nothing: but I say, I having made this conclusion, I returned 
desperately to my sport again; and I well remember, that presently this kind of 
despair did so possess my soul, that I was persuaded I could never attain to other 
comfort than what I should get in sin; for heaven was gone already, so that on that 
I must not think; wherefore I found within me a great desire to take my fill of 
sin, still studying what sin was set to be committed, that I might taste the sweetness 
of it; and I made as much haste as I could to fill my belly with its delicates, 
lest I should die before I had my desire; for that I feared greatly. In these things, 
I protest before God, I lie not, neither do I feign this sort of speech; these were 
really, strongly, and with all my heart, my desires; the good Lord, whose mercy 
is unsearchable, forgive me my transgressions .</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p25">25. And I am very confident, that this temptation of the devil is more than usual 
amongst poor creatures than many are aware of, even to overrun their spirits with 
a scurvy and seared frame of heart, and benumbing of conscience; which frame, he 
stilly and slily supplieth with such despair, that though not much guilt attendeth 
the soul, yet they continually have a secret conclusion within them, that there 
is no hopes for them; for they have loved sins, ‘therefore after them they will 
go’ (<scripRef passage="Jeremiah 2:25" id="iv-p25.1" parsed="|Jer|2|25|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.2.25">Jer. 2.25</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Jeremiah 18:12" id="iv-p25.2" parsed="|Jer|18|12|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.18.12">18.12</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p26">26. Now therefore I went on in sin with great greediness of mind, still grudging 
that I could not be so satisfied with it as I would. This did continue with me about 
a month, or more; but one day, as I was standing at a neighbour’s shop-window, and 
there cursing and swearing, and playing the madman, after my wonted manner, there 
sat within the woman of the house, and heard me, who, though she was a very loose 
and ungodly wretch, yet protested that I swore and cursed at that most fearful rate, 
that she was made to tremble to hear me; and told me further, that I was the ungodliest 
fellow for swearing that ever she heard in all her life; and that I, by thus doing, 
was able to spoil all the youth in a whole town, if they came but in my company.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p27">27. At this reproof I was silenced, and put to secret shame, and that too, as 
I thought, before the God of heaven; wherefore, while I stood there, and hanging 
down my head. I wished with all my heart that I might be a little child again, that 
my father might learn me to speak without this wicked way of swearing; for, thought 
I, I am so accustomed to it, that it is in vain for me to think of a reformation, 
for I thought it could never be.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p28">28. But how it came to pass, I know not; I did from this time forward so leave 
my swearing that it was a great wonder to myself to observe it; and whereas before 
I knew not how to speak unless I put an oath before and another behind, to make 
my words have authority, now I could, without it, speak better, and with more pleasantness, 
than ever I could before. All this while I knew not Jesus Christ, neither did I 
leave my sports and plays.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p29">29. But quickly after this, I fell in company with one poor man that made profession 
of religion; who, as I then thought, did talk pleasantly of the Scriptures, and 
of the matters of religion; wherefore, falling into some love and liking to what 
he said, I betook me to my Bible, and began to take great pleasure in reading, but 
especially with the historical part thereof; for, as for Paul’s epistles, and Scriptures 
of that nature, I could not away with them, being as yet but ignorant, either of 
the corruptions of my nature, or of the want and worth of Jesus Christ to save me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p30">30. Wherefore I fell to some outward reformation, both in my words and life, 
and did set the commandments before me for my way to heaven; which commandments 
I also did strive to keep, and, as I thought, did keep them pretty well sometimes, 
and then I should have comfort; yet now and then should break one, and so afflict 
my conscience; but then I should repent, and say I was sorry for it, and promise 
God to do better next time, and there get help again, for then I thought I pleased 
God as well as any man in England.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p31">31. Thus I continued about a year; all which time our neighbours did take me 
to be a very godly man, a new and religious man, and did marvel much to see such 
a great and famous alteration in my life and manners; and, indeed, so it was, though 
yet I knew not Christ, nor grace, nor faith, nor hope; and truly, as I have well 
seen since, had I then died, my state had been most fearful; well, this, I say, 
continued about a twelvemonth or more.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p32">32. But, I say, my neighbours were amazed at this my great conversion, from prodigious 
profaneness, to something like a moral life; and, truly, so they well might; for 
this my conversion was as great, as for Tom of Bedlam to become a sober man. Now, 
therefore, they began to praise, to commend, and to speak well of me, both to my 
face, and behind my back. Now, I was, as they said, become godly; now, I was become 
a right honest man. But oh! when I understood that these were their words and opinions 
of me, it pleased me mighty well. For though, as yet, I was nothing but a poor painted 
hypocrite, yet I loved to be talked of as one that was truly godly. I was proud 
of my godliness, and, I did all I did, either to be seen of, or to be well spoken 
of, by man. And thus I continued for about a twelvemonth or more.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p33">33. Now you must know, that before this I had taken much delight in ringing, 
but my conscience beginning to be tender, I thought such practice was but vain, 
and therefore forced myself to leave it, yet my mind hankered; wherefore I should 
go to the steeple house, and look on it, though I durst not ring. But I thought 
this did not become religion neither, yet I forced myself, and would look on still; 
but quickly after, I began to think, How, if one of the bells should fall? Then 
I chose to stand under a main beam, that lay overthwart the steeple, from side to 
side, thinking there I might stand sure, but then I should think again, should the 
bell fall with a swing, it might first hit the wall, and then rebounding upon me, 
might kill me for all this beam. This made me stand in the steeple door; and now, 
thought I, I am safe enough; for if a bell should then fall, I can slip out behind 
these thick walls, and so be preserved notwithstanding.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p34">34. So, after this, I would yet go to see them ring, but would not go farther 
than the steeple door; but then it came into my head, How, if the steeple itself 
should fall? And this thought, it may fall for aught I know, when I stood and looked 
on, did continually so shake my mind, that I durst not stand at the steeple door 
any longer, but was forced to flee, for fear the steeple should fall upon my head.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p35">35. Another thing was my dancing; I was a full year before I could quite leave 
that; but all this while, when I thought I kept this or that commandment, or did, 
by word or deed, anything that I thought was good, I had great peace in my conscience; 
and should think with myself, God cannot choose but be now pleased with me; yea, 
to relate it in mine own way, I thought no man in England could please God better 
than I.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p36">36. But, poor wretch as I was, I was all this while ignorant of Jesus Christ, 
and going about to establish my own righteousness; and had perished therein, had 
not God, in mercy, showed me more of my state of nature.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p37">37. But upon a day, the good providence of God did cast me to Bedford, to work 
on my calling; and in one of the streets of that town, I came where there were three 
or four poor women sitting at a door in the sun, and talking about the things of 
God; and being now willing to hear them discourse, I drew near to hear what they 
said, for I was now a brisk talker also myself in the matters of religion, but now 
I may say, I heard, but I understood not; for they were far above, out of my reach, 
for their talk was about a new birth, the work of God on their hearts, also how 
they were convinced of their miserable state by nature; they talked how God had 
visited their souls with His love in the Lord Jesus, and with what words and promises 
they had been refreshed, comforted, and supported against the temptations of the 
devil. Moreover, they reasoned of the suggestions and temptations of Satan in particular; 
and told to each other by which they had been afflicted, and how they were borne 
up under his assaults. They also discoursed of their own wretchedness of heart, 
of their unbelief; and did contemn, slight, and abhor their own righteousness, as 
filthy and insufficient to do them any good.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p38">38. And methought they spake as if joy did make them speak; they spake with such 
pleasantness of Scripture language, and with such appearance of grace in all they 
said, that they were to me as if they had found a new world, as if they were people 
that dwelt alone, and were not to be reckoned among their neighbours (<scripRef passage="Numbers 23:9" id="iv-p38.1" parsed="|Num|23|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Num.23.9">Num. 23.9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p39">39. At this I felt my own heart began to shake, as mistrusting my condition to 
be naught; for I saw that in all my thoughts about religion and salvation, the new 
birth did never enter into my mind, neither knew I the comfort of the Word and promise, 
nor the deceitfulness and treachery of my own wicked heart. As for secret thoughts, 
I took no notice of them; neither did I understand what Satan’s temptations were, 
nor how they were to be withstood and resisted, etc.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p40">40. Thus, therefore, when I had heard and considered what they said, I left them, 
and went about my employment again, but their talk and discourse went with me; also 
my heart would tarry with them, for I was greatly affected with their words, both 
because by them I was convinced that I wanted the true tokens of a truly godly man, 
and also because by them I was convinced of the happy and blessed condition of him 
that was such a one.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p41">41. Therefore I should often make it my business to be going again and again 
into the company of these poor people, for I could not stay away; and the more I 
went amongst them, the more I did question my condition; and as I still do remember, 
presently I found two things within me, at which I did sometimes marvel, especially 
considering what a blind, ignorant, sordid, and ungodly wretch but just before I 
was; the one was a great softness and tenderness of heart, which caused me to fall 
under the conviction of what by Scripture they asserted; and the other was a great 
bending in my mind to a continual meditating on it, and on all other good things 
which at any time I heard or read of.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p42">42. By these things my mind was now so turned, that it lay like a horse leech 
at the vein, still crying out, Give, give (<scripRef passage="Proverbs 30:15" id="iv-p42.1" parsed="|Prov|30|15|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Prov.30.15">Prov. 30.15</scripRef>); yea, it was so fixed on 
eternity, and on the things about the kingdom of heaven, that is, so far as I knew, 
though as yet, God knows, I knew but little; that neither pleasures nor profits, 
nor persuasions, nor threats, could loosen it, or make it let go its hold; and though 
I may speak it with shame, yet it is in very deed a certain truth, it would then 
have been as difficult for me to have taken my mind from heaven to earth, as I have 
found it often since to get it again from earth to heaven.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p43">43. One thing I may not omit: There was a young man in our town, to whom my heart 
was knit more than to any other, but he being a most wicked creature for cursing, 
and swearing, and whoring, I now shook him off, and forsook his company: but about 
a quarter of a year after I had left him, I met him in a certain lane, and asked 
him how he did; he, after his old swearing and mad way, answered, he was well. “But, 
Harry,” said I, “why do you swear and curse thus? What will become of you, if you 
die in this condition?” He answered me in a great chafe, “What would the devil do 
for company, if it were not for such as I am?”</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p44">44. About this time I met with some ranters’ books, that were put forth by some 
of our countrymen, which books were also highly in esteem by several old professors; 
some of these I read, but was not able to make a judgment about them; wherefore 
as I read in them, and thought upon them, feeling myself unable to judge, I should 
betake myself to hearty prayer in this manner: O Lord, I am a fool, and not able 
to know the truth from error: Lord, leave me not to my own blindness, either to 
approve of, or condemn this doctrine; if it be of God, let me not despise it; if 
it be of the devil, let me not embrace it. Lord, I lay my soul, in this matter, 
only at Thy foot; let me not be deceived, I humbly beseech Thee. I had one religious 
intimate companion all this while, and that was the poor man that I spoke of before; 
but about this time he also turned a most devilish ranter, and gave himself up to 
all manner of filthiness, especially uncleanness; he would also deny that there 
was a God, angel, or spirit; and would laugh at all exhortations to sobriety. When 
I laboured to rebuke his wickedness, he would laugh the more, and pretend that he 
had gone through all religions, and could never light on the right till now. He 
told me also, that in a little time we should see all professors turn to the ways 
of the ranters. Wherefore, abominating those cursed principles, I left his company 
forthwith, and became to him as great a stranger, as I had been before a familiar.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p45">45. Neither was this man only a temptation to me; but my calling lying in the 
country, I happened to light into several people’s company, who, though strict in 
religion formerly, yet were also swept away by these ranters. These would also talk 
with me of their ways, and condemn me as legal and dark; pretending that they had 
only attained to perfection that could do what they would, and not sin. Oh! these 
temptations were suitable to my flesh, I being but a young man, and my nature in 
its prime; but God, who had, I hope, designed me for better things, kept me in the 
fear of His name, and did not suffer me to accept of such principles. And blessed 
be God, who put it into my heart to cry to Him to be kept and directed, still distrusting 
mine own wisdom; for I have since seen even the effect of that prayer, in His preserving 
me not only from ranting errors, but from those also that have sprung up since. 
The Bible was precious to me in those days.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p46">46. And now, methought, I began to look into the Bible with new eyes, and read 
as I never did before; and especially the epistles of the apostle Paul were sweet 
and pleasant to me; and, indeed, I was then never out of the Bible, either by reading 
or meditation; still crying out to God, that I might know the truth, and way to 
heaven and glory.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p47">47. And as I went on and read, I lighted on that passage, ‘To one is given by 
the Spirit the word of wisdom; to another the word of knowledge by the same Spirit; 
and to another faith,’ etc. (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 12:8,9" id="iv-p47.1" parsed="|1Cor|12|8|12|9" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.12.8-1Cor.12.9">1 Cor. 12.8, 9</scripRef>). And though, as I have since seen, 
that by this Scripture the Holy Ghost intends, in special, things extraordinary, 
yet on me it did then fasten with conviction, that I did want things ordinary, even 
that understanding and wisdom that other Christians had. On this word I mused, and 
could not tell what to do, especially this word <i>faith</i> put me to it, for I could 
not help it, but sometimes must question, whether I had any faith or no; for I feared 
that it shut me out of all the blessings that other good people had given them of 
God; but I was loath to conclude I had no faith in my soul; for if I do so, thought 
I, then I shall count myself a very castaway indeed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p48">48. Now, said I with myself, though I am convinced that I am an ignorant sot, 
and that I want those blessed gifts of knowledge and understanding that other good 
people have; yet, at a venture, I will conclude I am not altogether faithless, though 
I know not what faith is. For it was shewn me, and that too, as I have since seen, 
by Satan, that those who conclude themselves in a faithless state, have neither 
rest nor quiet in their souls; and I was loath to fall quite into despair.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p49">49. Wherefore, by this suggestion, I was for a while made afraid to see my want 
of faith; but God would not suffer me thus to undo and destroy my soul, but did 
continually, against this my blind and sad conclusion, create still within me such 
suppositions, insomuch that I might in this deceive myself, that I could not rest 
content, until I did now come to some certain knowledge, whether I had faith or 
not; this always running in my mind, But how if you want faith indeed? But how can 
you tell if you have faith? And, besides, I saw for certain, if I had not, I was 
sure to perish for ever.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p50">50. So that though I endeavoured at the first to look over the business of faith, 
yet in a little time, I better considering the matter, was willing to put myself 
upon the trial, whether I had faith or no. But alas, poor wretch, so ignorant and 
brutish was I, that I knew to this day no more how to do it, than I know how to 
begin and accomplish that rare and curious piece of art which I never yet saw nor 
considered.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p51">51. Wherefore, while I was thus considering, and being put to my plunge about 
it, for you must know, that as yet I had in this matter broken my mind to no man, 
only did hear and consider, the tempter came in with his delusion, That there was 
no way for me to know I had faith, but by trying to work some miracle: urging those 
Scriptures that seem to look that way, for the enforcing and strengthening his temptation. 
Nay, one day as I was betwixt Elstow and Bedford, the temptation was hot upon me 
to try if I had faith, by doing of some miracle: which miracle at that time was 
this, I must say to the puddles that were in the horse pads, Be dry; and to the 
dry places, Be you the puddles. And truly, one time I was a-going to say so indeed; 
but just as I was about to speak, this thought came into my mind, But go under yonder 
hedge and pray first, that God would make you able. But when I had concluded to 
pray, this came hot upon me, That if I prayed, and came again and tried to do it, 
and yet did nothing notwithstanding, then be sure I had no faith, but was a castaway 
and lost. Nay, thought I, if it be so, I will never try yet, but will stay a little 
longer.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p52">52. So I continued at a great loss; for I thought, if they only had faith, which 
could do so wonderful things, then I concluded that, for the present, I neither 
had it, nor yet, for time to come, were ever like to have it. Thus I was tossed 
between the devil and my own ignorance, and so perplexed, especially at some times, 
that I could not tell what to do.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p53">53. About this time, the state and happiness of these poor people at Bedford 
was thus, in a dream or vision, represented to me. I saw, as if they were set on 
the sunny side of some high mountain, there refreshing themselves with the pleasant 
beams of the sun, while I was shivering and shrinking in the cold, afflicted with 
frost, snow, and dark clouds. Methought, also, betwixt me and them, I saw a wall 
that did compass about this mountain; now, through this wall my soul did greatly 
desire to pass; concluding, that if I could, I would go even into the very midst 
of them, and there also comfort myself with the heat of their sun.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p54">54. About this wall I thought myself, to go again and again, still prying as 
I went, to see if I could find some way or passage, by which I might enter therein; 
but none could I find for some time. At the last, I saw, as it were, a narrow gap, 
like a little doorway in the wall, through which I attempted to pass; but the passage 
being very strait and narrow, I made many efforts to get in, but all in vain, even 
until I was well-nigh quite beat out, by striving to get in; at last, with great 
striving, methought I at first did get in my head, and after that, by a sidling 
striving, my shoulders, and my whole body; then I was exceeding glad, and went and 
sat down in the midst of them, and so was comforted with the light and heat of their 
sun.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p55">55. Now, this mountain and wall, etc., was thus made out to me—the mountain signified 
the church of the living God; the sun that shone thereon, the comfortable shining 
of His merciful face on them that were therein; the wall, I thought, was the Word, 
that did make separation between the Christians and the world; and the gap which 
was in this wall, I thought, was Jesus Christ, who is the way to God the Father 
(<scripRef passage="John 14:6" id="iv-p55.1" parsed="|John|14|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.14.6">John 14.6</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Matthew 7:14" id="iv-p55.2" parsed="|Matt|7|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.7.14">Matt. 7.14</scripRef>). But forasmuch as the passage was wonderful narrow, even 
so narrow, that I could not, but with great difficulty, enter in thereat, it showed 
me that none could enter into life, but those that were in downright earnest, and 
unless they left this wicked world behind them; for here was only room for body 
and soul, but not for body and soul, and sin.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p56">56. This resemblance abode upon my spirit many days; all which time I saw myself 
in a forlorn and sad condition, but yet was provoked to a vehement hunger and desire 
to be one of that number that did sit in the sunshine. Now also I should pray wherever 
I was, whether at home or abroad, in house or field, and should also often, with 
lifting up of heart, sing that of the 51st Psalm, ‘O Lord, consider my distress’; 
for as yet I knew not where I was.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p57">57. Neither as yet could I attain to any comfortable persuasion that I had faith 
in Christ; but instead of having satisfaction, here I began to find my soul to be 
assaulted with fresh doubts about my future happiness; especially with such as these, 
Whether I was elected? But how, if the day of grace should now be past and gone?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p58">58. By these two temptations I was very much afflicted and disquieted; sometimes 
by one, and sometimes by the other of them. And first, to speak of that about my 
questioning my election, I found at this time, that though I was in a flame to find 
the way to heaven and glory, and though nothing could beat me off from this, yet 
this question did so offend and discourage me, that I was, especially at some times, 
as if the very strength of my body also had been taken away by the force and power 
thereof. This scripture did also seem to me to trample upon all my desires, ‘It 
is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy’ 
(<scripRef passage="Romans 9:16" id="iv-p58.1" parsed="|Rom|9|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.9.16">Rom. 9.16</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p59">59. With this scripture I could not tell what to do; for I evidently saw, that 
unless the great God, of His infinite grace and bounty, had voluntarily chosen me 
to be a vessel of mercy, though I should desire, and long and labour until my heart 
did break, no good could come of it. Therefore, this would still stick with me, 
How can you tell that you are elected? And what if you should not? How then?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p60">60. O Lord, thought I, what if I should not, indeed? It may be you are not, said 
the tempter; it may be so, indeed, thought I. Why, then, said Satan, you had as 
good leave off, and strive no further; for if, indeed, you should not be elected 
and chosen of God, there is no talk of your being saved; ‘For it is neither of him 
that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p61">61. By these things I was driven to my wits’ end, not knowing what to say, or 
how to answer these temptations. Indeed, I little thought that Satan had thus assaulted 
me, but that rather it was my own prudence, thus to start the question; for, that 
the elect only attained eternal life, that I, without scruple, did heartily close 
withal; but that myself was one of them, there lay all the question.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p62">62. Thus, therefore, for several days, I was greatly assaulted and perplexed, 
and was often, when I have been walking, ready to sink where I went, with faintness 
in my mind; but one day, after I had been so many weeks oppressed and cast down 
therewith, as I was now quite giving up the ghost of all my hopes of ever attaining 
life, that sentence fell with weight upon my spirit, ‘Look at the generations of 
old and see; did ever any trust in the Lord, and was confounded?’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p63">63. At which I was greatly lightened and encouraged in my soul; for thus, at 
that very instant it was expounded to me: Begin at the beginning of Genesis, and 
read to the end of the Revelations, and see if you can find that there was ever 
any that trusted in the Lord, and was confounded. So, coming home, I presently went 
to my Bible to see if I could find that saying, not doubting but to find it presently; 
for it was so fresh, and with such strength and comfort on my spirit, that I was 
as if it talked with me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p64">64. Well, I looked, but I found it not; only it abode upon me; then I did ask 
first this good man, and then another, if they knew where it was, but they knew 
no such place. At this I wondered that such a sentence should so suddenly, and with 
such comfort and strength, seize and abide upon my heart, and yet that none could 
find it, for I doubted not but it was in Holy Scripture.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p65">65. Thus I continued above a year, and could not find the place; but at last, 
casting my eye into the Apocrypha books, I found it in <scripRef passage="Ecclesiasticus 2:10" id="iv-p65.1" parsed="|Sir|2|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Sir.2.10">Ecclesiasticus 2.10</scripRef>. This, 
at the first, did somewhat daunt me; but because, by this time, I had got more experience 
of the love and kindness of God, it troubled me the less; especially when I considered, 
that though it was not in those texts that we call holy and canonical, yet forasmuch 
as this sentence was the sum and substance of many of the promises, it was my duty 
to take the comfort of it; and I bless God for that word, for it was of God to me: 
that word doth still, at times, shine before my face.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p66">66. After this, that other doubt did come with strength upon me, But how if the 
day of grace should be past and gone? How if you have overstood the time of mercy? 
Now, I remember that one day, as I was walking into the country, I was much in the 
thoughts of this, But how if the day of grace be past? And to aggravate my trouble, 
the tempter presented to my mind those good people of Bedford, and suggested thus 
unto me, That these being converted already, they were all that God would save in 
those parts; and that I came too late, for these had got the blessing before I came.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p67">67. Now was I in great distress, thinking in very deed that this might well be 
so; wherefore I went up and down bemoaning my sad condition, counting myself far 
worse than a thousand fools, for standing off thus long, and spending so many years 
in sin as I had done; still crying out, Oh, that I had turned sooner! Oh, that I 
had turned seven years ago! It made me also angry with myself, to think that I should 
have no more wit, but to trifle away my time till my soul and heaven were lost.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p68">68. But when I had been long vexed with this fear, and was scarce able to take 
one step more, just about the same place where I received my other encouragement, 
these words broke in upon my mind, ‘Compel them to come in, that my house may be 
filled’; ‘and yet there is room’ (<scripRef passage="Luke 14:22,23" id="iv-p68.1" parsed="|Luke|14|22|14|23" osisRef="Bible:Luke.14.22-Luke.14.23">Luke 14.22, 23</scripRef>). These words, but especially them, 
‘And yet there is room’, were sweet words to me; for, truly, I thought that by them 
I saw there was place enough in heaven for me; and, moreover, that when the Lord 
Jesus did speak these words, He then did think of me; and that He, knowing that 
the time would come that I should be afflicted with fear that there was no place 
left for me in His bosom, did before speak this word, and leave it upon record, 
that I might find help thereby against this vile temptation. This, I then verily 
believed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p69">69. In the light and encouragement of this word, I went a pretty while; and the 
comfort was the more, when I thought that the Lord Jesus should think on me so long 
ago, and that He should speak those words on purpose for my sake; for I did then 
think, verily, that He did on purpose speak them, to encourage me withal.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p70">70. But I was not without my temptations to go back again; temptations, I say, 
both from Satan, mine own heart, and carnal acquaintance; but I thank God these 
were outweighed by that sound sense of death and of the day of judgment, which abode, 
as it were, continually in my view; I should often also think on Nebuchadnezzar, 
of whom it is said, He had given him all the kingdoms of the earth (<scripRef passage="Daniel 5:19" id="iv-p70.1" parsed="|Dan|5|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Dan.5.19">Dan. 5.19</scripRef>). 
Yet, I thought, if this great man had all his portion in this world, one hour in 
hell fire would make him forget all. Which consideration was a great help to me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p71">71. I was almost made, about this time, to see something concerning the beasts 
that Moses counted clean and unclean. I thought those beasts were types of men; 
the clean, types of them that were the people of God; but the unclean, types of 
such as were the children of the wicked one. Now, I read that the clean beasts chewed 
the cud; that is, thought I, they show us we must feed upon the Word of God. They 
also parted the hoof; I thought that signified we must part, if we would be saved, 
with the ways of ungodly men. And also, in further reading about them I found that 
though we did chew the cud as the hare, yet if we walked with claws like a dog, 
or if we did part the hoof like the swine, yet if we did not chew the cud as the 
sheep, we were still, for all that, but unclean; for I thought the hare to be a 
type of those that talk of the Word, yet walk in the ways of sin; and that the swine 
was like him that parted with his outward pollutions, but still wanteth the Word 
of faith, without which there could be no way of salvation, let a man be never so 
devout (<scripRef passage="Deuteronomy 14:1-29" id="iv-p71.1" parsed="|Deut|14|1|14|29" osisRef="Bible:Deut.14.1-Deut.14.29">Deut. 14</scripRef>). After this I found, by reading the Word, that those that must 
be glorified with Christ in another world must be called by Him here; called to 
the partaking of a share in His Word and righteousness, and to the comforts and 
first fruits of His Spirit, and to a peculiar interest in all those heavenly things 
which do indeed fore fit the soul for that rest and house of glory which is in heaven 
above.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p72">72. Here, again, I was at a very great stand, not knowing what to do, fearing 
I was not called; for, thought I, if I be not called, what then can do me good? 
None but those who are effectually called, inherit the kingdom of heaven. But oh! 
how I now loved those words that spake of a Christian’s calling! as when the Lord 
said to one, ‘Follow me’, and to another, ‘Come after me’. And oh! thought I, that 
He would say so to me too, how gladly would I run after him!</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p73">73. I cannot now express with what longings and breakings in my soul I cried 
to Christ to call me. Thus I continued for a time, all on a flame to be converted 
to Jesus Christ; and did also see at that day, such glory in a converted state, 
that I could not be contented without a share therein. Gold! could it have been 
gotten for gold, what could I have given for it! had I a whole world it had all 
gone ten thousand times over for this, that my soul might have been in a converted 
state.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p74">74. How lovely now was everyone in my eyes that I thought to be converted men 
and women! they shone, they walked like a people that carried the broad seal of 
heaven about them. Oh! I saw the lot was fallen to them in pleasant places, and 
they had a goodly heritage (<scripRef passage="Psalm 16:6" id="iv-p74.1" parsed="|Ps|16|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.16.6">Ps. 16.6</scripRef>). But that which made me sick was that of Christ, 
in Mark, He went up into a mountain and called to Him whom He would, and they came 
unto Him (<scripRef passage="Mark 3:13" id="iv-p74.2" parsed="|Mark|3|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Mark.3.13">Mark 3.13</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p75">75. This scripture made me faint and fear, yet it kindled fire in my soul. That 
which made me fear was this, lest Christ should have no liking to me, for He called 
‘whom he would’. But oh! the glory that I saw in that condition did still so engage 
my heart that I could seldom read of any that Christ did call but I presently wished, 
Would I had been in their clothes; would I had been born Peter; would I had been 
born John; or would I had been by and had heard Him when He called them, how would 
I have cried, O Lord, call me also. But oh! I feared He would not call me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p76">76. And truly the Lord let me go thus many months together and showed me nothing; 
either that I was already, or should be called hereafter. But at last, after much 
time spent, and many groans to God, that I might be made partaker of the holy and 
heavenly calling, that Word came in upon me: ‘I will cleanse their blood that I 
have not cleansed: for the Lord dwelleth in Zion’ (<scripRef passage="Joel 3:21" id="iv-p76.1" parsed="|Joel|3|21|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Joel.3.21">Joel 3.21</scripRef>). These words I thought 
were sent to encourage me to wait still upon God, and signified unto me, that if 
I were not already, yet time might come, I might be in truth converted to Christ.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p77">77. About this time I began to break my mind to those poor people in Bedford, 
and to tell them my condition, which, when they had heard, they told Mr. Gifford 
of me, who himself also took occasion to talk with me, and was willing to be well 
persuaded of me, though I think but from little grounds: but he invited me to his 
house, where I should hear him confer with others, about the dealings of God with 
the soul; from all which I still received more conviction, and from that time began 
to see something of the vanity and inward wretchedness of my wicked heart, for as 
yet I knew no great matter therein; but now it began to be discovered unto me, and 
also to work at that rate for wickedness as it never did before. Now I evidently 
found that lusts and corruptions would strongly put forth themselves within me, 
in wicked thoughts and desires, which I did not regard before; my desires for heaven 
and life began to fail. I found also, that whereas my soul was full of longing after 
God, now my heart began to hanker after every foolish vanity; yea, my heart would 
not be moved to mind that that was good; it began to be careless, both of my soul 
and heaven; it would now continually hang back, both to, and in every duty; and 
was as a clog on the leg of a bird to hinder her from flying.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p78">78. Nay, thought I, now I grow worse and worse; now am I farther from conversion 
than ever I was before. Wherefore I began to sink greatly in my soul, and began 
to entertain such discouragement in my heart as laid me low as hell. If now I should 
have burned at a stake, I could not believe that Christ had love for me; alas, I 
could neither hear Him, nor see Him, nor feel Him, nor savour any of His things; 
I was driven as with a tempest, my heart would be unclean, the Canaanites would 
dwell in the land.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p79">79. Sometimes I would tell my condition to the people of God, which, when they 
heard, they would pity me, and would tell me of the promises; but they had as good 
have told me that I must reach the sun with my finger as have bidden me receive 
or rely upon the promise; and as soon as I should have done it, all my sense and 
feeling was against me; and I saw I had a heart that would sin, and that lay under 
a law that would condemn.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p80">80. These things have often made me think of that child which the father brought 
to Christ, who, while he was yet a-coming to him, was thrown down by the devil, 
and also so rent and torn by him that he lay and wallowed, foaming (<scripRef passage="Luke 9:42" id="iv-p80.1" parsed="|Luke|9|42|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.9.42">Luke 9.42</scripRef>, <scripRef passage="Mark 9:20" id="iv-p80.2" parsed="|Mark|9|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Mark.9.20">Mark 
9.20</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p81">81. Further, in these days I should find my heart to shut itself up against the 
Lord, and against His holy Word. I have found my unbelief to set, as it were, the 
shoulder to the door to keep Him out, and that too even then, when I have with many 
a bitter sigh cried, Good Lord, break it open; Lord, break these gates of brass, 
and cut these bars of iron asunder (<scripRef passage="Psalm 107:16" id="iv-p81.1" parsed="|Ps|107|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.107.16">Ps. 107.16</scripRef>). Yet that word would sometimes create 
in my heart a peaceable pause, ‘I girded thee, though thou hast not known me’ (<scripRef passage="Isaiah 45:5" id="iv-p81.2" parsed="|Isa|45|5|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.45.5">Isa. 
45.5</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p82">82. But all this while as to the act of sinning, I never was more tender than 
now; I durst not take a pin or a stick, though but so big as a straw, for my conscience 
now was sore, and would smart at every touch; I could not now tell how to speak 
my words, for fear I should misplace them. Oh, how gingerly did I then go in all 
I did or said! I found myself as on a miry bog that shook if I did but stir; and 
was there left both of God and Christ, and the Spirit, and all good things.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p83">83. But, I observe, though I was such a great sinner before conversion, yet God 
never much charged the guilt of the sins of my ignorance upon me; only He showed 
me I was lost if I had not Christ, because I had been a sinner; I saw that I wanted 
a perfect righteousness to present me without fault before God, and this righteousness 
was nowhere to be found, but in the person of Jesus Christ.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p84">84. But my original and inward pollution, that, that was my plague and my affliction; 
that, I say, at a dreadful rate, always putting forth itself within me; that I had 
the guilt of, to amazement; by reason of that, I was more loathsome in my own eyes 
than was a toad; and I thought I was so in God’s eyes too; sin and corruption, I 
said, would as naturally bubble out of my heart, as water would bubble out of a 
fountain. I thought now that everyone had a better heart than I had; I could have 
changed heart with anybody; I thought none but the devil himself could equalize 
me for inward wickedness and pollution of mind. I fell, therefore, at the sight 
of my own vileness, deeply into despair; for I concluded that this condition that 
I was in could not stand with a state of grace. Sure, thought I, I am forsaken of 
God; sure I am given up to the devil, and to a reprobate mind; and thus I continued 
a long while, even for some years together.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p85">85. While I was thus afflicted with the fears of my own damnation, there were 
two things would make me wonder; the one was, when I saw old people hunting after 
the things of this life, as if they should live here always; the other was, when 
I found professors much distressed and cast down, when they met with outward losses, 
as of husband, wife, child, etc. Lord, thought I, what ado is here about such little 
things as these! What seeking after carnal things by some, and what grief in others 
for the loss of them! If they so much labour after, and spend so many tears for 
the things of this present life, how am I to be bemoaned, pitied, and prayed for! 
My soul is dying, my soul is damning. Were my soul but in a good condition, and 
were I but sure of it, oh! how rich I should esteem myself, though blessed but with 
bread and water; I should count those but small afflictions, and should bear them 
as little burdens. ‘A wounded spirit who can bear?’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p86">86. And though I was thus troubled, and tossed, and afflicted, with the sight 
and sense and terror of my own wickedness, yet I was afraid to let this sight and 
sense go quite off my mind; for I found that, unless guilt of conscience was taken 
off the right way, that is, by the blood of Christ, a man grew rather worse for 
the loss of his trouble of mind, than better. Wherefore, if my guilt lay hard upon 
me, then I should cry that the blood of Christ might take it off; and if it was 
going off without it (for the sense of sin would be sometimes as if it would die, 
and go quite away), then I would also strive to fetch it upon my heart again, by 
bringing the punishment for sin in hell fire upon my spirits; and should cry, Lord, 
let it not go off my heart, but the right way, but by the blood of Christ, and by 
the application of Thy mercy, through Him, to my soul; for that scripture lay much 
upon me, ‘without shedding of blood is no remission’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 9:22" id="iv-p86.1" parsed="|Heb|9|22|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.9.22">Heb. 9.22</scripRef>). And that which 
made me the more afraid of this was, because I had seen some who, though when they 
were under wounds of conscience, then they would cry and pray; but they seeking 
rather present ease from their trouble, than pardon for their sin, cared not how 
they lost their guilt, so they got it out of their mind; and, therefore, having 
got it off the wrong way, it was not sanctified unto them; but they grew harder 
and blinder, and more wicked after their trouble. This made me afraid, and made 
me cry to God the more, that it might not be so with me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p87">87. And now was I sorry that God had made me a man, for I feared I was a reprobate; 
I counted man as unconverted, the most doleful of all the creatures. Thus being 
afflicted and tossed about my sad condition, I counted myself alone, and above the 
most of men unblessed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p88">88. Yea, I thought it impossible that ever I should attain to so much goodness 
of heart, as to thank God that He had made me a man. Man indeed is the most noble 
by creation, of all creatures in the visible world; but by sin he has made himself 
the most ignoble. The beasts, birds, fishes, etc., I blessed their condition, for 
they had not a sinful nature, they were not obnoxious in the sight of God; they 
were not to go to hell fire after death; I could therefore have rejoiced had my 
condition been as any of theirs.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p89">89. In this condition I went a great while; but when comforting time was come, 
I heard one preach a sermon upon those words in the <scripRef passage="Song 4" id="iv-p89.1" parsed="|Song|4|0|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Song.4">Song 4</scripRef>.1, ‘Behold thou art fair, 
my love; behold, thou art fair.’ But at that time he made these two words, ‘My love’, 
his chief and subject matter; from which, after he had a little opened the text, 
he observed these several conclusions: 1. That the Church, and so every saved soul, 
is Christ’s love, when loveless. 2. Christ’s love without a cause. 3. Christ’s love 
when hated of the world. 4. Christ’s love when under temptation, and under desertion. 
5. Christ’s love from first to last.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p90">90. But I got nothing by what he said at present, only when he came to the application 
of the fourth particular, this was the word he said: If it be so, that the saved 
soul is Christ’s love when under temptation and desertion; then, poor tempted soul, 
when thou art assaulted and afflicted with temptation, and the hidings of God’s 
face, yet think on these two words, ‘My love’, still.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p91">91. So as I was a-going home, these words came again into my thoughts; and I 
well remember, as I came in, I said thus in my heart, What shall I get by thinking 
on these two words? This thought had no sooner passed through my heart, but the 
words began thus to kindle in my spirit, ‘Thou art my love, thou art my love’, twenty 
times together; and still as they ran thus in my mind, they waxed stronger and warmer, 
and began to make me look up; but being as yet between hope and fear, I still replied 
in my heart, But is it true, but is it true? At which, that sentence fell in upon 
me, he ‘wist not that it was true which was done by the angel’ (<scripRef passage="Acts 12:9" id="iv-p91.1" parsed="|Acts|12|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.12.9">Acts 12.9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p92">92. Then I began to give place to the word, which, with power, did over and over 
make this joyful sound within my soul, Thou art my love, thou art my love; and nothing 
shall separate thee from my love; and with that, <scripRef passage="Rom 8" id="iv-p92.1" parsed="|Rom|8|0|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.8">Rom 8</scripRef>.39 came into my mind. Now 
was my heart filled full of comfort and hope, and now I could believe that my sins 
should be forgiven me; yea, I was now so taken with the love and mercy of God, that 
I remember I could not tell how to contain till I got home; I thought I could have 
spoken of His love, and of His mercy to me, even to the very crows that sat upon 
the ploughed lands before me, had they been capable to have understood me; wherefore 
I said in my soul with much gladness, Well, I would I had a pen and ink here, I 
would write this down before I go any farther, for surely I will not forget this 
forty years hence; but alas! within less than forty days, I began to question all 
again; which made me begin to question all still.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p93">93. Yet still at times, I was helped to believe that it was a true manifestation 
of grace unto my soul, though I had lost much of the life and savour of it. Now 
about a week or fortnight after this, I was much followed by this scripture, ‘Simon, 
Simon, behold Satan hath desired to have you’ (<scripRef passage="Luke 22:31" id="iv-p93.1" parsed="|Luke|22|31|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.22.31">Luke 22.31</scripRef>). And sometimes it would 
sound so loud within me, yea, and as it were call so strongly after me, that once 
above all the rest, I turned my head over my shoulder, thinking verily that some 
man had, behind me, called to me; being at a great distance, methought he called 
so loud; it came, as I have thought since, to have stirred me up to prayer, and 
to watchfulness; it came to acquaint me that a cloud and a storm was coming down 
upon me, but I understood it not.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p94">94. Also, as I remember, that time that it called to me so loud, was the last 
time that it sounded in mine ear; but methinks I hear still with what a loud voice 
these words, Simon, Simon, sounded in mine ears. I thought verily, as I have told 
you, that somebody had called after me, that was half a mile behind me; and although 
that was not my name, yet it made me suddenly look behind me, believing that he 
that called so loud meant me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p95">95. But so foolish was I, and ignorant, that I knew not the reason of this sound; 
which, as I did both see and feel soon after, was sent from heaven as an alarm, 
to awaken me to provide for what was coming; only it would make me muse and wonder 
in my mind, to think what should be the reason that this scripture, and that at 
this rate, so often and so loud, should still be sounding and rattling in mine ears; 
but, as I said before, I soon after perceived the end of God therein.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p96">96. For about the space of a month after, a very great storm came down upon me, 
which handled me twenty times worse than all I had met with before; it came stealing 
upon me, now by one piece, then by another; first, all my comfort was taken from 
me, then darkness seized upon me, after which whole floods of blasphemies, both 
against God, Christ, and the Scriptures, were poured upon my spirit, to my great 
confusion and astonishment. These blasphemous thoughts were such as also stirred 
up questions in me, against the very being of God, and of His only beloved Son; 
as whether there were, in truth, a God, or Christ, or no? And whether the holy Scriptures 
were not rather a fable, and cunning story, than the holy and pure Word of God?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p97">97 The tempter would also much assault me with this, How can you tell but that 
the Turks had as good Scriptures to prove their Mahomet the Saviour, as we have 
to prove our Jesus is? And, could I think, that so many ten thousands, in so many 
countries and kingdoms, should be without the knowledge of the right way to heaven; 
if there were indeed a heaven, and that we only, who live in a corner of the earth, 
should alone be blessed therewith? Everyone doth think his own religion rightest, 
both Jews and Moors, and Pagans! and how if all our faith, and Christ, and Scriptures, 
should be but a think-so too?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p98">98. Sometimes I have endeavoured to argue against these suggestions, and to set 
some of the sentences of blessed Paul against them; but, alas! I quickly felt, when 
I thus did, such arguings as these would return again upon me, Though we made so 
great a matter of Paul, and of his words, yet how could I tell, but that in very 
deed, he being a subtle and cunning man, might give himself up to deceive with strong 
delusions; and also take both that pains and travail, to undo and destroy his fellows?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p99">99. These suggestions, with many other which at this time I may not, nor dare 
not utter, neither by word nor pen, did make such a seizure upon my spirit, and 
did so overweigh my heart, both with their number, continuance, and fiery force, 
that I felt as if there were nothing else but these from morning to night within 
me; and as though, indeed, there could be room for nothing else; and also concluded 
that God had, in very wrath to my soul, given me up unto them, to be carried away 
with them, as with a mighty whirlwind.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p100">100. Only by the distaste that they gave unto my spirit, I felt there was something 
in me that refused to embrace them. But this consideration I then only had, when 
God gave me leave to swallow my spittle, otherwise the noise, and strength, and 
force of these temptations, would drown and overflow, and as it were bury all such 
thoughts or the remembrance of any such thing. While I was in this temptation, I 
should often find my mind suddenly put upon it, to curse and swear, or to speak 
some grievous thing against God, or Christ His Son, and of the Scriptures.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p101">101. Now I thought, surely I am possessed of the devil; at other times again, 
I thought I should be bereft of my wits; for instead of lauding and magnifying God 
the Lord with others, if I have but heard Him spoken of, presently some most horrible 
blasphemous thought or other would bolt out of my heart against Him; so that whether 
I did think that God was, or again did think there were no such thing, no love, 
nor peace, nor gracious disposition could I feel within me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p102">102. These things did sink me into very deep despair; for I concluded, that such 
things could not possibly be found amongst them that loved God. I often, when these 
temptations have been with force upon me, did compare myself in the case of such 
a child, whom some gipsy hath by force took up under her apron, and is carrying 
from friend and country; kick sometimes I did, and also scream and cry; but yet 
I was as bound in the wings of the temptation, and the wind would carry me away. 
I thought also of Saul, and of the evil spirit that did possess him; and did greatly 
fear that my condition was the same with that of his (<scripRef passage="1Samuel 16:14" id="iv-p102.1" parsed="|1Sam|16|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Sam.16.14">1 Sam. 16.14</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p103">103. In these days, when I have heard others talk of what was the sin against 
the Holy Ghost, then would the tempter so provoke me to desire to sin that sin, 
that I was as if I could not, must not, neither should be quiet until I had committed 
that; now, no sin would serve but that; if it were to be committed by speaking of 
such a word, then I have been as if my mouth would have spoken that word, whether 
I would or no; and in so strong a measure was this temptation upon me, that often 
I have been ready to clap my hand under my chin, to hold my mouth from opening; 
and to that end also I have had thoughts at other times, to leap with my head downward, 
into some muck-hill hole or other, to keep my mouth from speaking.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p104">104. Now I blessed the condition of the dog and toad, and counted the estate 
of everything that God had made far better than this dreadful state of mine, and 
such as my companions was; yea, gladly would I have been in the condition of dog 
or horse, for I knew they had no soul to perish under the everlasting weights of 
hell for sin, as mine was like to do. Nay, and though I saw this, felt this, and 
was broken to pieces with it, yet that which added to my sorrow was, that I could 
not find that with all my soul I did desire deliverance. That scripture did also 
tear and rend my soul, in the midst of these distractions, ‘The wicked are like 
the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and dirt. There 
is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked, saith my God.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p105">105. And now my heart was, at times, exceeding hard; if I would have given a 
thousand pounds for a tear, I could not shed one; no, nor sometimes scarce desire 
to shed one. I was much dejected to think that this should be my lot. I saw some 
could mourn and lament their sin; and others, again, could rejoice, and bless God 
for Christ; and others, again, could quietly talk of, and with gladness remember, 
the Word of God; while I only was in the storm or tempest. This much sunk me; I 
thought my condition was alone. I should, therefore, much bewail my hard hap; but 
get out of, or get rid of, these things, I could not.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p106">106. While this temptation lasted, which was about a year, I could attend upon 
none of the ordinances of God but with sore and great affliction. Yea, then was 
I most distressed with blasphemies; if I have been hearing the Word, then uncleanness, 
blasphemies and despair would hold me as captive there; if I have been reading, 
then, sometimes, I had sudden thoughts to question all I read; sometimes, again, 
my mind would be so strangely snatched away, and possessed with other things, that 
I have neither known, nor regarded, nor remembered so much as the sentence that 
but now I have read.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p107">107. In prayer, also, I have been greatly troubled at this time; sometimes I 
have thought I should see the devil; nay, thought I have felt him, behind me, pull 
my clothes; he would be, also, continually at me in the time of prayer to have done; 
break off, make haste, you have prayed enough, and stay no longer, still drawing 
my mind away. Sometimes, also, he would cast in such wicked thoughts as these: that 
I must pray to him, or for him. I have thought sometimes of that—Fall down, or, 
‘if thou wilt fall down and worship me’ (<scripRef passage="Matthew 4:9" id="iv-p107.1" parsed="|Matt|4|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.4.9">Matt. 4.9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p108">108. Also, when, because I have had wandering thoughts in the time of this duty, 
I have laboured to compose my mind and fix it upon God, then, with great force, 
hath the tempter laboured to distract me, and confound me, and to turn away my mind, 
by presenting to my heart and fancy the form of a bush, a bull, a besom, or the 
like, as if I should pray to those; to these he would, also, at some times especially, 
so hold my mind that I was as if I could think of nothing else, or pray to nothing 
else but to these, or such as they.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p109">109. Yet, at times I should have some strong and heart-affecting apprehensions 
of God, and the reality of the truth of His gospel; but, oh! how would my heart, 
at such times, put forth itself with inexpressible groanings. My whole soul was 
then in every word; I should cry with pangs after God that He would be merciful 
unto me; but then I should be daunted again with such conceits as these: I should 
think that God did mock at these, my prayers, saying, and that in the audience of 
the holy angels, This poor simple wretch doth hanker after Me as if I had nothing 
to do with My mercy but to bestow it on such as he. Alas, poor fool! how art thou 
deceived; It is not for such as thee to have favour with the Highest.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p110">110. Then hath the tempter come upon me, also, with such discouragements as these—You are very hot for mercy, but I will cool you; this frame shall not last always; 
many have been as hot as you for a spirit, but I have quenched their zeal. And with 
this, such and such who were fallen off would be set before mine eyes. Then I should 
be afraid that I should do so too; but, thought I, I am glad this comes into my 
mind. Well, I will watch, and take what heed I can. Though you do, said Satan, I 
shall be too hard for you; I will cool you insensibly, by degrees, by little and 
little. What care I, saith he, though I be seven years in chilling your heart if 
I can do it at last? Continual rocking will lull a crying child asleep. I will ply 
it close, but I will have my end accomplished. Though you be burning hot at present, 
yet, if I can pull you from this fire, I shall have you cold before it be long.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p111">111. These things brought me into great straits; for as I at present could not 
find myself fit for present death, so I thought to live long would make me yet more 
unfit; for time would make me forget all, and wear even the remembrance of the evil 
of sin, the worth of heaven, and the need I had of the blood of Christ to wash me, 
both out of mind and thought; but I thank Christ Jesus these things did not at present 
make me slack my crying, but rather did put me more upon it, like her who met with 
the adulterer (<scripRef passage="Deuteronomy 22:27" id="iv-p111.1" parsed="|Deut|22|27|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Deut.22.27">Deut. 22.27</scripRef>); in which days that was a good word to me after I had 
suffered these things a while: ‘I am persuaded that neither height, nor depth, 
nor life,’ etc., ‘shall separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus’ 
(<scripRef passage="Romans 8:38" id="iv-p111.2" parsed="|Rom|8|38|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.8.38">Rom. 8.38</scripRef>). And now I hoped long life should not destroy me, nor make me miss of 
heaven.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p112">112. Yet I had some supports in this temptation, though they were then all questioned 
by me; that in the third of Jeremiah, at the first, was something to me, and so 
was the consideration of the fifth verse of that chapter; that though we have spoken 
and done as evil things as we could, yet we should cry unto God, ‘My Father, Thou 
art the guide of my youth’; and should return unto Him.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p113">113. I had, also, once a sweet glance from that in <scripRef passage="2Corinthians 5:21" id="iv-p113.1" parsed="|2Cor|5|21|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.5.21">II Cor. 5.21</scripRef>: ‘For he hath 
made him to be sin for us, who knew no sin; that we might be made the righteousness 
of God in him.’ I remember, also, that one day as I was sitting in a neighbour’s 
house, and there very sad at the consideration of my many blasphemies, and as I 
was saying in my mind, What ground have I to think that I, who have been so vile 
and abominable, should ever inherit eternal life? that word came suddenly upon me, 
‘What shall we then say to these things? If God be for us, who can be against us?’ 
(<scripRef passage="Romans 8:31" id="iv-p113.2" parsed="|Rom|8|31|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.8.31">Rom. 8.31</scripRef>). That, also, was an help unto me, ‘Because I live, ye shall live also’ 
(<scripRef passage="John 14:19" id="iv-p113.3" parsed="|John|14|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.14.19">John 14.19</scripRef>). But these were but hints, touches, and short visits, though very sweet 
when present; only they lasted not; but, like to Peter’s sheet, of a sudden were 
caught up from me to heaven again (<scripRef passage="Acts 10:16" id="iv-p113.4" parsed="|Acts|10|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.10.16">Acts 10.16</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p114">114. But afterwards the Lord did more fully and graciously discover Himself unto 
me; and, indeed, did quite, not only deliver me from the guilt that, by these things, 
was laid upon my conscience, but also from the very filth thereof; for the temptation 
was removed, and I was put into my right mind again, as other Christians were.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p115">115. I remember that one day, as I was travelling into the country and musing 
on the wickedness and blasphemy of my heart, and considering of the enmity that 
was in me to God, that scripture came in my mind, He hath ‘made peace through the 
blood of his cross’ (<scripRef passage="Colossians 1:20" id="iv-p115.1" parsed="|Col|1|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Col.1.20">Col. 1.20</scripRef>). By which I was made to see, both again, and again, 
and again, that day, that God and my soul were friends by this blood; yea, I saw 
that the justice of God and my sinful soul could embrace and kiss each other through 
this blood. This was a good day to me; I hope I shall not forget it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p116">116. At another time, as I sat by the fire in my house, and musing on my wretchedness, 
the Lord made that also a precious word unto me, ‘Forasmuch, then, as the children 
are partakers of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise took part of the same; 
that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death, that is, the 
devil, and deliver them who, through fear of death, were all their lifetime subject 
to bondage’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 2:14,15" id="iv-p116.1" parsed="|Heb|2|14|2|15" osisRef="Bible:Heb.2.14-Heb.2.15">Heb. 2.14, 15</scripRef>). I thought that the glory of these words was then so 
weighty on me that I was, both once and twice, ready to swoon as I sat; yet not 
with grief and trouble, but with solid joy and peace.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p117">117. At this time, also, I sat under the ministry of holy Mr. Gifford, whose 
doctrine, by God’s grace, was much for my stability. This man made it much his business 
to deliver the people of God from all those faults and unsound rests that, by nature, 
we are prone to take and make to our souls. He pressed up to take special heed that 
we took not up any truth upon trust—as from this, or that, or any other man or men—but 
to cry mightily to God that He would convince us of the reality thereof, and 
set us down therein, by His own Spirit, in the holy Word; for, said he, if you do 
otherwise when temptations come, if strongly, you, not having received them with 
evidence from heaven, will find you want that help and strength now to resist as 
once you thought you had.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p118">118. This was as seasonable to my soul as the former and latter rain in their 
season; for I had found, and that by sad experience, the truth of these his words; 
for I had felt what no man can say, especially when tempted by the devil, that Jesus 
Christ is Lord but by the Holy Ghost. Wherefore I found my soul, through grace, 
very apt to drink in this doctrine, and to incline to pray to God that, in nothing 
that pertained to God’s glory and my own eternal happiness, He would suffer me to 
be without the confirmation thereof from heaven; for now I saw clearly there was 
an exceeding difference betwixt the notions of flesh and blood, and the revelations 
of God in heaven; also, a great difference between that faith that is feigned, and 
according to man’s wisdom, and of that which comes by a man’s being born thereto 
of God (<scripRef passage="Matthew 16:17-17" id="iv-p118.1" parsed="|Matt|16|17|16|17" osisRef="Bible:Matt.16.17-Matt.16.17">Matt. 16.15-17</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="1John 5:1" id="iv-p118.2" parsed="|1John|5|1|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1John.5.1">1 John 5.1</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p119">119. But, oh! now, how was my soul led from truth to truth by God! even from 
the birth and cradle of the Son of God to His ascension and second coming from heaven 
to judge the world.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p120">120. Truly, I then found, upon this account, the great God was very good unto 
me; for, to my remembrance, there was not anything that I then cried unto God to 
make known and reveal unto me but He was pleased to do it for me; I mean not one 
part of the gospel of the Lord Jesus, but I was orderly led into it. Methought I 
saw with great evidence, from the relation of the four evangelists, the wonderful 
work of God, in giving Jesus Christ to save us, from His conception and birth even 
to His second coming to judgment. Methought I was as if I had seen Him born, as 
if I had seen Him grow up, as if I had seen Him walk through this world, from the 
cradle to His cross: to which, also, when He came, I saw how gently He gave Himself 
to be hanged and nailed on it for my sins and wicked doings. Also, as I was musing 
on this, His progress, that dropped on my spirit, He was ordained for the slaughter 
(<scripRef passage="1Peter 1:19,20" id="iv-p120.1" parsed="|1Pet|1|19|1|20" osisRef="Bible:1Pet.1.19-1Pet.1.20">1 Pet. 1.19, 20</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p121">121. When I have considered also the truth of His resurrection, and have remembered 
that word, ‘Touch me not, Mary,’ etc., I have seen as if He leaped at the grave’s 
mouth for joy that He was risen again, and had got the conquest over our dreadful 
foes (<scripRef passage="John 20:17" id="iv-p121.1" parsed="|John|20|17|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.20.17">John 20.17</scripRef>). I have also, in the spirit, seen Him a man on the right hand 
of God the Father for me, and have seen the manner of His coming from heaven to 
judge the world with glory, and have been confirmed in these things by these scriptures 
following, <scripRef passage="Acts 1:9,10" id="iv-p121.2" parsed="|Acts|1|9|1|10" osisRef="Bible:Acts.1.9-Acts.1.10">Acts 1.9, 10</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Acts 7:56" id="iv-p121.3" parsed="|Acts|7|56|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.7.56">7.56</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Acts 10:42" id="iv-p121.4" parsed="|Acts|10|42|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.10.42">10.42</scripRef>; 
<scripRef passage="Hebrews 7:24" id="iv-p121.5" parsed="|Heb|7|24|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.7.24">Heb. 7.24</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Hebrews 8:3" id="iv-p121.6" parsed="|Heb|8|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.8.3">8.3</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Revelation 1:18" id="iv-p121.7" parsed="|Rev|1|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rev.1.18">Rev. 1.18</scripRef>; 
<scripRef passage="1Thessalonians 4:17,18" id="iv-p121.8" parsed="|1Thess|4|17|4|18" osisRef="Bible:1Thess.4.17-1Thess.4.18">1 Thess. 4.17, 18</scripRef>.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p122">122. Once I was much troubled to know whether the Lord Jesus was both man as 
well as God, and God as well as man; and truly, in those days, let men say what 
they would, unless I had it with evidence from heaven, all was as nothing to me, 
I counted not myself set down in any truth of God. Well, I was much troubled about 
this point, and could not tell how to be resolved; at last, that in the fifth of 
the Revelations came into my mind, ‘And I beheld, and lo, in the midst of the throne 
and of the four beasts, and in the midst of the elders, stood a Lamb.’ In the midst 
of the throne, thought I, there is His Godhead; in the midst of the elders, there 
is His manhood; but oh! methought this did glister! it was a goodly touch, and gave 
me sweet satisfaction. That other scripture also did help me much in this, ‘To us 
a child is born, unto us a son is given; and the government shall be on his shoulder: 
and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counsellor, The mighty God, The everlasting 
Father, The Prince of Peace,’ etc. (<scripRef passage="Isaiah 9:6" id="iv-p122.1" parsed="|Isa|9|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.9.6">Isa. 9.6</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p123">123. Also, besides these teachings of God in His Word, the Lord made use of two 
things to confirm me in these things; the one was the errors of the Quakers, and 
the other was the guilt of sin; for as the Quakers did oppose His truth, so God 
did the more confirm me in it, by leading me into the scriptures that did wonderfully 
maintain it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p124">124. The errors that this people then maintained were: 1. That the holy Scriptures 
were not the Word of God. 2. That every man in the world had the spirit of Christ, 
grace, faith, etc. 3. That Christ Jesus, as crucified, and dying 1600 years ago, 
did not satisfy divine justice for the sins of the people. 4. That Christ’s flesh 
and blood was within the saints. 5. That the bodies of the good and bad that are 
buried in the churchyard shall not arise again. 6. That the resurrection is past 
with good men already. 7. That that man Jesus, that was crucified between two thieves 
on Mount Calvary, in the land of Canaan, by Jerusalem, was not ascended up above 
the starry heavens. 8. That He should not, even the same Jesus that died by the 
hands of the Jews, come again at the last day, and as man judge all nations, etc.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p125">125. Many more vile and abominable things were in those days fomented by them, 
by which I was driven to a more narrow search of the Scriptures, and was, through 
their light and testimony, not only enlightened, but greatly confirmed and comforted 
in the truth; and, as I said, the guilt of sin did help me much, for still as that 
would come upon me, the blood of Christ did take it off again, and again, and again, 
and that too, sweetly, according to the Scriptures. O friends! cry to God to reveal 
Jesus Christ unto you; there is none teacheth like Him.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p126">126. It would be too long for me here to stay, to tell you in particular how 
God did set me down in all the things of Christ, and how He did, that He might do 
so, lead me into His words; yea, and also how He did open them unto me, make them 
shine before me, and comfort me over and over, both of His own being, and the being 
of His Son, and Spirit, and Word, and gospel.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p127">127. Only this, as I said before I will say unto you again, that in general He 
was pleased to take this course with me; first, to suffer me to be afflicted with 
temptation concerning them, and then reveal them to me: as sometimes I should lie 
under great guilt for sin, even crushed to the ground therewith, and then the Lord 
would show me the death of Christ; yea, and so sprinkle my conscience with His blood, 
that I should find, and that before I was aware, that in that conscience where but 
just now did reign and rage the law, even there would rest and abide the peace and 
love of God through Christ.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p128">128. Now had I an evidence, as I thought, of my salvation from heaven, with many 
golden seals thereon, all hanging in my sight; now could I remember this manifestation 
and the other discovery of grace, with comfort; and should often long and desire 
that the last day were come, that I might for ever be inflamed with the sight, and 
joy, and communion with Him whose head was crowned with thorns, whose face was spit 
on, and body broken, and soul made an offering for my sins: for whereas, before, 
I lay continually trembling at the mouth of hell, now methought I was got so far 
therefrom that I could not, when I looked back, scarce discern it; and oh! thought 
I, that I were fourscore years old now, that I might die quickly, that my soul might 
be gone to rest.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p129">129. But before I had got thus far out of these my temptations, I did greatly 
long to see some ancient godly man’s experience, who had writ some hundreds of years 
before I was born; for those who had writ in our days, I thought, but I desire them 
now to pardon me, that they had writ only that which others felt, or else had, through 
the strength of their wits and parts, studied to answer such objections as they 
perceived others were perplexed with, without going down themselves into the deep. 
Well, after many such longings in my mind, the God in whose hands are all our days 
and ways, did cast into my hand, one day, a book of Martin Luther; it was his comment 
on the Galatians—it also was so old that it was ready to fall piece from piece if 
I did but turn it over. Now I was pleased much that such an old book had fallen 
into my hands; the which, when I had but a little way perused, I found my condition, 
in his experience, so largely and profoundly handled, as if his book had been written 
out of my heart. This made me marvel; for thus thought I, This man could not know 
anything of the state of Christians now, but must needs write and speak the experience 
of former days.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p130">130. Besides, he doth most gravely, also, in that book, debate of the rise of 
these temptations, namely, blasphemy, desperation, and the like; showing that the 
law of Moses as well as the devil, death, and hell hath a very great hand therein, 
the which, at first, was very strange to me; but considering and watching, I found 
it so indeed. But of particulars here I intend nothing; only this, methinks, I must 
let fall before all men, I do prefer this book of Martin Luther upon the Galatians, 
excepting the Holy Bible, before all the books that ever I have seen, as most fit 
for a wounded conscience.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p131">131. And now I found, as I thought, that I loved Christ dearly; oh! methought 
my soul cleaved unto Him, my affections cleaved unto Him, I felt love unto Him as 
hot as fire; and now, as Job said, I thought I should die in my nest; but I did 
quickly find that my great love was but little, and that I, who had, as I thought, 
such burning love to Jesus Christ, could let Him go again for a very trifle; God 
can tell how to abase us, and can hide pride from man. Quickly after this my love 
was tried to purpose.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p132">132. For after the Lord had, in this manner, thus graciously delivered me from 
this great and sore temptation, and had set me down so sweetly in the faith of His 
holy gospel, and had given me such strong consolation and blessed evidence from 
heaven touching my interest in His love through Christ; the tempter came upon me 
again, and that with a more grievous and dreadful temptation than before.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p133">133. And that was, To sell and part with this most blessed Christ, to exchange 
Him for the things of this life, for anything. The temptation lay upon me for the 
space of a year, and did follow me so continually that I was not rid of it one day 
in a month, no, not sometimes one hour in many days together, unless when I was 
asleep.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p134">134. And though, in my judgment, I was persuaded that those who were once effectually 
in Christ, as I hoped, through His grace, I had seen myself, could never lose Him 
for ever—for ‘the land shall not be sold for ever, for the land is mine,’ saith 
God (<scripRef passage="Leviticus 25:23" id="iv-p134.1" parsed="|Lev|25|23|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Lev.25.23">Lev. 25.23</scripRef>)—yet it was a continual vexation to me to think that I should have 
so much as one such thought within me against a Christ, a Jesus, that had done for 
me as He had done; and yet then I had almost none others, but such blasphemous ones.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p135">135. But it was neither my dislike of the thought, nor yet any desire and endeavour 
to resist it that in the least did shake or abate the continuation, or force and 
strength thereof; for it did always, in almost whatever I thought, intermix itself 
therewith in such sort that I could neither eat my food, stoop for a pin, chop a 
stick, or cast mine eye to look on this, or that, but still the temptation would 
come, Sell Christ for this, or sell Christ for that; sell Him, sell Him.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p136">136. Sometimes it would run in my thoughts, not so little as a hundred times 
together, Sell Him, sell Him, sell Him; against which I may say, for whole hours 
together, I have been forced to stand as continually leaning and forcing my spirit 
against it, lest haply, before I were aware, some wicked thought might arise in 
my heart that might consent thereto; and sometimes also the tempter would make me 
believe I had consented to it, then should I be as tortured upon a rack for whole 
days together.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p137">137. This temptation did put me to such scares, lest I should at sometimes, I 
say, consent thereto, and be overcome therewith, that by the very force of my mind 
in labouring to gainsay and resist this wickedness, my very body also would be put 
into action or motion by way of pushing or thrusting with my hands or elbows, still 
answering as fast as the destroyer said, Sell Him; I will not, I will not, I will 
not, I will not; no, not for thousands, thousands, thousands of worlds. Thus reckoning 
lest I should in the midst of these assaults, set too low a value of Him, even until 
I scarce well knew where I was, or how to be composed again.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p138">138. At these seasons he would not let me eat my food at quiet; but, forsooth, 
when I was set at the table at my meat, I must go hence to pray; I must leave my 
food now, and just now, so counterfeit holy also would this devil be. When I was 
thus tempted, I should say in myself, Now I am at my meat, let me make an end. No, 
said he, you must do it now, or you will displease God, and despise Christ. Wherefore 
I was much afflicted with these things; and because of the sinfulness of my nature, 
imagining that these things were impulses from God, I should deny to do it, as if 
I denied God; and then should I be as guilty, because I did not obey a temptation 
of the devil, as if I had broken the law of God indeed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p139">139. But to be brief, one morning, as I did lie in my bed, I was, at other times, 
most fiercely assaulted with this temptation, to sell and part with Christ; the 
wicked suggestion still running in my mind, Sell Him, sell Him, sell Him, sell Him, 
sell Him, as fast as a man could speak; against which also, in my mind, as at other 
times, I answered, No, no, not for thousands, thousands, thousands, at least twenty 
times together. But at last, after much striving, even until I was almost out of 
breath, I felt this thought pass through my heart, Let Him go, if He will! and I 
thought also, that I felt my heart freely consent thereto. Oh, the diligence of 
Satan! Oh, the desperateness of man’s heart!</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p140">140. Now was the battle won, and down I fell, as a bird that is shot from the 
top of a tree, into great guilt, and fearful despair. Thus getting out of my bed, 
I went moping into the field; but God knows, with as heavy a heart as mortal man, 
I think, could bear; where, for the space of two hours, I was like a man bereft 
of life, and as now past all recovery, and bound over to eternal punishment.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p141">141. And withal, that scripture did seize upon my soul, ‘Or profane person, as 
Esau, who for one morsel of meat, sold his birthright; for ye know, how that afterward, 
when he would have inherited the blessing, he was rejected; for he found no place 
of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 12:16,17" id="iv-p141.1" parsed="|Heb|12|16|12|17" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.16-Heb.12.17">Heb. 12.16,17</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p142">142. Now was I as one bound, I felt myself shut up unto the judgment to come; 
nothing now for two years together would abide with me, but damnation, and an expectation 
of damnation; I say, nothing now would abide with me but this, save some few moments 
for relief, as in the sequel you will see.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p143">143. These words were to my soul like fetters of brass to my legs, in the continual 
sound of which I went for several months together. But about ten or eleven o’clock 
one day, as I was walking under a hedge, full of sorrow and guilt, God knows, and 
bemoaning myself for this hard hap that such a thought should arise within me; suddenly 
this sentence bolted in upon me, The blood of Christ remits all guilt. At this I 
made a stand in my spirit; with that, this word took hold upon me, ‘The blood of 
Jesus Christ, his Son, cleanseth us from all sin’ (<scripRef passage="1John 1:7" id="iv-p143.1" parsed="|1John|1|7|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1John.1.7">1 John 1.7</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p144">144. Now I began to conceive peace in my soul, and methought I saw as if the 
tempter did leer and steal away from me, as being ashamed of what he had done. At 
the same time also I had my sin, and the blood of Christ thus represented to me, 
that my sin, when compared to the blood of Christ, was no more to it, than this 
little clot or stone before me, is to this vast and wide field that here I see. 
This gave me good encouragement for the space of two or three hours; in which time 
also, methought I saw, by faith, the Son of God, as suffering for my sins; but because 
it tarried not, I therefore sunk in my spirit, under exceeding guilt again.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p145">145. But chiefly by the afore-mentioned scripture, concerning Esau’s selling 
of his birthright; for that scripture would lie all day long, all the week long, 
yea, all the year long in my mind, and hold me down, so that I could by no means 
lift up myself; for when I would strive to turn me to this scripture, or that, for 
relief, still that sentence would be sounding in me, ‘For ye know, how that afterward, 
when he would have inherited the blessing—he found no place of repentance, though 
he sought it carefully with tears.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p146">146. Sometimes, also, I should have a touch from that in <scripRef passage="Luke 22:32" id="iv-p146.1" parsed="|Luke|22|32|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.22.32">Luke 22.32</scripRef>, ‘I have 
prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not’; but it would not abide upon me; neither 
could I indeed, when I considered my state, find ground to conceive in the least, 
that there should be the root of that grace within me, having sinned as I had done. 
Now was I torn and rent in heavy case, for many days together.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p147">147. Then began I with sad and careful heart, to consider of the nature and largeness 
of my sin, and to search in the Word of God, if I could in any place espy a word 
of promise, or any encouraging sentence by which I might take relief. Wherefore 
I began to consider that third of Mark, All manner of sins and blasphemies shall 
be forgiven unto the sons of men, wherewith soever they shall blaspheme. Which place, 
methought, at a blush, did contain a large and glorious promise, for the pardon 
of high offences; but considering the place more fully, I thought it was rather 
to be understood as relating more chiefly to those who had, while in a natural state, 
committed such things as there are mentioned; but not to me, who had not only received 
light and mercy, but that had, both after, and also contrary to that, so slighted 
Christ as I had done.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p148">148. I feared therefore that this wicked sin of mine might be that sin unpardonable, 
of which he there thus speaketh, ‘But he that shall blaspheme against the Holy Ghost 
hath never forgiveness, but is in danger of eternal damnation’ (<scripRef passage="Mark 3:29" id="iv-p148.1" parsed="|Mark|3|29|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Mark.3.29">Mark 3.29</scripRef>). And 
I did the rather give credit to this, because of that sentence in the Hebrews, ‘For 
ye know, how that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, he was rejected; 
for he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears.’ 
And this stuck always with me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p149">149. And now was I both a burden and a terror to myself, nor did I ever so know, 
as now, what it was to be weary of my life, and yet afraid to die. Oh, how gladly 
now would I have been anybody but myself! Anything but a man! and in any condition 
but mine own! for there was nothing did pass more frequently over my mind, than 
that it was impossible for me to be forgiven my transgression, and to be saved from 
wrath to come.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p150">150. And now began I to labour to call again time that was past; wishing a thousand 
times twice told, that the day was yet to come, when I should be tempted to such 
a sin; concluding with great indignation, both against my heart, and all assaults, 
how I would rather have been torn in pieces, than found a consenter thereto. But 
alas! these thoughts, and wishings, and resolvings, were now too late to help me; 
the thought had passed my heart, God hath let me go, and I am fallen. Oh! thought 
I, ‘that it was with me as in months past, as in the days when God preserved me!’ 
(<scripRef passage="Job 29:2" id="iv-p150.1" parsed="|Job|29|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Job.29.2">Job 29.2</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p151">151. Then again, being loath and unwilling to perish, I began to compare my sin 
with others, to see if I could find that any of those that were saved had done as 
I had done. So I considered David’s adultery and murder, and found them most heinous 
crimes; and those too committed after light and grace received; but yet by considering, 
I perceived that his transgressions were only such as were against the law of Moses; 
from which the Lord Christ could, with the consent of His Word, deliver him; but 
mine was against the gospel, yea, against the Mediator thereof; I had sold my Saviour.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p152">152. Now again should I be as if racked upon the wheel, when I considered, that, 
besides the guilt that possessed me, I should be so void of grace, so bewitched. 
What, thought I, must it be no sin but this? Must it needs be the great transgression 
(<scripRef passage="Psalm 19:13" id="iv-p152.1" parsed="|Ps|19|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.19.13">Ps. 19.13</scripRef>)? Must that wicked one touch my soul (<scripRef passage="1John 5:18" id="iv-p152.2" parsed="|1John|5|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1John.5.18">1 John 5.18</scripRef>)? Oh, what stings did 
I find in all these sentences!</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p153">153. What, thought I, is there but one sin that is unpardonable? But one sin 
that layeth the soul without the reach of God’s mercy; and must I be guilty of that? 
Must it needs be that? Is there but one sin among so many millions of sins, for 
which there is no forgiveness; and must I commit this? Oh, unhappy sin! Oh, unhappy 
man! These things would so break and confound my spirit, that I could not tell what 
to do; I thought, at times, they would have broke my wits; and still, to aggravate 
my misery, that would run in my mind, ‘Ye know how that afterward, when he would 
have inherited the blessing, he was rejected.’ Oh! none knows the terrors of those 
days but myself.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p154">154. After this I came to consider of Peter’s sin, which he committed in denying 
his Master; and indeed, this came nighest to mine, of any that I could find; for 
he had denied his Saviour, as I, and that after light and mercy received; yea, and 
that too, after warning given him. I also considered, that he did it both once and 
twice; and that, after time to consider betwixt. But though I put all these circumstances 
together, that, if possible, I might find help, yet I considered again, that his 
was but a denial of his Master, but mine was a selling of my Saviour. Wherefore 
I thought with myself, that I came nearer to Judas, than either to David or Peter.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p155">155. Here again my torment would flame out and afflict me; yea, it would grind 
me, as it were, to powder, to discern the preservation of God towards others, while 
I fell into the snare; for in my thus considering of other men’s sins, and comparing 
of them with my own, I could evidently see how God preserved them, notwithstanding 
their wickedness, and would not let them, as he had let me, to become a son of perdition.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p156">156. But oh, how did my soul, at this time, prize the preservation that God did 
set about his people! Ah, how safely did I see them walk, whom God had hedged in! 
They were within His care, protection, and special providence; though they were 
full as bad as I by nature; yet because He loved them, He would not suffer them 
to fall without the range of mercy; but as for me, I was gone, I had done it; He 
would not preserve me, nor keep me; but suffered me, because I was a reprobate, 
to fall as I had done. Now, did those blessed places, that spake of God’s keeping 
His people, shine like the sun before me, though not to comfort me, but to show 
me the blessed state and heritage of those whom the Lord had blessed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p157">157. Now I saw, that as God had His hand in all providences and dispensation 
that overtook His elect, so He had His hand in all the temptations that they had 
to sin against Him, not to animate them unto wickedness, but to choose their temptations 
and troubles for them; and also to leave them, for a time, to such sins only as 
might not destroy, but humble them; as might not put them beyond, but lay them in 
the way of the renewing of His mercy. But oh, what love, what care, what kindness 
and mercy did I now see, mixing itself with the most severe and dreadful of all 
God’s ways to His people! He would let David, Hezekiah, Solomon, Peter, and others 
fall, but He would not let them fall into sin unpardonable, nor into hell for sin. 
Oh! thought I, these be the men that God hath loved; these be the men that God, 
though He chastiseth them, keeps them in safety by Him, and them whom He makes to 
abide under the shadow of the Almighty. But all these thoughts added sorrow, grief, 
and horror to me, as whatever I now thought on, it was killing to me. If I thought 
how God kept His own, that was killing to me. If I thought of how I was falling 
myself, that was killing to me. As all things wrought together for the best, and 
to do good to them that were the called, according to His purpose; so I thought 
that all things wrought for my damage, and for my eternal overthrow.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p158">158. Then, again, I began to compare my sin with the sin of Judas, that, if possible, 
I might find that mine differed from that which, in truth, is unpardonable. And, 
oh! thought I, if it should differ from it, though but the breadth of an hair, what 
a happy condition is my soul in! And, by considering, I found that Judas did his 
intentionally, but mine was against my prayer and strivings; besides, his was committed 
with much deliberation, but mine in a fearful hurry, on a sudden; all this while 
I was tossed to and fro, like the locusts, and driven from trouble to sorrow; hearing 
always the sound of Esau’s fall in mine ears, and of the dreadful consequences thereof.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p159">159. Yet this consideration about Judas, his sin, was, for a while, some little 
relief unto me; for I saw I had not, as to the circumstances, transgressed so foully 
as he. But this was quickly gone again, for, I thought with myself, there might 
be more ways than one to commit the unpardonable sin; also I thought that there 
might be degrees of that, as well as of other transgressions; wherefore, for aught 
I yet could perceive, this iniquity of mine might be such, as might never be passed 
by.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p160">160. I was often now ashamed, that I should be like such an ugly man as Judas; 
I thought, also, how loathsome I should be unto all the saints at the day of judgment; 
insomuch, that now I could scarce see a good man, that I believed had a good conscience, 
but I should feel my heart tremble at him, while I was in his presence. Oh! now 
I saw a glory in walking with God, and what a mercy it was to have a good conscience 
before Him.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p161">161. I was much about this time tempted to content myself, by receiving some 
false opinion; as that there should be no such thing as a day of judgment, that 
we should not rise again, and that sin was no such grievous thing; the tempter suggesting 
thus, For if these things should indeed be true, yet to believe otherwise, would 
yield you ease for the present. If you must perish, never torment yourself so much 
beforehand; drive the thoughts of damning out of your mind, by possessing your mind 
with some such conclusions that Atheists and Ranters do use to help themselves withal.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p162">162. But oh! when such thoughts have led through my heart, how, as it were, within 
a step, hath death and judgment been in my view; methought the judge stood at the 
door, I was as if it was come already; so that such things could have no entertainment. 
But, methinks, I see by this, that Satan will use any means to keep the soul from 
Christ; he loveth not an awakened frame of spirit; security, blindness, darkness, 
and error is the very kingdom and habitation of the wicked one.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p163">163. I found it hard work now to pray to God, because despair was swallowing 
me up; I thought I was, as with a tempest, driven away from God, for always when 
I cried to God for mercy, this would come in, It is too late, I am lost, God hath 
let me fall; not to my correction, but condemnation; my sin is unpardonable; and 
I know, concerning Esau, how that, after he had sold his birthright, he would have 
received the blessing, but was rejected. About this time, I did light on that dreadful 
story of that miserable mortal, Francis Spira; a book that was to my troubled spirit 
as salt, when rubbed into a fresh wound; every sentence in that book, every groan 
of that man, with all the rest of his actions in his dolours, as his tears, his 
prayers, his gnashing of teeth, his wringing of hands, his twining and twisting, 
languishing and pining away under that mighty hand of God that was upon him, was 
as knives and daggers in my soul; especially that sentence of his was frightful 
to me, Man knows the beginning of sin, but who bounds the issues thereof? Then would 
the former sentence, as the conclusion of all, fall like a hot thunderbolt again</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p164">upon my conscience; ‘for you know how that afterward, when he would have inherited 
the blessing, he was rejected; for he found no place of repentance, though he sought 
it carefully with tears.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p165">164. Then was I struck into a very great trembling, insomuch that at sometimes 
I could, for whole days together, feel my very body, as well as my mind, to shake 
and totter under the sense of the dreadful judgment of God, that should fall on 
those that have sinned that most fearful and unpardonable sin. I felt also such 
a clogging and heat at my stomach, by reason of this my terror, that I was, especially 
at some times, as if my breast bone would have split in sunder; then I thought of 
that concerning Judas, who, by his falling headlong, burst asunder, and all his 
bowels gushed out (<scripRef passage="Acts 1:18" id="iv-p165.1" parsed="|Acts|1|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.1.18">Acts 1:18</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p166">165. I feared also that this was the mark that the Lord did set on Cain, even 
continued fear and trembling, under the heavy load of guilt that he had charged 
on him for the blood of his brother Abel. Thus did I wind, and twine, and shrink, 
under the burden that was upon me; which burden also did so oppress me, that I could 
neither stand, nor go, nor lie, either at rest or quiet.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p167">166. Yet that saying would sometimes come to my mind, He hath received gifts 
for the rebellious (<scripRef passage="Psalm 68:18" id="iv-p167.1" parsed="|Ps|68|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.68.18">Ps. 68.18</scripRef>). ‘The rebellious,’ thought I; why, surely they are 
such as once were under subjection to their prince, even those who, after they have 
sworn subjection to his government, have taken up arms against him; and this, thought 
I, is my very condition; once I loved Him, feared Him, served Him; but now I am 
a rebel; I have sold Him, I have said, Let Him go if He will; but yet He has gifts 
for rebels, and then why not for me?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p168">167. This sometimes I thought on, and should labour to take hold thereof, that 
some, though small, refreshment might have been conceived by me; but in this also 
I missed of my desire, I was driven with force beyond it, I was like a man that 
is going to the place of execution, even by that place where he would fain creep 
in and hide himself, but may not.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p169">168. Again, after I had thus considered the sins of the saints in particular, 
and found mine went beyond them, then I began to think thus with myself: Set the 
case I should put all theirs together, and mine alone against them, might I not 
then find some encouragement? For if mine, though bigger than any one, yet should 
but be equal to all, then there is hopes; for that blood that hath virtue enough 
in it to wash away all theirs, hath also virtue enough in it to do away mine, though 
this one be full as big, if no bigger, than all theirs. Here, again, I should consider 
the sin of David, of Solomon, of Manasseh, of Peter, and the rest of the great offenders; 
and should also labour, what I might with fairness, to aggravate and heighten their 
sins by several circumstances: but, alas! it was all in vain.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p170">169. I should think with myself that David shed blood to cover his adultery, 
and that by the sword of the children of Ammon; a work that could not be done but 
by continuance and deliberate contrivance, which was a great aggravation to his 
sin. But then this would turn upon me: Ah! but these were but sins against the law, 
from which there was a Jesus sent to save them; but yours is a sin against the Saviour, 
and who shall save you from that?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p171">170. Then I thought on Solomon, and how he sinned in loving strange women, in 
falling away to their idols, in building them temples, in doing this after light, 
in his old age, after great mercy received; but the same conclusion that cut me 
off in the former consideration, cut me off as to this; namely, that all those were 
but sins against the law, for which God had provided a remedy; but I had sold my 
Saviour, and there now remained no more sacrifice for sin.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p172">171. I would then add to those men’s sins, the sins of Manasseh, how that he 
built altars for idols in the house of the Lord; he also observed times, used enchantments, 
had to do with wizards, was a wizard, had his familiar spirits, burned his children 
in the fire in sacrifice to devils, and made the streets of Jerusalem run down with 
the blood of innocents. These, I thought, are great sins, sins of a bloody colour; 
yea, it would turn again upon me: They are none of them of the nature of yours; 
you have parted with Jesus, you have sold your Saviour.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p173">172. This one consideration would always kill my heart, My sin was point-blank 
against my Saviour; and that too, at that height, that I had in my heart said of 
Him, Let Him go if He will. Oh! methought, this sin was bigger than the sins of 
a country, of a kingdom, or of the whole world, no one pardonable, nor all of them 
together, was able to equal mine; mine outwent them every one.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p174">173. Now I should find my mind to flee from God, as from the face of a dreadful 
judge; yet this was my torment, I could not escape His hand: ‘It is a fearful thing 
to fall into the hands of the living God’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 10:31" id="iv-p174.1" parsed="|Heb|10|31|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.10.31">Heb. 10.31</scripRef>). But blessed be His grace, 
that scripture, in these flying sins, would call as running after me, ‘I have blotted 
out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions; and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto 
me, for I have redeemed thee’ (<scripRef passage="Isaiah 44:22" id="iv-p174.2" parsed="|Isa|44|22|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.44.22">Isa. 44.22</scripRef>). This, I say, would come in upon my mind, 
when I was fleeing from the face of God; for I did flee from His face, that is, 
my mind and spirit fled before Him; by reason of His highness, I could not endure; 
then would the text cry, ‘Return unto me, for I have redeemed thee.’ Indeed, this 
would make me make a little stop, and, as it were, look over my shoulder behind 
me, to see if I could discern that the God of grace did follow me with a pardon 
in His hand, but I could no sooner do that, but all would be clouded and darkened 
again by that sentence, ‘For you know how that afterward, when he would have inherited 
the blessing, he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with 
tears.’ Wherefore I could not return, but fled, though at sometimes it cried ‘Return, 
return’, as if it did holloa after me. But I feared to close in therewith, lest 
it should not come from God; for that other, as I said was still sounding in my 
conscience, ‘For you know how that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, 
he was rejected’, etc.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p175">174. Once as I was walking to and fro in a good man’s shop, bemoaning of myself 
in my sad and doleful state, afflicting myself with self-abhorrence for this wicked 
and ungodly thought; lamenting, also, this hard hap of mine, for that I should commit 
so great a sin; greatly fearing I would not be pardoned; praying, also, in my heart, 
that if this sin of mine did differ from that against the Holy Ghost, the Lord would 
show it me. And being now ready to sink with fear, suddenly there was, as if there 
had rushed in at the window, the noise of wind upon me, but very pleasant, and as 
if I heard a voice speaking, Didst ever refuse to be justified by the blood of Christ? 
And withal my whole life and profession past was, in a moment, opened to me, wherein 
I was made to see that designedly I had not; so my heart answered groaningly, No. 
Then fell, with power, that word of God upon me, ‘See that ye refuse not him that speaketh’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 12:25" id="iv-p175.1" parsed="|Heb|12|25|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.25">Heb. 12.25</scripRef>). This made a strange seizure upon my spirit; it brought light 
with it, and commanded a silence in my heart of all those tumultuous thoughts that 
before did use, like masterless hell-hounds, to roar and bellow, and make a hideous 
noise within me. It showed me, also, that Jesus Christ had yet a word of grace and 
mercy for me, that He had not, as I had feared, quite forsaken and cast off my soul; 
yea, this was a kind of chide for my proneness to desperation; a kind of a threatening 
me if I did not, notwithstanding my sins and the heinousness of them, venture my 
salvation upon the Son of God. But as to my determining about this strange dispensation, 
what it was I knew not; from whence it came I knew not. I have not yet, in twenty 
years’ time, been able to make a judgment of it; I thought then what here I shall 
be loath to speak. But verily, that sudden rushing wind was as if an angel had come 
upon me; but both it and the salvation I will leave until the day of judgment; only 
this I say, it commanded a great calm in my soul, it persuaded me there might be 
hope; it showed me, as I thought, what the sin unpardonable was, and that my soul 
had yet the blessed privilege to flee to Jesus for mercy. But, I say, concerning 
this dispensation, I know not what yet to say unto it; which was, also, in truth, 
the cause that, at first, I did not speak of it in the book; I do now, also, leave 
it to be thought on by men of sound judgment. I lay not the stress of my salvation 
thereupon, but upon the Lord Jesus, in the promise; yet, seeing I am here unfolding 
of my secret things, I thought it might not be altogether inexpedient to let this 
also show itself, though I cannot now relate the matter as there I did experience 
it. This lasted, in the savour of it, for about three or four days, and then I began 
to mistrust and to despair again.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p176">175. Wherefore, still my life hung in doubt before me, not knowing which way 
I should tip; only this I found my soul desire, even to cast itself at the foot 
of grace, by prayer and supplication. But, oh! it was hard for me now to bear the 
face to pray to this Christ for mercy, against whom I had thus most vilely sinned; 
it was hard work, I say, to offer to look Him in the face against whom I had so 
vilely sinned; and, indeed, I have found it as difficult to come to God by prayer, 
after backsliding from Him, as to do any other thing. Oh, the shame that did now 
attend me! especially when I thought I am now a-going to pray to Him for mercy that 
I had so lightly esteemed but a while before! I was ashamed, yea, even confounded, 
because this villainy had been committed by me; but I saw there was but one way 
with me, I must go to Him and humble myself unto Him, and beg that He, of His wonderful 
mercy, would show pity to me, and have mercy upon my wretched sinful soul.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p177">176. Which, when the tempter perceived, he strongly suggested to me, That I ought 
not to pray to God; for prayer was not for any in my case, neither could it do me 
good, because I had rejected the Mediator, by whom all prayer came with acceptance 
to God the Father, and without whom no prayer could come into His presence. Wherefore, 
now to pray is but to add sin to sin; yea, now to pray, seeing God has cast you 
off, is the next way to anger and offend Him more than you ever did before.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p178">177. For God, saith he, hath been weary of you for these several years already, 
because you are none of His; your bawlings in His ears hath been no pleasant voice 
to Him; and, therefore, He let you sin this sin, that you might be quite cut off; 
and will you pray still? This the devil urged, and set forth that, in Numbers, when 
Moses said to the children of Israel, That because they would not go up to possess 
the land when God would have them, therefore, for ever after, God did bar them out 
from thence, though they prayed they might, with tears (<scripRef passage="Numbers 14:36,37" id="iv-p178.1" parsed="|Num|14|36|14|37" osisRef="Bible:Num.14.36-Num.14.37">Num. 14.36, 37</scripRef>, etc.).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p179">178. As it is said in another place (<scripRef passage="Exodus 21:14" id="iv-p179.1" parsed="|Exod|21|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Exod.21.14">Exod. 21.14</scripRef>), the man that sins presumptuously 
shall be taken from God’s altar, that he may die; even as Joab was by King Solomon, 
when he thought to find shelter there (<scripRef passage="1Kings 2:28" id="iv-p179.2" parsed="|1Kgs|2|28|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Kgs.2.28">1 Kings 2.28</scripRef>, etc.). These places did pinch 
me very sore; yet, my case being desperate, I thought with myself I can but die; 
and if it must be so, it shall once be said, that such an one died at the foot of 
Christ in prayer. This I did, but with great difficulty, God doth know; and that 
because, together with this, still that saying about Esau would be set at my heart, 
even like a flaming sword, to keep the way of the tree of life, lest I should taste 
thereof and live. Oh! who knows how hard a thing I found it to come to God in prayer.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p180">179. I did also desire the prayers of the people of God for me, but I feared 
that God would give them no heart to do it; yea, I trembled in my soul to think 
that some or other of them would shortly tell me, that God had said those words 
to them that He once did say to the prophet concerning the children of Israel, ‘Pray 
thou not for this people,’ for I have rejected them (<scripRef passage="Jeremiah 11:14" id="iv-p180.1" parsed="|Jer|11|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.11.14">Jer. 11.14</scripRef>). So, pray not for 
him, for I have rejected him. Yea, I thought that He had whispered this to some 
of them already, only they durst not tell me so, neither durst I ask them of it, 
for fear, if it should be so, it would make me quite beside myself. Man knows the 
beginning of sin, said Spira, but who bounds the issues thereof?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p181">180. About this time I took an opportunity to break my mind to an ancient Christian, 
and told him all my case; I told him, also, that I was afraid that I had sinned 
the sin against the Holy Ghost; and he told me he thought so too. Here, therefore, 
I had but cold comfort; but, talking a little more with him, I found him, though 
a good man, a stranger to much combat with the devil. Wherefore, I went to God again, 
as well as I could, for mercy still.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p182">181. Now, also, did the tempter begin to mock me in my misery, saying, that, 
seeing I had thus parted with the Lord Jesus, and provoked Him to displeasure, who 
would have stood between my soul and the flame of devouring fire, there was now 
but one way, and that was, to pray that God the Father would be the Mediator betwixt 
His Son and me, that we might be reconciled again, and that I might have that blessed 
benefit in Him that His blessed saints enjoyed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p183">182. Then did that scripture seize upon my soul, He is of one mind, and who can 
turn Him? Oh! I saw it was as easy to persuade Him to make a new world, a new covenant, 
or new Bible, besides that we have already, as to pray for such a thing. This was 
to persuade Him that what He had done already was mere folly, and persuade with 
Him to alter, yea, to disannul, the whole way of salvation; and then would that 
saying rend my soul asunder, ‘Neither is there salvation in any other: for there 
is none other name under heaven, given among men, whereby we must be saved’ (<scripRef passage="Acts 4:12" id="iv-p183.1" parsed="|Acts|4|12|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.4.12">Acts 
4.12</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p184">183. Now the most free, and full, and gracious words of the gospel were the greatest 
torment to me; yea, nothing so afflicted me as the thoughts of Jesus Christ, the 
remembrance of a Saviour; because I had cast Him off, brought forth the villainy 
of my sin, and my loss by it to mind; nothing did twinge my conscience like this. 
Every time that I thought of the Lord Jesus, of His grace, love, goodness, kindness, 
gentleness, meekness, death, blood, promises and blessed exhortations, comforts 
and consolations, it went to my soul like a sword; for still, unto these my considerations 
of the Lord Jesus, these thoughts would make place for themselves in my heart; aye, 
this is the Jesus, the loving Saviour, the Son of God, whom thou hast parted with, 
whom you slighted, despised, and abused. This is the only Saviour, the only Redeemer, 
the only one that could so love sinners as to wash them from their sins in His own 
most precious blood; but you have no part nor lot in this Jesus, you have put Him 
away from you, you have said in your heart, Let Him go if He will. Now, therefore, 
you are severed from Him; you have severed yourself from Him. Behold, then, His 
goodness, but you yourself be no partaker of it. Oh, thought I, what have I lost! 
What have I parted with! What have I disinherited my poor soul of! Oh! it is sad 
to be destroyed by the grace and mercy of God; to have the Lamb, the Saviour, turn 
lion and destroyer (<scripRef passage="Revelation 6:1-17" id="iv-p184.1" parsed="|Rev|6|1|6|17" osisRef="Bible:Rev.6.1-Rev.6.17">Rev. 6</scripRef>). I also trembled, as I have said, at the sight of the 
saints of God, especially at those that greatly loved Him, and that made it their 
business to walk continually with Him in this world; for they did, both in their 
words, their carriages, and all their expressions of tenderness and fear to sin 
against their precious Saviour, condemn, lay guilt upon, and also add continual 
affliction and shame unto my soul. The dread of them was upon me, and I trembled 
at God’s Samuels (<scripRef passage="1Samuel 16:4" id="iv-p184.2" parsed="|1Sam|16|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Sam.16.4">1 Sam. 16.4</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p185">184. Now, also, the tempter began afresh to mock my soul another way, saying 
that Christ, indeed, did pity my case, and was sorry for my loss; but forasmuch 
as I had sinned and transgressed, as I had done, He could by no means help me, nor 
save me from what I feared; for my sin was not of the nature of theirs for whom 
He bled and died, neither was it counted with those that were laid to His charge 
when He hanged on the tree. Therefore, unless He should come down from heaven and 
die anew for this sin, though, indeed, He did greatly pity me, yet I could have 
no benefit of Him. These things may seem ridiculous to others, even as ridiculous 
as they were in themselves, but to me they were most tormenting cogitations; every 
of them augmented my misery, that Jesus Christ should have so much love as to pity 
me when He could not help me; nor did I think that the reason why He could not help 
me was because His merits were weak, or His grace and salvation spent on them already, 
but because His faithfulness to His threatening would not let Him extend His mercy 
to me. Besides, I thought, as I have already hinted, that my sin was not within 
the bounds of that pardon that was wrapped up in a promise; and if not, then I knew 
assuredly, that it was more easy for heaven and earth to pass away than for me to 
have eternal life. So that the ground of all these fears of mine did arise from 
a steadfast belief that I had of the stability of the holy Word of God, and, also, 
from my being misinformed of the nature of my sin.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p186">185. But oh! how this would add to my affliction, to conceit that I should be 
guilty of such a sin for which He did not die. These thoughts would so confound 
me, and imprison me, and tie me up from faith, that I knew not what to do; but, 
oh! I thought, that He would come down again! Oh! that the work of man’s redemption 
was yet to be done by Christ! How would I pray Him and entreat Him to count and 
reckon this sin amongst the rest for which He died! But this scripture would strike 
me down as dead, ‘Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death hath no 
more dominion over him’ (<scripRef passage="Romans 6:9" id="iv-p186.1" parsed="|Rom|6|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.6.9">Rom. 6.9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p187">186. Thus, by the strange and unusual assaults of the tempter, was my soul, like 
a broken vessel, driven as with the winds, and tossed sometimes headlong into despair, 
sometimes upon the covenant of works, and sometimes to wish that the new covenant, 
and the conditions thereof, might, so far forth as I thought myself concerned, be 
turned another way and changed. But in all these I was but as those that justle 
against the rocks; more broken, scattered, and rent. Oh, the unthought of imaginations, 
frights, fears, and terrors that are affected by a thorough application of guilt, 
yielded to desperation! this is the man that hath ‘his dwelling among the tombs’ 
with the dead; that is, always crying out and ‘cutting himself with stones’ (<scripRef passage="Mark 5:2-5" id="iv-p187.1" parsed="|Mark|5|2|5|5" osisRef="Bible:Mark.5.2-Mark.5.5">Mark 
5. 2-5</scripRef>). But I say, all in vain; desperation will not comfort him, the old covenant 
will not save him; nay, heaven and earth shall pass away before one jot or tittle 
of the Word and law of grace shall fall or be removed. This I saw, this I felt, 
and under this I groaned; yet this advantage I got thereby, namely, a further confirmation 
of the certainty of the way of salvation, and that the Scriptures were the Word 
of God! Oh! I cannot now express what then I saw and felt of the steadiness of Jesus 
Christ, the rock of man’s salvation; what was done could not be undone, added to, 
nor altered. I saw, indeed, that sin might drive the soul beyond Christ, even the 
sin which is unpardonable; but woe to him that was so driven, for the Word would 
shut him out.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p188">187. Thus was I always sinking, whatever I did think or do. So one day I walked 
to a neighbouring town, and sat down upon a settle in the street, and fell into 
a very deep pause about the most fearful state my sin had brought me to; and, after 
long musing, I lifted up my head, but methought I saw as if the sun that shineth 
in the heavens did grudge to give light, and as if the very stones in the street, 
and tiles upon the houses, did bend themselves against me; methought that they all 
combined together to banish me out of the world; I was abhorred of them, and unfit 
to dwell among them, or be partaker of their benefits, because I had sinned against 
the Saviour. O how happy, now, was every creature over what I was; for they stood 
fast and kept their station, but I was gone and lost.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p189">188. Then breaking out in the bitterness of my soul, I said to myself, with a 
grievous sigh, How can God comfort such a wretch as I? I had no sooner said it but 
this returned upon me, as an echo doth answer a voice, This sin is not unto death. 
At which I was as if I had been raised out of a grave, and cried out again, Lord, 
how couldest Thou find out such a word as this? for I was filled with admiration 
at the fitness, and, also, at the unexpectedness of the sentence, the fitness of 
the word, the rightness of the timing of it, the power, and sweetness, and light, 
and glory that came with it, was marvellous to me to find. I was now, for the time, 
out of doubt as to that about which I so much was in doubt before; my fears before 
were, that my sin was not pardonable, and so that I had no right to pray, to repent, 
etc., or that if I did, it would be of no advantage or profit to me. But now, thought 
I, if this sin is not unto death, then it is pardonable; therefore, from this I 
have encouragement to come to God, by Christ, for mercy, to consider the promise 
of forgiveness as that which stands with open arms to receive me, as well as others. 
This, therefore, was a great easement to my mind; to wit, that my sin was pardonable, 
that it was not the sin unto death (<scripRef passage="1John 5:16,17" id="iv-p189.1" parsed="|1John|5|16|5|17" osisRef="Bible:1John.5.16-1John.5.17">1 John 5.16, 17</scripRef>). None but those that know what 
my trouble, by their own experience, was, can tell what relief came to my soul by 
this consideration; it was a release to me from my former bonds, and a shelter from 
my former storm. I seemed now to stand upon the same ground with other sinners, 
and to have as good right to the word and prayer as any of them.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p190">189. Now, I say, I was in hopes that my sin was not unpardonable, but that there 
might be hopes for me to obtain forgiveness. But oh, how Satan did now lay about 
him for to bring me down again! But he could by no means do it, neither this day 
nor the most part of the next, for this sentence stood like a mill-post at my back; 
yet, towards the evening of the next day, I felt this word begin to leave me and 
to withdraw its supportation from me, and so I returned to my old fears again, but 
with a great deal of grudging and peevishness, for I feared the sorrow of despair; 
nor could my faith now longer retain this word.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p191">190. But the next day, at evening, being under many fears, I went to seek the 
Lord; and as I prayed, I cried, and my soul cried to Him in these words, with strong 
cries:—O Lord, I beseech thee, show me that thou hast loved me with everlasting 
love (<scripRef passage="Jeremiah 31:3" id="iv-p191.1" parsed="|Jer|31|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.31.3">Jer. 31.3</scripRef>). I had no sooner said it but, with sweetness, this returned upon 
me, as an echo or sounding again, ‘I have loved thee with an everlasting love.’ 
Now I went to bed at quiet; also, when I awaked the next morning, it was fresh upon 
my soul—and I believed it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p192">191. But yet the tempter left me not; for it could not be so little as an hundred 
times that he that day did labour to break my peace. Oh! the combats and conflicts 
that I did then meet with as I strove to hold by this word; that of Esau would fly 
in my face like to lightning. I should be sometimes up and down twenty times in 
an hour, yet God did bear me up and keep my heart upon this world, from which I 
had also, for several days together, very much sweetness and comfortable hopes of 
pardon; for thus it was made out to me, I loved thee whilst thou wast committing 
this sin, I loved thee before, I love thee still, and I will love thee for ever.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p193">192. Yet I saw my sin most barbarous, and a filthy crime, and could not but conclude, 
and that with great shame and astonishment, that I had horribly abused the holy 
Son of God; wherefore, I felt my soul greatly to love and pity Him, and my bowels 
to yearn towards Him; for I saw He was still my Friend, and did reward me good for 
evil; yea, the love and affection that then did burn within to my Lord and Saviour 
Jesus Christ did work, at this time, such a strong and hot desire of revengement 
upon myself for the abuse I had done unto him, that, to speak as I then thought, 
had I a thousand gallons of blood within my veins, I could freely then have spilt 
it all at the command and feet of this my Lord and Saviour.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p194">193. And as I was thus in musing and in my studies, considering how to love the 
Lord and to express my love to Him, that saying came in upon me, ‘If thou, Lord, 
shouldest mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand? But there is forgiveness with 
thee, that thou mayest be feared’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 130:3,4" id="iv-p194.1" parsed="|Ps|130|3|130|4" osisRef="Bible:Ps.130.3-Ps.130.4">Ps. 130.3, 4</scripRef>). These were good words to me, especially 
the latter part thereof; to wit, that there is forgiveness with the Lord, that He 
might be feared; that is, as then I understood it, that He might be loved and had 
in reverence; for it was thus made out to me, that the great God did set so high 
an esteem upon the love of His poor creatures, that rather than He would go without 
their love He would pardon their transgressions.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p195">194. And now was that word fulfilled on me, and I was also refreshed by it, Then 
shall they be ashamed and confounded, ‘and never open their mouth any more because 
of their shame, when I am pacified towards them for all that they have done, saith 
the Lord God’ (<scripRef passage="Ezekiel 16:63" id="iv-p195.1" parsed="|Ezek|16|63|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ezek.16.63">Ezek. 16.63</scripRef>). Thus was my soul at this time, and, as I then did think, 
for ever, set at liberty from being again afflicted with my former guilt and amazement.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p196">195. But before many weeks were over I began to despond again, fearing lest, 
notwithstanding all that I had enjoyed, that yet I might be deceived and destroyed 
at the last; for this consideration came strong into my mind, that whatever comfort 
and peace I thought I might have from the word of the promise of life, yet unless 
there could be found in my refreshment a concurrence and agreement in the Scriptures, 
let me think what I will thereof, and hold it never so fast, I should find no such 
thing at the end; ‘for the Scripture cannot be broken’ (<scripRef passage="John 10:35" id="iv-p196.1" parsed="|John|10|35|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.10.35">John 10.35</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p197">196. Now began my heart again to ache and fear I might meet with disappointment 
at the last, wherefore I began, with all seriousness, to examine my former comfort, 
and to consider whether one that had sinned as I have done, might with confidence 
trust upon the faithfulness of God, laid down in those words by which I had been 
comforted and on which I had leaned myself. But now were brought those sayings to 
my mind, ‘For it is impossible for those who were once enlightened, and have tasted 
of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghost, and have tasted 
the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, if they shall fall away, 
to renew them again unto repentance’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 6:4-6" id="iv-p197.1" parsed="|Heb|6|4|6|6" osisRef="Bible:Heb.6.4-Heb.6.6">Heb. 6.4-6</scripRef>). ‘For if we sin wilfully after 
that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more sacrifice 
for sins, but a certain fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation, which 
shall devour the adversaries’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 10:26,27" id="iv-p197.2" parsed="|Heb|10|26|10|27" osisRef="Bible:Heb.10.26-Heb.10.27">Heb. 10.26, 27</scripRef>). Even ‘as Esau, who for one morsel 
of meat sold his birthright; for ye know how that afterward, when he would have 
inherited the blessing, he was rejected; for he found no place of repentance, though 
he sought it carefully with tears’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 12:16,17" id="iv-p197.3" parsed="|Heb|12|16|12|17" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.16-Heb.12.17">Heb. 12.16, 17</scripRef>) .</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p198">197. Now was the word of the gospel forced from my soul, so that no promise or 
encouragement was to be found in the Bible for me; and now would that saying work 
upon my spirit to afflict me, ‘Rejoice not, O Israel, for joy as other people’ (<scripRef passage="Hosea 9:1" id="iv-p198.1" parsed="|Hos|9|1|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Hos.9.1">Hos. 
9.1</scripRef>). For I saw indeed there was cause of rejoicing for those that held to Jesus; 
but as for me, I had cut myself off by my transgressions, and left myself neither 
foot-hold, nor hand-hold, amongst all the stays and props in the precious word of 
life.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p199">198. And truly I did now feel myself to sink into a gulf, as an house whose foundation 
is destroyed; I did liken myself, in this condition, unto the case of a child that 
was fallen into a mill-pit, who, though it could make some shift to scrabble and 
spraul in the water, yet because it could find neither hold for hand nor foot, therefore 
at last it must die in that condition. So soon as this fresh assault had fastened 
on my soul, that scripture came into my heart, ‘This is for many days’ (<scripRef passage="Daniel 10:14" id="iv-p199.1" parsed="|Dan|10|14|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Dan.10.14">Dan. 10.14</scripRef>). 
And indeed I found it was so; for I could not be delivered, nor brought to peace 
again, until well-nigh two years and an half were completely finished. Wherefore 
these words, though in themselves they tended to discouragement, yet to me, who 
feared this condition would be eternal, they were at sometimes as an help and refreshment 
to me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p200">199. For, thought I, many days are not for ever, many days will have an end, 
therefore seeing I was to be afflicted, not a few, but many days, yet I was glad 
it was but for many days. Thus, I say, I could recall myself sometimes, and give 
myself a help, for as soon as ever the words came into my mind at first, I knew 
my trouble would be long; yet this would be but sometimes, for I could not always 
think on this, nor ever be helped by it, though I did.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p201">200. Now while these scriptures lay before me, and laid sin anew at my door, 
that saying in the eighteeneth of Luke, with others, did encourage me to prayer. 
Then the tempter again laid at me very sore, suggesting, that neither the mercy 
of God, nor yet the blood of Christ, did at all concern me, nor could they help 
me for my sin; therefore it was in vain to pray. Yet, thought I, I will pray. But, 
said the tempter, your sin is unpardonable. Well, said I, I will pray. It is to 
no boot, said he. Yet, said I, I will pray. So I went to prayer to God; and while 
I was at prayer, I uttered words to this effect, Lord, Satan tells me that neither 
Thy mercy, nor Christ’s blood, is sufficient to save my soul; Lord, shall I honour 
Thee most, by believing Thou wilt and canst? or him, by believing Thou neither wilt 
nor canst? Lord, I would fain honour Thee, by believing Thou wilt and canst.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p202">201. And as I was thus before the Lord, that scripture fastened on my heart, 
‘O man, great is thy faith’ (<scripRef passage="Matthew 15:28" id="iv-p202.1" parsed="|Matt|15|28|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.15.28">Matt. 15.28</scripRef>), even as if one had clapped me on the 
back, as I was on my knees before God. Yet I was not able to believe this, that 
this was a prayer of faith, till almost six months after; for I could not think 
that I had faith, or that there should be a word for me to act faith on; therefore 
I should still be as sticking in the jaws of desperation, and went mourning up and 
down in a sad condition, crying, Is His mercy clean gone? Is His mercy clean gone 
for ever? And I thought sometimes, even when I was groaning in these expressions, 
they did seem to make a question whether it was or no; yet I greatly feared it was.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p203">202. There was nothing now that I longed for more than to be put out of doubt, 
as to this thing in question; and, as I was vehemently desiring to know if there 
was indeed hopes for me, these words came rolling into my mind, ‘Will the Lord cast 
off for ever? and will he be favourable no more? Is his mercy clean gone for ever? 
Doth his promise fail for evermore? Hath God forgotten to be gracious? Hath he in 
anger shut up his tender mercies?’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 77:7-9" id="iv-p203.1" parsed="|Ps|77|7|77|9" osisRef="Bible:Ps.77.7-Ps.77.9">Ps. 77.7-9</scripRef>). And all the while they run in my 
mind, methought I had this still as the answer, It is a question whether He had 
or no; it may be He hath not. Yea, the interrogatory seemed to me to carry in it 
a sure affirmation that indeed He had not, nor would so cast off, but would be favourable; 
that His promise doth not fail, and that He had not forgotten to be gracious, nor 
would in anger shut up His tender mercy. Something, also, there was upon my heart 
at the same time, which I now cannot call to mind; which, with this text, did sweeten 
my heart, and made me conclude that His mercy might not be quite gone, nor clean 
gone for ever.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p204">203. At another time, I remember I was again much under the question, Whether 
the blood of Christ was sufficient to save my soul? In which doubt I continued from 
morning till about seven or eight at night: and at last, when I was, as it were, 
quite worn out with fear, lest it should not lay hold on me, these words did sound 
suddenly within my heart, He is able. But methought this word <span class="sc" id="iv-p204.1">able</span> was spoke 
so loud unto me; it showed such a great word, it seemed to be writ in great letters, 
and gave such a justle to my fear and doubt; I mean for the time it tarried with 
me, which was about a day, as I never had from that all my life, either before or 
after that (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 7:25" id="iv-p204.2" parsed="|Heb|7|25|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.7.25">Heb. 7.25</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p205">204. But one morning, when I was again at prayer, and trembling under the fear 
of this, that no word of God could help me, that piece of a sentence darted in upon 
me, ‘My grace is sufficient.’ At this methought I felt some stay, as if there might 
be hopes. But, oh, how good a thing it is for God to send His word! For about a 
fortnight before I was looking on this very place, and then I thought it could not 
come near my soul with comfort, therefore I threw down my book in a pet. Then I 
thought it was not large enough for me; no, not large enough; but now, it was as 
if it had arms of grace so wide that it could not only enclose me, but many more 
besides.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p206">205. By these words I was sustained, yet not without exceeding conflicts, for 
the space of seven or eight weeks; for my peace would be in and out, sometimes twenty 
times a day; comfort now, and trouble presently; peace now, and before I could go 
a furlong as full of fear and guilt as ever heart could hold; and this was not only 
now and then, but my whole seven weeks’ experience; for this about the sufficiency 
of grace, and that of Esau’s parting with his birthright, would be like a pair of 
scales within my mind, sometimes one end would be uppermost, and sometimes again 
the other; according to which would be my peace or trouble.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p207">206. Therefore I still did pray to God, that He would come in with this scripture 
more fully on my heart; to wit, that He would help me to apply the whole sentence, 
for as yet I could not: that He gave, I gathered; but farther I could not go, for 
as yet it only helped me to hope there might be mercy for me, ‘My grace is sufficient’; 
and though it came no farther, it answered my former question; to wit, that there 
was hope; yet, because ‘for thee’ was left out, I was not contented, but prayed 
to God for that also. Wherefore, one day, as I was in a meeting of God’s people, 
full of sadness and terror, for my fears again were strong upon me; and as I was 
now thinking my soul was never the better; but my case most sad and fearful, these 
words did, with great power, suddenly break in upon me, ‘My grace is sufficient 
for thee, my grace is sufficient for thee, my grace is sufficient for thee,’ three 
times together; and, oh! methought that every word was a mighty word unto me; as 
my, and grace, and sufficient, and for thee; they were then, and sometimes are still, 
far bigger than others be.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p208">207. At which time my understanding was so enlightened, that I was as though 
I had seen the Lord Jesus look down from heaven through the tiles upon me, and direct 
these words unto me. This sent me mourning home, it broke my heart, and filled me 
full of joy, and laid me low as the dust; only it stayed not long with me, I mean 
in this glory and refreshing comfort, yet it continued with me for several weeks, 
and did encourage me to hope. But so soon as that powerful operation of it was taken 
off my heart, that other about Esau returned upon me as before; so my soul did hang 
as in a pair of scales again, sometimes up and sometimes down, now in peace, and 
anon again in terror.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p209">208. Thus I went on for many weeks, sometimes comforted, and sometimes tormented; 
and, especially at some times, my torment would be very sore, for all those scriptures 
forenamed in the Hebrews, would be set before me, as the only sentences that would 
keep me out of heaven. Then, again, I should begin to repent that ever that thought 
went through me, I should also think thus with myself, Why, how many scriptures 
are there against me? There are but three or four: and cannot God miss them, and 
save me for all of them? Sometimes, again, I should think, Oh! if it were not for 
these three or four words, now how I might be comforted? And I could hardly forbear, 
at some times, but to wish them out of the book.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p210">209. Then methought I should see as if both Peter, and Paul, and John, and all 
the writers, did look with scorn upon me, and hold me in derision; and as if they 
said unto me, All our words are truth, one of as much force as another. It is not 
we that have cut you off, but you have cast away yourself; there is none of our 
sentences that you must take hold upon but these, and such as these: ‘It is impossible; 
there remains no more sacrifice for sin’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 6:1-20" id="iv-p210.1" parsed="|Heb|6|1|6|20" osisRef="Bible:Heb.6.1-Heb.6.20">Heb. 6</scripRef>). And ‘it had been better for them 
not to have known’ the will of God, ‘than, after they have known it, to turn from 
the holy commandment delivered unto them’ (<scripRef passage="2Peter 2:21" id="iv-p210.2" parsed="|2Pet|2|21|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Pet.2.21">II Pet. 2.21</scripRef>). ‘For the Scriptures cannot 
be broken.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p211">210. These, as the elders of the city of refuge, I saw were to be the judges 
both of my case and me, while I stood, with the avenger of blood at my heels, trembling 
at their gate for deliverance, also with a thousand fears and mistrusts, I doubted 
that they would shut me out for ever (<scripRef passage="Joshua 20:3,4" id="iv-p211.1" parsed="|Josh|20|3|20|4" osisRef="Bible:Josh.20.3-Josh.20.4">Josh. 20.3, 4</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p212">211. Thus was I confounded, not knowing what to do, nor how to be satisfied in 
this question, Whether the scriptures could agree in the salvation of my soul? I 
quaked at the apostles, I knew their words were true, and that they must stand for 
ever.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p213">212. And I remember one day, as I was in diverse frames of spirit, and considering 
that these frames were still according to the nature of the several scriptures that 
came in upon my mind; if this of grace, then was I quiet; but if that of Esau, then 
tormented; Lord, thought I, if both these scriptures would meet in my heart at once, 
I would which of them would get the better of me. So methought I had a longing mind 
that they might come both together upon me; yea, I desired of God they might.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p214">213. Well, about two or three days after, so they did indeed; they bolted both 
upon me at a time, and did work and struggle strangely in me for a while; at last, 
that about Esau’s birthright began to wax weak, and withdraw, and vanish and this 
about the sufficiency of grace prevailed with peace and joy. And as I was in a muse 
about this thing, that scripture came home upon me, ‘Mercy rejoiceth against judgment’ 
(<scripRef passage="James 2:13" id="iv-p214.1" parsed="|Jas|2|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jas.2.13">Jas. 2.13</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p215">214. This was a wonderment to me; yet truly I am apt to think it was of God; 
for the word of the law and wrath must give place to the word of life and grace; 
because, though the word of condemnation be glorious, yet the word of life and salvation 
doth far exceed in glory (<scripRef passage="2Corinthians 3:8-12" id="iv-p215.1" parsed="|2Cor|3|8|3|12" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.3.8-2Cor.3.12">II Cor. 3.8-12</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Mark 9:5-7" id="iv-p215.2" parsed="|Mark|9|5|9|7" osisRef="Bible:Mark.9.5-Mark.9.7">Mark 9.5-7</scripRef>). Also, that Moses and Elias 
must both vanish, and leave Christ and His saints alone.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p216">215. This scripture did also most sweetly visit my soul, ‘And him that cometh 
to me I will in no wise cast out’ (<scripRef passage="John 6:37" id="iv-p216.1" parsed="|John|6|37|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.6.37">John 6.37</scripRef>). Oh, the comfort that I have had from 
this word, ‘in no wise’! as who should say, by no means, for no thing, whatever 
he hath done. But Satan would greatly labour to pull this promise from me, telling 
of me that Christ did not mean me, and such as I, but sinners of a lower rank, that 
had not done as I had done. But I should answer him again, Satan, here is in this 
word no such exception; but ‘him that comes’, <span class="sc" id="iv-p216.2">him</span>, any him; ‘him that cometh 
to me I will in no wise cast out.’ And this I well remember still, that of all the 
sleights that Satan used to take this scripture from me, yet he never did so much 
as put this question, But do you come aright? And I have thought the reason was, 
because he thought I knew full well what coming aright was; for I saw that to come 
aright was to come as I was, a vile and ungodly sinner, and to cast myself at the 
feet of mercy, condemning myself for sin. If ever Satan and I did strive for any 
word of God in all my life, it was for this good word of Christ; he at one end and 
I at the other. Oh, what work did we make! It was for this in John, I say, that 
we did so tug and strive; he pulled and I pulled; but, God be praised, I got the 
better of him, I got some sweetness from it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p217">216. But notwithstanding all these helps and blessed words of grace, yet that 
of Esau’s selling of his birthright would still at times distress my conscience; 
for though I had been most sweetly comforted, and that but just before, yet when 
that came into my mind, it would make me fear again, I could not be quite rid thereof, 
it would every day be with me: wherefore now I went another way to work, even to 
consider the nature of this blasphemous thought; I mean, if I should take the words 
at the largest, and give them their own natural force and scope, even every word 
therein. So when I had thus considered, I found, that if they were fairly taken, 
they would amount to this, that I had freely left the Lord Jesus Christ to His choice, 
whether He would be my Saviour or no; for the wicked words were these, Let Him go 
if He will. Then that scripture gave me hope, ‘I will never leave thee nor forsake 
thee’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 13:5" id="iv-p217.1" parsed="|Heb|13|5|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.13.5">Heb. 13.5</scripRef>). O Lord, said I, but I have left Thee. Then it answered again, 
‘But I will not leave thee.’ For this I thank God also.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p218">217. Yet I was grievously afraid He should, and found it exceedingly hard to 
trust Him, seeing I had so offended Him. I could have been exceeding glad that this 
thought had never befallen, for then I thought I could, with more ease and freedom 
in abundance, have leaned upon His grace. I see it was with me, as it was with Joseph’s 
brethren; the guilt of their own wickedness did often fill them with fears that 
their brother would at last despise them (<scripRef passage="Genesis 50:15-17" id="iv-p218.1" parsed="|Gen|50|15|50|17" osisRef="Bible:Gen.50.15-Gen.50.17">Gen. 50.15-17</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p219">218. But above all the scriptures that I yet did meet with, that in the twentieth 
of Joshua was the greatest comfort to me, which speaks of the slayer that was to 
flee for refuge. And if the avenger of blood pursue the slayer, then, saith Moses, 
they that are the elders of the city of refuge shall not deliver him into his hand, 
because he smote his neighbour unwittingly, and hated him not aforetime. Oh, blessed 
be God for this word; I was convinced that I was the slayer; and that the avenger 
of blood pursued me, that I felt with great terror; only now it remained that I 
inquire whether I have right to enter the city of refuge. So I found that he must 
not, who lay in wait to shed blood: it was not the wilful murderer, but he who unwittingly 
did it, he who did unawares shed blood; not of spite, or grudge, or malice, he that 
shed it unwittingly, even he who did not hate his neighbour before. Wherefore:</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p220">219. I thought verily I was the man that must enter, because I had smitten my 
neighbour unwittingly, and hated him not aforetime. I hated Him not aforetime; no, 
I prayed unto Him, was tender of sinning against Him; yea, and against this wicked 
temptation I had strove for a twelvemonth before; yea, and also when it did pass 
through my heart, it did in spite of my teeth: wherefore I thought I had right to 
enter this city, and the elders, which are the apostles, were not to deliver me 
up. This, therefore, was great comfort to me; and did give me much ground of hope.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p221">220. Yet being very critical, for my smart had made me that I knew not what ground 
was sure enough to bear me, I had one question that my soul did much desire to be 
resolved about; and that was, Whether it be possible for any soul that hath indeed 
sinned the unpardonable sin, yet after that to receive though but the least true 
spiritual comfort from God through Christ? The which, after I had much considered, 
I found the answer was, No, they could not, and that for these reasons:</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p222">221. First, Because those that have sinned that sin, they are debarred a share 
in the blood of Christ, and being shut out of that, they must needs be void of the 
least ground of hope. and so of spiritual comfort; for to such ‘there remaineth 
no more sacrifice for sins’ (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 10:26" id="iv-p222.1" parsed="|Heb|10|26|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.10.26">Heb 10.26</scripRef>). Secondly, Because they are denied a share 
in the promise of life; they shall never be forgiven, ‘neither in this world, neither 
in that which is to come’ (<scripRef passage="Matthew 12:32" id="iv-p222.2" parsed="|Matt|12|32|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.12.32">Matt. 12.32</scripRef>). Thirdly, The Son of God excludes them also 
from a share in His blessed intercession, being for ever ashamed to own them both 
before His holy Father, and the blessed angels in heaven (<scripRef passage="Mark 8:38" id="iv-p222.3" parsed="|Mark|8|38|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Mark.8.38">Mark 8.38</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p223">222. When I had, with much deliberation, considered of this matter, and could 
not but conclude that the Lord had comforted me, and that too after this my wicked 
sin; then, methought, I durst venture to come nigh into those most fearful and terrible 
scriptures, with which all this while I had been so greatly affrighted, and on which, 
indeed, before I durst scarce cast mine eye, yea, had much ado an hundred times 
to forbear wishing them out of the Bible; for I thought they would destroy me; but 
now, I say, I began to take some measure of encouragement to come close to them, 
to read them, and consider them, and to weigh their scope and tendency.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p224">223. The which, when I began to do, I found their visage changed; for they looked 
not so grimly on me as before I thought they did. And, first, I came to the sixth 
of the Hebrews, yet trembling for fear it should strike me; which when I had considered, 
I found that the falling there intended was a falling quite away; that is, as I 
conceived, a falling from, and an absolute denial of the gospel of remission of 
sins by Christ; for from them the apostle begins his argument (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 6:1-3" id="iv-p224.1" parsed="|Heb|6|1|6|3" osisRef="Bible:Heb.6.1-Heb.6.3">ver. 1-3</scripRef>). Secondly, 
I found that this falling away must be openly, even in the view of the world, even 
so as ‘to put Christ to an open shame’. Thirdly, I found that those he there intended 
were for ever shut up of God, both in blindness, hardness, and impenitency: it is 
impossible they should be renewed again unto repentance. By all these particulars, 
I found, to God’s everlasting praise, my sin was not the sin in this place intended.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p225">First, I confessed I was fallen, but not fallen away, that is, from the profession 
of faith in Jesus unto eternal life. Secondly, I confessed that I had put Jesus 
Christ to shame by my sin, but not to open shame; I did not deny Him before men, 
nor condemn Him as a fruitless one before the world. Thirdly, Nor did I find that 
God had shut me up, or denied me to come, though I found it hard work indeed to 
come to Him by sorrow and repentance. Blessed be God for unsearchable grace.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p226">224. Then I considered that in the tenth of the Hebrews, and found that the wilful 
sin there mentioned is not every wilful sin, but that which doth throw off Christ, 
and then His commandments too. Secondly, That must also be done openly, before two 
or three witnesses, to answer that of the law (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 10:28" id="iv-p226.1" parsed="|Heb|10|28|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.10.28"> ver. 28</scripRef>). Thirdly, This sin cannot 
be committed, but with great despite done to the Spirit of grace; despising both 
the dissuasions from that sin, and the persuasions to the contrary. But the Lord 
knows, though this my sin was devilish, yet it did not amount to these.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p227">225. And as touching that in the twelfth of the Hebrews, about Esau’s selling 
his birthright, though this was that which killed me, and stood like a spear against 
me; yet now I did consider, First, That his was not a hasty thought against the 
continual labour of his mind, but a thought consented to and put in practice likewise, 
and that too after some deliberation (<scripRef passage="Genesis 25:1-34" id="iv-p227.1" parsed="|Gen|25|1|25|34" osisRef="Bible:Gen.25.1-Gen.25.34">Gen. 25</scripRef>). Secondly, it was a public and open 
action, even before his brother, if not before many more; this made his sin of a 
far more heinous nature than otherwise it would have been. Thirdly, He continued 
to slight his birthright: ‘He did eat and drink, and went his way; thus Esau despised 
his birthright’ (<scripRef passage="Genesis 25:34" id="iv-p227.2" parsed="|Gen|25|34|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.25.34">ver. 34</scripRef>). Yea, twenty years after, he was found to despise it still. 
‘And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; keep that thou hast unto thyself’ (<scripRef passage="Genesis 33:9" id="iv-p227.3" parsed="|Gen|33|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.33.9">Gen. 
33.9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p228">226. Now as touching this, that Esau sought a place of repentance; thus I thought, 
first, This was not for the birthright, but for the blessing; this is clear from 
the apostle, and is distinguished by Esau himself; ‘He took away my birthright (that 
is, formerly); and behold, now he hath taken away my blessing’ (<scripRef passage="Genesis 27:36" id="iv-p228.1" parsed="|Gen|27|36|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.27.36">Gen. 27.36</scripRef>). Secondly, 
Now, this being thus considered, I came again to the apostle, to see what might 
be the mind of God, in a New Testament style and sense, concerning Esau’s sin; and 
so far as I could conceive, this was the mind of God, that the birthright signified 
regeneration, and the blessing the eternal inheritance; for so the apostle seems 
to hint, ‘Lest there be any profane person, as Esau, who for one morsel of meat 
sold his birthright’; as if he should say, Lest there be any person amongst you 
that shall cast off all those blessed beginnings of God that at present are upon 
him, in order to a new birth, lest they become as Esau, even be rejected afterwards, 
when they would inherit the blessing.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p229">227. For many there are who, in the day of grace and mercy, despise those things 
which are indeed the birthright to heaven, who yet, when the deciding day appears, 
will cry as loud as Esau, ‘Lord, Lord, open to us’; but then, as Isaac would not 
repent, no more will God the Father, but will say, I have blessed these, yea, and 
they shall be blessed; but as for you, depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity 
(<scripRef passage="Genesis 27:33" id="iv-p229.1" parsed="|Gen|27|33|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.27.33">Gen. 27.33</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Luke 13:25-27" id="iv-p229.2" parsed="|Luke|13|25|13|27" osisRef="Bible:Luke.13.25-Luke.13.27">Luke 13.25-27</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p230">228. When I had thus considered these scriptures, and found that thus to understand 
them was not against, but according to other scriptures; this still added further 
to my encouragement and comfort, and also gave a great blow to that objection, to 
wit, that the scripture could not agree in the salvation of my soul. And now remained 
only the hinder part of the tempest, for the thunder was gone beyond me, only some 
drops did still remain, that now and then would fall upon me; but because my former 
frights and anguish were very sore and deep, therefore it did oft befal me still, 
as it befalleth those that have been scared with fire, I thought every voice was 
Fire, fire; every little touch would hurt my tender conscience.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p231">229. But one day, as I was passing in the field, and that too with some dashes 
on my conscience, fearing lest yet all was not right, suddenly this sentence fell 
upon my soul, Thy righteousness is in heaven; and methought withal, I saw, with 
the eyes of my soul, Jesus Christ at God’s right hand; there, I say, is my righteousness; 
so that wherever I was, or whatever I was a-doing, God could not say of me, He wants 
my righteousness, for that was just before Him. I also saw, moreover, that it was 
not my good frame of heart that made my righteousness better, nor yet my bad frame 
that made my righteousness worse; for my righteousness was Jesus Christ Himself, 
the same yesterday, and to-day, and for ever (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 13:8" id="iv-p231.1" parsed="|Heb|13|8|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.13.8">Heb. 13.8</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p232">230. Now did my chains fall off my legs indeed, I was loosed from my affliction 
and irons, my temptations had fled away; so that, from that time, those dreadful 
scriptures of God left off to trouble me now; now went I also home rejoicing, for 
the grace and love of God. So when I came home, I looked to see if I could find 
that sentence, Thy righteousness is in heaven; but could not find such a saying, 
wherefore my heart began to sink again, only that was brought to my remembrance, 
He ‘of God is made unto us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption’ 
by this word I saw the other sentence true (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 1:30" id="iv-p232.1" parsed="|1Cor|1|30|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.1.30">1 Cor. 1.30</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p233">231. For by this scripture, l saw that the man Christ Jesus, as He is distinct 
from us, as touching His bodily presence, so He is our righteousness and sanctification 
before God. Here, therefore, I lived for some time, very sweetly at peace with God 
through Christ; Oh, methought, Christ! Christ! there was nothing but Christ that 
was before my eyes, I was not only for looking upon this and the other benefits 
of Christ apart, as of His blood, burial, or resurrection, but considered Him as 
a whole Christ! As He in whom all these, and all other His virtues, relations, offices, 
and operations met together, and that as He sat on the right hand of God in heaven.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p234">232. It was glorious to me to see His exaltation, and the worth and prevalency 
of all His benefits, and that because of this: now I could look from myself to Him, 
and should reckon that all those graces of God that now were green in me, were yet 
but like those cracked groats and fourpence-halfpennies that rich men carry in their 
purses, when their gold is in their trunks at home! Oh, I saw my gold was in my 
trunk at home! In Christ, my Lord and Saviour! Now Christ was all; all my wisdom, 
all my righteousness, all my sanctification, and all my redemption.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p235">233. Further, the Lord did also lead me into the mystery of union with the Son 
of God, that I was joined to Him, that I was flesh of His flesh, and bone of His 
bone, and now was that a sweet word to me in <scripRef passage="Ephesians 5:30" id="iv-p235.1" parsed="|Eph|5|30|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eph.5.30">Eph. 5.30</scripRef>. By this also was my faith 
in Him, as my righteousness, the more confirmed to me; for if He and I were one, 
then His righteousness was mine, His merits mine, His victory also mine. Now could 
I see myself in heaven and earth at once; in heaven by my Christ, by my head, by 
my righteousness and life, though on earth by my body or person.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p236">234. Now I saw Christ Jesus was looked on of God, and should also be looked on 
by us, as that common or public person, in whom all the whole body of His elect 
are always to be considered and reckoned; that we fulfilled the law by Him, rose 
from the dead by Him, got the victory over sin, death, the devil, and hell, by Him; 
when He died, we died; and so of His resurrection. ‘Thy dead men shall live, together 
with my dead body shall they arise,’ saith he (<scripRef passage="Isaiah 26:19" id="iv-p236.1" parsed="|Isa|26|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Isa.26.19">Isa. 26.19</scripRef>). And again, ‘After two 
days will he revive us: in the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live 
in his sight’ (<scripRef passage="Hosea 6:2" id="iv-p236.2" parsed="|Hos|6|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Hos.6.2">Hos. 6.2</scripRef>); which is now fulfilled by the sitting down of the Son 
of Man on the right hand of the Majesty in the heavens, according to that to the 
Ephesians, He ‘hath raised us up together, and made us sit together in heavenly 
places in Christ Jesus’ (<scripRef passage="Ephesians 2:6" id="iv-p236.3" parsed="|Eph|2|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Eph.2.6">Eph. 2.6</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p237">235. Ah, these blessed considerations and scriptures, with many others of a like 
nature, were in those days made to spangle in mine eyes, so that I have cause to 
say, ‘Praise ye the Lord. Praise God in his sanctuary: praise him in the firmament 
of his power. Praise him for his mighty acts: praise him according to his excellent 
greatness’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 150:1,2" id="iv-p237.1" parsed="|Ps|150|1|150|2" osisRef="Bible:Ps.150.1-Ps.150.2">Ps. 150.1, 2</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p238">236. Having thus, in few words, given you a taste of the sorrow and affliction 
that my soul went under, by the guilt and terror that this my wicked thought did 
lay me under; and having given you also a touch of my deliverance therefrom, and 
of the sweet and blessed comfort that I met with afterwards, which comfort dwelt 
about a twelvemonth with my heart, to my unspeakable admiration; I will now, God 
willing, before I proceed any farther, give you in a word or two, what, as I conceive, 
was the cause of this temptation; and also after that, what advantage, at the last, 
it became unto my soul.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p239">237. For the causes, I conceived they were principally two: of which two I also 
was deeply convinced all the time this trouble lay upon me. The first was, for that 
I did not, when I was delivered from the temptation that went before, still pray 
to God to keep me from temptations that were to come; for though, as I can say in 
truth, my soul was much in prayer before this trial seized me, yet then I prayed 
only, or at the most, principally for the removal of present troubles, and for fresh 
discoveries of His love in Christ, which I saw afterwards was not enough to do; 
I also should have prayed that the great God would keep me from the evil that was 
to come.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p240">238. Of this I was made deeply sensible by the prayer of holy David, who, when 
he was under present mercy, yet prayed that God would hold him back from sin and 
temptation to come; ‘Then,’ saith he, ‘shall I be upright, I shall be innocent from 
the great transgression’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 19:13" id="iv-p240.1" parsed="|Ps|19|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Ps.19.13">Ps. 19.13</scripRef>). By this very word was I galled and condemned, 
quite through this long temptation.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p241">239. That also was another word that did much condemn me for my folly, in the 
neglect of this duty (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 4:16" id="iv-p241.1" parsed="|Heb|4|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.4.16">Heb 4.16</scripRef>), ‘Let us therefore come boldly unto the throne of 
grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need.’ This I 
had not done, and therefore was suffered thus to sin and fall, according to what 
is written, ‘Pray that ye enter not into temptation.’ And truly this very thing 
is to this day of such weight and awe upon me, that I dare not, when I come before 
the Lord, go off my knees, until I entreat Him for help and mercy against the temptations 
that are to come; and I do beseech thee, reader, that thou learn to beware of my 
negligence, by the affliction that for this thing I did for days, and months, and 
years, with sorrow undergo.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p242">240. Another cause of this temptation was, that I had tempted God; and on this 
manner did I do it. Upon a time my wife was great with child, and before her full 
time was come, her pangs, as of a woman in travail, were fierce and strong upon 
her, even as if she would have immediately fallen in labour, and been delivered 
of an untimely birth. Now, at this very time it was that I had been so strongly 
tempted to question the being of God, wherefore, as my wife lay crying by me, I 
said, but with all secrecy imaginable, even thinking in my heart, Lord, if thou 
wilt now remove this sad affliction from my wife, and cause that she be troubled 
no more therewith this night, and now were her pangs just upon her, then I shall 
know that thou canst discern the most secret thoughts of the heart.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p243">241. I had no sooner said it in my heart, but her pangs were taken from her, 
and she was cast into a deep sleep, and so she continued till morning; at this I 
greatly marvelled, not knowing what to think; but after I had been awake a good 
while, and heard her cry no more, I fell to sleeping also. So when I waked in the 
morning, it came upon me again, even what I had said in my heart the last night, 
and how the Lord had showed me that He knew my secret thoughts, which was a great 
astonishment unto me for several weeks after.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p244">242. Well, about a year and a half afterwards, that wicked sinful thought, of 
which I have spoken before, went through my wicked heart, even this thought, Let 
Christ go if He will; so when I was fallen under guilt for this, the remembrance 
of my other thought, and of the effect thereof, would also come upon me with this 
retort, which also carried rebuke along with it, Now you may see that God doth know 
the most secret thoughts of the heart.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p245">243. And with this, that of the passages that were betwixt the Lord and His servant 
Gideon fell upon my spirit; how because that Gideon tempted God with his fleece, 
both wet and dry, when he should have believed and ventured upon his words, therefore 
the Lord did afterwards so try him, as to send him against an innumerable company 
of enemies; and that too, as to outward appearance, without any strength or help 
(<scripRef passage="Judges 6:1-40" id="iv-p245.1" parsed="|Judg|6|1|6|40" osisRef="Bible:Judg.6.1-Judg.6.40">Judg. 6</scripRef>, <scripRef passage="Judges 7:1-25" id="iv-p245.2" parsed="|Judg|7|1|7|25" osisRef="Bible:Judg.7.1-Judg.7.25">7</scripRef>). Thus He served me, and that justly, for I should have believed His 
word, and not have put an <span class="sc" id="iv-p245.3">if</span> upon the all-seeingness of God.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p246">244. And now to show you something of the advantages that I also gained by this 
temptation; and first, By this I was made continually to possess in my soul a very 
wonderful sense both of the being and glory of God, and of His beloved Son; in the 
temptation that went before, my soul was perplexed with unbelief, blasphemy, hardness 
of heart, questions about the being of God, Christ, the truth of the Word, and certainty 
of the world to come; I say, then I was greatly assaulted and tormented with atheism; 
but now the case was otherwise, now was God and Christ continually before my face, 
though not in a way of comfort, but in a way of exceeding dread and terror. The 
glory of the holiness of God did at this time break me to pieces; and the bowels 
and compassion of Christ did break me as on the wheel; for I could not consider 
Him but as a lost and rejected Christ, the remembrance of which was as the continual 
breaking of my bones.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p247">245. The Scriptures now also were wonderful things unto me; I saw that the truth 
and verity of them were the keys of the kingdom of heaven; those that the Scriptures 
favour they must inherit bliss, but those that they oppose and condemn must perish 
evermore. Oh! this word, ‘For the Scriptures cannot be broken,’ would rend the caul 
of my heart; and so would that other, ‘Whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted 
unto them; and whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained.’ Now I saw the apostles 
to be the elders of the city of refuge (<scripRef passage="Joshua 20:4" id="iv-p247.1" parsed="|Josh|20|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Josh.20.4">Josh. 20.4</scripRef>), those that they were to receive 
in, were received to life; but those that they shut out were to be slain by the 
avenger of blood.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p248">246. Oh! one sentence of the Scripture did more afflict and terrify my mind, 
I mean those sentences that stood against me, as sometimes I thought they every 
one did, more, I say, than an army of forty thousand men that might have come against 
me. Woe be to him against whom the Scriptures bend themselves.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p249">247. By this temptation I was made to see more into the nature of the promises 
than ever I was before; for I lying now trembling under the mighty hand of God, 
continually torn and rent by the thunderings of His justice; this made me, with 
careful heart and watchful eye, with great seriousness, to turn over every leaf, 
and with much diligence, mixed with trembling, to consider every sentence, together 
with its natural force and latitude.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p250">248. By this temptation, also, I was greatly beaten off my former foolish practice, 
of putting by the word of promise when it came into my mind; for now, though I could 
not suck that comfort and sweetness from the promise as I had done at other times, 
yea, like to a man a-sinking, I should catch at all I saw; formerly I thought I 
might not meddle with the promise unless I felt its comfort, but now it was no time 
thus to do, the avenger of blood too hardly did pursue me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p251">249. Now therefore I was glad to catch at that word, which yet I feared I had 
no ground or right to own; and even to leap into the bosom of that promise, that 
yet I feared did shut its heart against me. Now also I should labour to take the 
Word as God had laid it down, without restraining the natural force of one syllable 
thereof. O what did I now see in that blessed sixth of John, ‘And him that cometh 
to me I will in no wise cast out’ (<scripRef passage="John 6:37" id="iv-p251.1" parsed="|John|6|37|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.6.37">ver. 37</scripRef>). Now I began to consider with myself, 
that God had a bigger mouth to speak with than I had heart to conceive with. I thought 
also with myself that He spake not His words in haste, or in unadvised heat, but 
with infinite wisdom and judgment, and in very truth and faithfulness.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p252">250. I should in these days, often in my greatest agonies, even flounce towards 
the promise, as the horses do towards sound ground that yet stick in the mire, concluding, 
though as one almost bereft of his wits through fear, on this I will rest and stay, 
and leave the fulfilling of it to the God of heaven that made it. Oh! many a pull 
hath my heart had with Satan for that sixth of John. I did not now, as at other 
times, look principally for comfort, though, O how welcome would it have been unto 
me! But now a word, a word to lean a weary soul upon, that I might not sink for 
ever! it was that I hunted for.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p253">251. Yea, often when I have been making to the promise, I have seen as if the 
Lord would refuse my soul for ever. I was often as if I had run upon the pikes, 
and as if the Lord had thrust at me to keep me from Him as with a flaming sword. 
Then I should think of Esther, who went to petition the king contrary to the law 
(<scripRef passage="Esther 4:16" id="iv-p253.1" parsed="|Esth|4|16|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Esth.4.16">Esth 4.16</scripRef>). I thought also of Benhadad’s servants, who went with ropes upon their 
heads to their enemies for mercy (<scripRef passage="1Kings 20:31" id="iv-p253.2" parsed="|1Kgs|20|31|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Kgs.20.31">1 Kings 20.31</scripRef>). The woman of Canaan also, that 
would not be daunted, though called dog by Christ (<scripRef passage="Matthew 15:21-28" id="iv-p253.3" parsed="|Matt|15|21|15|28" osisRef="Bible:Matt.15.21-Matt.15.28">Matt. 15.21-8</scripRef>); and the man that 
went to borrow bread at midnight (<scripRef passage="Luke 11:5-8" id="iv-p253.4" parsed="|Luke|11|5|11|8" osisRef="Bible:Luke.11.5-Luke.11.8">Luke 11.5-8</scripRef>), were great encouragements unto me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p254">252. I never saw those heights and depths in grace, and love, and mercy, as I 
saw after this temptation. Great sins to draw out great grace; and where guilt is 
most terrible and fierce there the mercy of God in Christ, when showed to the soul, 
appears most high and mighty. When Job had passed through his captivity, he had 
‘twice as much as he had before’ (<scripRef passage="Job 42:10" id="iv-p254.1" parsed="|Job|42|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Job.42.10">Job 42.10</scripRef>). Blessed be God for Jesus Christ our 
Lord. Many other things I might here make observation of, but I would be brief, 
and therefore shall at this time omit them, and do pray God that my harms may make 
others fear to offend, lest they also be made to bear the iron yoke as I did.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p255">I had two or three times, at or about my deliverance from this temptation, such 
strange apprehensions of the grace of God, that I could hardly bear up under it, 
it was so out of measure amazing, when I thought it could reach me, that I do think, 
if that sense of it had abode long upon me, it would have made me incapable for 
business.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p256">253. Now I shall go forward to give you a relation of other of the Lord’s leadings 
with me, of His dealings with me at sundry other seasons, and of the temptations 
I then did meet withal. I shall begin with what I met when I first did join in fellowship 
with the people of God in Bedford. After I had propounded to the church that my 
desire was to walk in the order and ordinances of Christ with them, and was also 
admitted by them; while I thought of that blessed ordinance of Christ, which was 
His last supper with His disciples before His death, that scripture, ‘This do in 
remembrance of me’ (<scripRef passage="Luke 22:19" id="iv-p256.1" parsed="|Luke|22|19|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Luke.22.19">Luke 22.19</scripRef>), was made a very precious word unto me; for by it 
the Lord did come down upon my conscience with the discovery of His death for my 
sins; and as I then felt, did as if He plunged me in the virtue of the same. But, 
behold, I had not been long a partaker at that ordinance, but such fierce and sad 
temptations did attend me at all times therein, both to blaspheme the ordinance, 
and to wish some deadly thing to those that then did eat thereof; that, lest I should 
at any time be guilty of consenting to these wicked and fearful thoughts, I was 
forced to bend myself all the while to pray to God to keep me from such blasphemies; 
and also to cry to God to bless the bread and cup to them as it went from mouth 
to mouth. The reason of this temptation I have thought since was, because I did 
not, with that reverence as became me, at first approach to partake thereof.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p257">254. Thus I continued for three-quarters of a year, and could never have rest 
nor ease; but at last the Lord came in upon my soul with that same scripture by 
which my soul was visited before; and after that I have been usually very well and 
comfortable in the partaking of that blessed ordinance, and have, I trust, therein 
discerned the Lord’s body as broken for my sins, and that His precious blood hath 
been shed for my transgressions.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p258">255. Upon a time I was somewhat inclining to a consumption, wherewith, about 
the spring, I was suddenly and violently seized with much weakness in my outward 
man, insomuch that I thought I could not live. Now began I afresh to give myself 
up to a serious examination after my state and condition for the future, and of 
my evidences for that blessed world to come; for it hath, I bless the name of God, 
been my usual course, as always, so especially in the day of affliction, to endeavour 
to keep my interest in the life to come clear before my eye.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p259">256. But I had no sooner began to recall to mind my former experience of the 
goodness of God to my soul, but there came flocking into my mind an innumerable 
company of my sins and transgressions, amongst which these were at this time most 
to my affliction, namely, my deadness, dulness, and coldness in holy duties; my 
wanderings of heart, of my wearisomeness in all good things, my want of love to 
God, His ways, and people, with this at the end of all, Are these the fruits of 
Christianity? are these the tokens of a blessed man?</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p260">257. At the apprehension of these things my sickness was doubled upon me, for 
now was I sick in my inward man, my soul was clogged with guilt; now also was my 
former experience of God’s goodness to me quite taken out of my mind, and hid as 
if it had never been, nor seen. Now was my soul greatly pinched between these two 
considerations. Live I must not, Die I dare not; now I sunk and fell in my spirit; 
and was giving up all for lost; but as I was walking up and down in the house, as 
a man in a most woeful state, that word of God took hold of my heart, Ye are ‘justified 
freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus’ (<scripRef passage="Romans 3:24" id="iv-p260.1" parsed="|Rom|3|24|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.3.24">Rom. 3.24</scripRef>). 
But oh, what a turn it made upon me!</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p261">258. Now was I as one awakened out of some troublesome sleep and dream, and listening 
to this heavenly sentence, I was as if I had heard it thus expounded to me: Sinner, 
thou thinkest that because of thy sins and infirmities I cannot save thy soul, but 
behold My Son is by Me, and upon Him I look, and not on thee, and will deal with 
thee according as I am pleased with Him. At this I was greatly lightened in my mind, 
and made to understand that God could justify a sinner at any time; it was but His 
looking upon Christ, and imputing of His benefits to us, and the work was forthwith 
done.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p262">259. And as I was thus in a muse, that scripture also came with great power upon 
my spirit, ‘Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his 
mercy he saved us,’ etc. (<scripRef passage="Titus 3:5" id="iv-p262.1" parsed="|Titus|3|5|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Titus.3.5">Tit. 3.5</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="2Timothy 1:9" id="iv-p262.2" parsed="|2Tim|1|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Tim.1.9">II Tim. 1.9</scripRef>). Now was I got on high; I saw myself 
within the arms of grace and mercy; and though I was before afraid to think of a 
dying hour, yet now I cried, Let me die. Now death was lovely and beautiful in my 
sight; for I saw we shall never live indeed till we be gone to the other world. 
Oh, methought this life is but a slumber in comparison of that above; at this time 
also I saw more in those words, ‘Heirs of God’ (<scripRef passage="Romans 8:17" id="iv-p262.3" parsed="|Rom|8|17|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.8.17">Rom. 8.17</scripRef>), than ever I shall be 
able to express while I live in this world. ‘Heirs of God’! God Himself is the portion 
of the saints. This I saw and wondered at, but cannot tell you what I saw.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p263">260. Again, as I was at another time very ill and weak, all that time also the 
tempter did beset me strongly, for I find he is much for assaulting the soul when 
it begins to approach towards the grave, then is his opportunity, labouring to hide 
from me my former experience of God’s goodness; also setting before me the terrors 
of death and the judgment of God, insomuch that at this time, through my fear of 
miscarrying for ever, should I now die, I was as one dead before death came, and 
was as if I had felt myself already descending into the pit; methought, I said, 
there was no way, but to hell I must; but behold, just as I was in the midst of 
those fears, these words of the angels carrying Lazarus into Abraham’s bosom darted 
in upon me, as who should say, So it shall be with thee when thou dost leave this 
world. This did sweetly revive my spirit, and help me to hope in God; which, when 
I had with comfort mused on a while, that word fell with great weight upon my mind, 
‘O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory?’ (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 15:55" id="iv-p263.1" parsed="|1Cor|15|55|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.15.55">1 Cor. 15.55</scripRef>). At 
this I became both well in body and mind at once, for my sickness did presently 
vanish, and I walked comfortably in my work for God again.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p264">261. At another time, though just before I was pretty well and savoury in my 
spirit, yet suddenly there fell upon me a great cloud of darkness, which did so 
hide from me the things of God and Christ, that I was as if I had never seen or 
known them in my life; was also so overrun in my soul, with a senseless, heartless 
frame of spirit, that I could not feel my soul to move or stir after grace and life 
by Christ; I was as if my loins were broken, or as if my hands and feet had been 
tied or bound with chains. At this time also I felt some weakness to seize upon 
my outward man, which made still the other affliction the more heavy and uncomfortable 
to me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p265">262. After I had been in this condition some three or four days, as I was sitting 
by the fire, I suddenly felt this word to sound in my heart, I must go to Jesus; 
at this my former darkness and atheism fled away, and the blessed things of heaven 
were set within my view. While I was on this sudden thus overtaken with surprise, 
Wife, said I, is there ever such a scripture, I must go to Jesus? She said she could 
not tell, therefore I sat musing still to see if I could remember such a place; 
I had not sat above two or three minutes but that came bolting in upon me, ‘And 
to an innumerable company of angels,’ and withal, Hebrews the twelfth, about the 
mount Sion, was set before mine eyes (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 12:22-24" id="iv-p265.1" parsed="|Heb|12|22|12|24" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.22-Heb.12.24">ver. 22-4</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p266">263. Then with joy I told my wife, O now I know, I know! But that night was a 
good night to me, I never had but few better; I longed for the company of some of 
God’s people that I might have imparted unto them what God had showed me. Christ 
was a precious Christ to my soul that night; I could scarce lie in my bed for joy, 
and peace, and triumph, through Christ; this great glory did not continue upon me 
until morning, yet that twelfth of the author of (<scripRef passage="Hebrews 12:22-24" id="iv-p266.1" parsed="|Heb|12|22|12|24" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.22-Heb.12.24">Hebrews 12:22-4</scripRef>) was a blessed 
scripture to me for many days together after this.</p>

<p class="normal" id="iv-p267">264. The words are these, ‘Ye are come unto mount Sion, and unto the city of 
the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable company of angels, 
to the general assembly and church of the firstborn, which are written in heaven, 
and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect, and to 
Jesus the mediator of the new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling, that speaketh 
better things than that of Abel.’ Through this blessed sentence the Lord led me 
over and over, first to this word, and then to that, and showed me wonderful glory 
in every one of them. These words also have oft since this time been great refreshment 
to my spirit. Blessed be God in having mercy on me.</p>

</div1>

<div1 title="A Brief Account of the Author’s Call to the Work of the Ministry" progress="85.29%" prev="iv" next="vi" id="v">
<h2 id="v-p0.1">A BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE AUTHOR’S CALL TO THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY </h2>
<p class="normal" id="v-p1">265. And now I am speaking my experience, I will in this place thrust in a word 
or two concerning my preaching the Word, and of God’s dealing with me in that particular 
also. For after I had been about five or six years awakened, and helped myself to 
see both the want and worth of Jesus Christ our Lord, and also enabled to venture 
my soul upon Him, some of the most able among the saints with us, I say the most 
able for judgment and holiness of life, as they conceived, did perceive that God 
had counted me worthy to understand something of His will in His holy and blessed 
Word, and had given me utterance, in some measure, to express what I saw to others 
for edification; therefore they desired me, and that with much earnestness, that 
I would be willing, at sometimes, to take in hand, in one of the meetings, to speak 
a word of exhortation unto them.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p2">266. The which, though at the first it did much dash and abash my spirit, yet 
being still by them desired and intreated, I consented to their request, and did 
twice at two several assemblies, but in private, though with much weakness and infirmity, 
discover my gift amongst them; at which they not only seemed to be, but did solemnly 
protest, as in the sight of the great God, they were both affected and comforted, 
and gave thanks to the Father of mercies for the grace bestowed on me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p3">267. After this, sometimes when some of them did go into the country to teach, 
they would also that I should go with them; where, though as yet I did not, nor 
durst not, make use of my gift in an open way, yet more privately still as I came 
amongst the good people in those places, I did sometimes speak a word of admonition 
unto them also; the which, they as the other received, with rejoicing at the mercy 
of God to me-ward, professing their souls were edified thereby.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p4">268. Wherefore, to be brief, at last, being still desired by the church, after 
some solemn prayer to the Lord, with fasting, I was more particularly called forth, 
and appointed to a more ordinary and public preaching of the Word, not only to, 
and amongst them that believed, but also to offer the gospel to those who had not 
yet received the faith thereof; about which time I did evidently find in my mind 
a secret pricking forward thereto; though I bless God, not for desire of vain glory, 
for at that time I was most sorely afflicted with the fiery darts of the devil concerning 
my eternal state.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p5">269. But yet could not be content, unless I was found in the exercise of my gift, 
unto which I was greatly animated, not only by the continual desires of the godly, 
but also by that saying of Paul to the Corinthians, ‘I beseech you, brethren (ye 
know the household of Stephanas, that it is the firstfruits of Achaia, and that 
they have addicted themselves to the ministry of the saints), that ye submit yourselves 
unto such, and to every one that helpeth with us, and laboureth’ (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 16:15,16" id="v-p5.1" parsed="|1Cor|16|15|16|16" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.16.15-1Cor.16.16">I Cor. 16.15, 
16</scripRef>) .</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p6">270. By this text I was made to see that the Holy Ghost never intended that men 
who have gifts and abilities should bury them in the earth, but rather did command 
and stir up such to the exercise of their gift, and also did commend those that 
were apt and ready so to do, ‘They have addicted themselves to the ministry of the 
saints.’ This scripture, in these days, did continually run in my mind, to encourage 
me and strengthen me in this work for God; I have also been encouraged from several 
other scriptures and examples of the godly, both specified in the Word and other 
ancient histories (<scripRef passage="Acts 8:4" id="v-p6.1" parsed="|Acts|8|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.8.4">Act. 8.4</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Acts 18:24,25" id="v-p6.2" parsed="|Acts|18|24|18|25" osisRef="Bible:Acts.18.24-Acts.18.25">18.24, 25</scripRef>; 
<scripRef passage="1Peter 4:10" id="v-p6.3" parsed="|1Pet|4|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Pet.4.10">1 Pet. 4.10</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Romans 12:6" id="v-p6.4" parsed="|Rom|12|6|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.12.6">Rom. 12.6</scripRef>; Foxe’s Acts and 
Mounments).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p7">271. Wherefore, though of myself of all the saints the most unworthy, yet I, 
but with great fear and trembling at the sight of my own weakness, did set upon 
the work, and did according to my gift, and the proportion of my faith, preach that 
blessed gospel that God had showed me in the holy Word of truth; which, when the 
country understood, they came in to hear the Word by hundreds, and that from all 
parts, though upon sundry and divers accounts.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p8">272. And I thank God He gave unto me some measure of bowels and pity for their 
souls, which also did put me forward to labour with great diligence and earnestness, 
to find out such a word as might, if God would bless it, lay hold of and awaken 
the conscience, in which the good Lord had respect to the desire of His servant; 
for I had not preached long before some began to be touched by the Word, and to 
be greatly afflicted in their minds at the apprehension of the greatness of their 
sin, and of their need of Jesus Christ.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p9">273. But I at first could not believe that God should speak by me to the heart 
of any man, still counting myself unworthy; yet those who were thus touched would 
love me and have a peculiar respect for me; and though I did put it from me, that 
they should be awakened by me, still they would confess it, and affirm it before 
the saints of God; they would also bless God for me, unworthy wretch that I am! 
and count me God’s instrument that showed to them the way of salvation.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p10">274. Wherefore, seeing them in both their words and deeds to be so constant, 
and also in their hearts so earnestly pressing after the knowledge of Jesus Christ, 
rejoicing that ever God did send me where they were; then I began to conclude it 
might be so, that God had owned in His work such a foolish one as I, and then came 
that word of God to my heart with much sweet refreshment, ‘The blessing of him that 
was ready to perish came upon me; and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy’ 
(<scripRef passage="Job 29:13" id="v-p10.1" parsed="|Job|29|13|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Job.29.13">Job 29.13</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p11">275. At this therefore I rejoiced, yea, the tears of those whom God did awaken 
by my preaching would be both solace and encouragement to me; for I thought on those 
sayings, ‘Who is he that maketh me glad but the same which is made sorry by me?’ 
(<scripRef passage="2Corinthians 2:2" id="v-p11.1" parsed="|2Cor|2|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.2.2">II Cor. 2.2</scripRef>); and again, Though ‘I be not an apostle to others, yet doubtless I 
am to you: for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord’ (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 9:2" id="v-p11.2" parsed="|1Cor|9|2|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.9.2">1 Cor. 9.2</scripRef>). These 
things, therefore, were as another argument unto me that God had called me to, and 
stood by me in this work.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p12">276. In my preaching of the Word, I took special notice of this one thing, namely, 
that the Lord did lead me to begin where His Word begins with sinners; that is, 
to condemn all flesh, and to open and allege that the curse of God, by the law, 
doth belong to and lay hold on all men as they come into the world, because of sin. 
Now this part of my work I fulfilled with great sense; for the terrors of the law, 
and guilt for my transgressions, lay heavy on my conscience. I preached what I felt, 
what I smartingly did feel, even that under which my poor soul did groan and tremble 
to astonishment.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p13">277. Indeed I have been as one sent to them from the dead; I went myself in chains 
to preach to them in chains; and carried that fire in my own conscience that I persuaded 
them to beware of. I can truly say, and that without dissembling, that when I have 
been to preach, I have gone full of guilt and terror even to the pulpit door, and 
there it hath been taken off, and I have been at liberty in my mind until I have 
done my work, and then immediately, even before I could get down the pulpit stairs, 
I have been as bad as I was before; yet God carried me on, but surely with a strong 
hand, for neither guilt nor hell could take me off my work.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p14">278. Thus I went for the space of two years, crying out against men’s sins, and 
their fearful state because of them. After which the Lord came in upon my own soul 
with some staid peace and comfort through Christ; for He did give me many sweet 
discoveries of His blessed grace through Him. Wherefore now I altered in my preaching, 
for still I preached what I saw and felt; now therefore I did much labour to hold 
forth Jesus Christ in all His offices, relations, and benefits unto the world; and 
did strive also to discover, to condemn, and remove those false supports and props 
on which the world doth both lean, and by them fall and perish. On these things 
also I staid as long as on the other.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p15">279. After this, God led me into something of the mystery of union with Christ; 
wherefore that I discovered and showed to them also. And when I had travelled through 
these three chief points of the Word of God, about the space of five years or more, 
I was caught in my present practice and cast into prison, where I have lain above 
as long again, to confirm the truth by way of suffering, as I was before in testifying 
of it according to the Scriptures in a way of preaching.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p16">280. When I have been preaching, I thank God, my heart hath often all the time 
of this and the other exercise, with great earnestness, cried to God that He would 
make the Word effectual to the salvation of the soul; still being grieved lest the 
enemy should take the Word away from the conscience, and so it should become unfruitful. 
Wherefore I did labour so to speak the Word, as that thereby, if it were possible, 
the sin and the person guilty might be particularized by it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p17">281. Also, when I have done the exercise, it hath gone to my heart to think the 
Word should now fall as rain on stony places, still wishing from my heart, O that 
they who have heard me speak this day did but see as I do what sin, death, hell, 
and the curse of God is; and also what the grace, and love, and mercy of God is, 
through Christ, to men in such a case as they are, who are yet estranged from Him. 
And, indeed, I did often say in my heart before the Lord, That if to be hanged up 
presently before their eyes would be a means to awaken them, and confirm them in 
the truth, I gladly should be contented.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p18">282. For I have been in my preaching, especially when I have been engaged in 
the doctrine of life by Christ, without works, as if an angel of God had stood by 
at my back to encourage me. Oh, it hath been with such power and heavenly evidence 
upon my own soul, while I have been labouring to unfold it, to demonstrate it, and 
to fasten it upon the consciences of others, that I could not be contented with 
saying, I believe, and am sure; methought I was more than sure, if it be lawful 
so to express myself, that those things which then I asserted were true.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p19">283. When I went first to preach the Word abroad, the doctors and priests of 
the country did open wide against me. But I was persuaded of this, not to render 
railing for railing, but to see how many of their carnal professors I could convince 
of their miserable state by the law, and of the want and worth of Christ; for, thought 
I, This shall answer for me in time to come, when they shall be for my hire before 
their faces (<scripRef passage="Genesis 30:33" id="v-p19.1" parsed="|Gen|30|33|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Gen.30.33">Gen. 30.33</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p20">284. I never cared to meddle with things that were controverted, and in dispute 
amongst the saints, especially things of the lowest nature; yet it pleased me much 
to contend with great earnestness for the word of faith and the remission of sins 
by the death and sufferings of Jesus; but I say, as to other things, I should let 
them alone, because I saw they engendered strife, and because that they neither, 
in doing nor in leaving undone, did commend us to God to be His. Besides, I saw 
my work before me did run in another channel even to carry an awakening word; to 
that therefore did I stick and adhere.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p21">285. I never endeavoured to, nor durst make use of other men’s lines (<scripRef passage="Romans 15:18" id="v-p21.1" parsed="|Rom|15|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.15.18">Rom. 15.18</scripRef>), 
though I condemn not all that do, for I verily thought, and found by experience, 
that what was taught me by the Word and Spirit of Christ, could be spoken, maintained, 
and stood to by the soundest and best established conscience; and though I will 
not now speak all that I know in this matter, yet my experience hath more interest 
in that text of Scripture than many amongst men are aware (<scripRef passage="Galatians 1:11,12" id="v-p21.2" parsed="|Gal|1|11|1|12" osisRef="Bible:Gal.1.11-Gal.1.12">Gal. 1.11, 12</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p22">286. If any of those who were awakened by my ministry did after that fall back, 
as sometimes too many did, I can truly say their loss hath been more to me than 
if one of my own children, begotten of my body, had been going to its grave; I think, 
verily, I may speak it without an offence to the Lord, nothing hath gone so near 
me as that, unless it was the fear of the loss of the salvation of my own soul. 
I have counted as if I had goodly buildings and lordships in those places where 
my children were born; my heart hath been so wrapped up in the glory of this excellent 
work, that I counted myself more blessed and honoured of God by this than if He 
had made me the emperor of the Christian world, or the lord of all the glory of 
the earth without it! O these words, ‘He which converteth the sinner from the error 
of his way shall save a soul from death’ (<scripRef passage="James 5:20" id="v-p22.1" parsed="|Jas|5|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jas.5.20">Jas. 5.20</scripRef>). ‘The fruit of the righteous 
is a tree of life; and he that winneth souls is wise’ (<scripRef passage="Proverbs 11:30" id="v-p22.2" parsed="|Prov|11|30|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Prov.11.30">Prov. 11.30</scripRef>). ‘They that 
be wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn many 
to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever’ (<scripRef passage="Daniel 12:3" id="v-p22.3" parsed="|Dan|12|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Dan.12.3">Dan. 12.3</scripRef>). ‘For what is our hope, 
or joy, or crown of rejoicing? Are not even ye in the presence of our Lord Jesus 
Christ at his coming? For ye are our glory and joy’ (<scripRef passage="1Thessalonians 2:19,20" id="v-p22.4" parsed="|1Thess|2|19|2|20" osisRef="Bible:1Thess.2.19-1Thess.2.20">1 Thess. 2.19, 20</scripRef>). These, 
I say, with many others of a like nature, have been great refreshments to me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p23">287. I have observed, that where I have had a work to do for God, I have had 
first, as it were, the going of God upon my spirit to desire I might preach there. 
I have also observed that such and such souls in particular have been strongly set 
upon my heart, and I stirred up to wish for their salvation; and that these very 
souls have, after this, been given in as the fruits of my ministry. I have also 
observed, that a word cast in by the by hath done more execution in a sermon than 
all that was spoken besides; sometimes also when I have thought I did no good, then 
I did the most of all; and at other times when I thought I should catch them I have 
fished for nothing.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p24">288. I have also observed, that where there hath been a work to do upon sinners, 
there the devil hath begun to roar in the hearts, and by the mouths of his servants. 
Yea, oftentimes when the wicked world hath raged most, there hath been souls awaked 
by the word. I could instance particulars, but I forbear.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p25">289. My great desire in fulfilling my ministry was to get into the darkest places 
of the country, even amongst those people that were farthest off of profession; 
yet not because I could not endure the light, for I feared not to show my gospel 
to any, but because I found my spirit leaned most after awakening and converting 
work, and the Word that I carried did lead itself most that way also; ‘yea, so have 
I strived to preach the gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I should build 
upon another man’s foundation’ (<scripRef passage="Romans 15:20" id="v-p25.1" parsed="|Rom|15|20|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Rom.15.20">Rom. 15.20</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p26">290. In my preaching I have really been in pain, and have, as it were, travailed 
to bring forth children to God; neither could I be satisfied unless some fruits 
did appear in my work. If I were fruitless it mattered not who commended me; but 
if I were fruitful, I cared not who did condemn. I have thought of that, ‘He that 
winneth souls is wise’ (<scripRef passage="Proverbs 11:30" id="v-p26.1" parsed="|Prov|11|30|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Prov.11.30">Prov. 11.30</scripRef>); and again, ‘Lo, children are an heritage of 
the Lord; and the fruit of the womb is his reward. As arrows in the hand of a mighty 
man, so are children of the youth. Happy is the man that hath filled his quiver 
full of them; they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in 
the gate’ (<scripRef passage="Psalm 127:3-5" id="v-p26.2" parsed="|Ps|127|3|127|5" osisRef="Bible:Ps.127.3-Ps.127.5">Ps. 127.3-5</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p27">291. It pleased me nothing to see people drink in opinions if they seemed ignorant 
of Jesus Christ, and the worth of their own salvation, sound conviction for sin, 
especially for unbelief, and an heart set on fire to be saved by Christ, with strong 
breathing after a truly sanctified soul; that it was that delighted me; those were 
the souls I counted blessed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p28">292. But in this work, as in all other, I had my temptations attending me, and 
that of diverse kinds, as sometimes I should be assaulted with great discouragement 
therein, fearing that I should not be able to speak the Word at all to edification; 
nay, that I should not be able to speak sense unto the people; at which times I 
should have such a strange faintness and strengthlessness seize upon my body that 
my legs have scarce been able to carry me to the place of exercise.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p29">293. Sometimes, again, when I have been preaching, I have been violently assaulted 
with thoughts of blasphemy, and strongly tempted to speak the words with my mouth 
before the congregation. I have also at some times, even when I have begun to speak 
the Word with much clearness, evidence, and liberty of speech, yet been before the 
ending of that opportunity so blinded, and so estranged from the things I have been 
speaking, and have also been so straitened in my speech, as to utterance before 
the people, that I have been as if I had not known or remembered what I have been 
about, or as if my head had been in a bag all the time of the exercise.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p30">294. Again, when as sometimes I have been about to preach upon some smart and 
scorching portion of the Word, I have found the tempter suggest, What, will you 
preach this? this condemns yourself; of this your own soul is guilty; wherefore 
preach not of it at all; or if you do, yet so mince it as to make way for your own 
escape; lest instead of awakening others, you lay that guilt upon your own soul 
as you will never get from under.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p31">295. But, I thank the Lord, I have been kept from consenting to these so horrid 
suggestions, and have rather, as Samson, bowed myself with all my might, to condemn 
sin and transgression wherever I found it, yea, though therein also I did bring 
guilt upon my own conscience! ‘Let me die,’ thought I, ‘with the Philistines’ (<scripRef passage="Judges 16:29,30" id="v-p31.1" parsed="|Judg|16|29|16|30" osisRef="Bible:Judg.16.29-Judg.16.30">Judg. 
16.29, 30</scripRef>), rather than deal corruptly with the blessed Word of God, ‘Thou that 
teachest another, teachest not thou thyself?’ It is far better that thou do judge 
thyself, even by preaching plainly to others, than that thou, to save thyself, imprison 
the truth in unrighteousness; blessed be God for His help also in this.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p32">296. I have also, while found in this blessed work of Christ, been often tempted 
to pride and liftings up of heart; and though I dare not say I have not been infected 
with this, yet truly the Lord, of His precious mercy, hath so carried it towards 
me, that, for the most part, I have had but small joy to give way to such a thing; 
for it hath been my every day’s portion to be let into the evil of my own heart, 
and still made to see such a multitude of corruptions and infirmities therein, that 
it hath caused hanging down of the head under all my gifts and attainments; I have 
felt this thorn in the flesh, the very mercy of God to me (<scripRef passage="2Corinthians 12:7-9" id="v-p32.1" parsed="|2Cor|12|7|12|9" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.12.7-2Cor.12.9">II Cor. 12.7-9</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p33">297. I have had also, together with this, some notable place or other of the 
Word presented before me, which word hath contained in it some sharp and piercing 
sentence concerning the perishing of the soul, notwithstanding gifts and parts; 
as, for instance, that hath been of great use unto me, ‘Though I speak with the 
tongues of men and of angels, and have not charity, I am become as sounding brass, 
and a tinkling cymbal’ (<scripRef passage="1Corinthians 13:1,2" id="v-p33.1" parsed="|1Cor|13|1|13|2" osisRef="Bible:1Cor.13.1-1Cor.13.2">1 Cor. 13.1, 2</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p34">298. A tinkling cymbal is an instrument of music, with which a skilful player 
can make such melodious and heart-inflaming music, that all who hear him play can 
scarcely hold from dancing; and yet behold the cymbal hath not life, neither comes 
the music from it, but because of the art of him that plays therewith; so then the 
instrument at last may come to naught and perish, though, in times past, such music 
hath been made upon it.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p35">299. Just thus I saw it was and will be with them who have gifts, but want saving 
grace, they are in the hand of Christ, as the cymbal in the hand of David; and as 
David could, with the cymbal, make that mirth in the service of God, as to elevate 
the hearts of the worshippers, so Christ can use these gifted men, as with them 
to affect the souls of His people in His church; yet when He hath done all, hang 
them by as lifeless, though sounding cymbals.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p36">300. This consideration, therefore, together with some others, were, for the 
most part, as a maul on the head of pride, and desire of vain glory; what, thought 
I, shall I be proud because I am a sounding brass? Is it so much to be a fiddle? 
Hath not the least creature that hath life, more of God in it than these? Besides, 
I knew it was love should never die, but these must cease and vanish; so I concluded, 
a little grace, a little love, a little of the true fear of God, is better than 
all these gifts; yea, and I am fully convinced of it, that it is possible for a 
soul that can scarce give a man an answer, but with great confusion as to method, 
I say it is possible for them to have a thousand times more grace, and so to be 
more in the love and favour of the Lord than some who, by virtue of the gift of 
knowledge, can deliver themselves like angels.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p37">301. Thus, therefore, I came to perceive, that though gifts in themselves were 
good to the thing for which they are designed, to wit, the edification of others; 
yet empty and without power to have the soul of him that hath them, if they be alone; 
neither are they, as so, any sign of a man’s state to be happy, being only a dispensation 
of God to some, of whose improvement, or non-improvement, they must, when a little 
love more is over, give an account to Him that is ready to judge the quick and the 
dead.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p38">302. This showed me, too, that gifts being alone, were dangerous, not in themselves, 
but because of those evils that attend them that have them, to wit, pride, desire 
of vain glory, self-conceit, etc., all of which were easily blown up at the applause 
and commendation of every unadvised Christian, to the endangering of a poor creature 
to fall into the condemnation of the devil.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p39">303. I saw therefore that he that hath gifts had need be let into a sight of 
the nature of them, to wit, that they come short of making of him to be in a truly 
saved condition, lest he rest in them, and so fall short of the grace of God.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p40">304. He hath also cause to walk humbly with God, and be little in his own eyes, 
and to remember withal, that his gifts are not his own, but the church’s; and that 
by them he is made a servant to the church; and that he must give at last an account 
of his stewardship unto the Lord Jesus; and to give a good account, will be a blessed 
thing.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p41">305. Let all men therefore prize a little with the fear of the Lord; gifts indeed 
are desirable, but yet great grace and small gifts are better than great gifts and 
no grace. It doth not say, the Lord gives gifts and glory, but the Lord gives grace 
and glory; and blessed is such an one to whom the Lord gives grace, true grace, 
for that is a certain forerunner of glory.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p42">306. But when Satan perceived that his thus tempting and assaulting of me would 
not answer his design, to wit, to overthrow my ministry, and make it ineffectual, 
as to the ends thereof; then he tried another way, which was to stir up the minds 
of the ignorant and malicious, to load me with slanders and reproaches; now therefore 
I may say, that what the devil could devise, and his instruments invent, was whirled 
up and down the country against me, thinking, as I said, that by that means they 
should make my ministry to be abandoned.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p43">307. It began therefore to be rumoured up and down among the people, that I was 
a witch, a Jesuit, a highwayman, and the like.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p44">308. To all which, I shall only say, God knows that I am innocent. But as for 
mine accusers, let them provide themselves to meet me before the tribunal of the 
Son of God, there to answer for these things, with all the rest of their iniquities, 
unless God shall give them repentance for them, for the which I pray with all my 
heart.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p45">309. But that which was reported with the boldest confidence, was, that I had 
my misses, my whores, my bastards, yea, two wives at once, and the like. Now these 
slanders, with the other, I glory in, because but slanders, foolish, or knavish 
lies, and falsehoods cast upon me by the devil and his seed; and should I not be 
dealt with thus wickedly by the world, I should want one sign of a saint, and a 
child of God. ‘Blessed are ye (said the Lord Jesus) when men shall revile you, and 
persecute you, and shall say all manner of evil against you falsely for my sake; 
rejoice, and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven; for so persecuted 
they the prophets which were before you’ (<scripRef passage="Matthew 5:11" id="v-p45.1" parsed="|Matt|5|11|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Matt.5.11">Matt. 5.11</scripRef>).</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p46">310. These things, therefore, upon mine own account, trouble me not; no, though 
they were twenty times more than they are. I have a good conscience, and whereas 
they speak evil of me, as an evil doer, they shall be ashamed that falsely accuse 
my good conversation in Christ.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p47">311. So, then, what shall I say to those that have thus bespattered me? Shall 
I threaten them? Shall I chide them? Shall I flatter them? Shall I intreat them 
to hold their tongues? No, not I, were it not for that these things make them ripe 
for damnation, that are the authors and abettors, I would say unto them, Report 
it, because it will increase my glory.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p48">312. Therefore I bind these lies and slanders to me as an ornament, it belongs 
to my Christian profession to be vilified, slandered, reproached and reviled; and 
since all this is nothing else, as my God and my conscience do bear me witness, 
I rejoice in reproaches for Christ’s sake.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p49">313. I also calling all those fools, or knaves, that have thus made it anything 
of their business to affirm any of the things afore-named of me, namely, that I 
have been naught with other women, or the like. When they have used to the utmost 
of their endeavours, and made the fullest inquiry that they can, to prove against 
me truly, that there is any woman in heaven, or earth, or hell, that can say, I 
have at any time, in any place, by day or night, so much as attempted to be naught 
with them; and speak I thus, to beg mine enemies into a good esteem of me? No, not 
I: I will in this beg relief of no man; believe or disbelieve me in this, all is 
a case to me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p50">314. My foes have missed their mark in this their shooting at me. I am not the 
man. I wish that they themselves be guiltless. If all the fornicators and adulterers 
in England were hanged by the neck till they be dead, <span class="sc" id="v-p50.1">John Bunyan</span>, the object 
of their envy, would be still alive and well. I know not whether there be such a 
thing as a woman breathing under the copes of the whole heaven but by their apparel, 
their children, or by common fame, except my wife.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p51">315. And in this I admire the wisdom of God, that He made me shy of women from 
my first conversion until now. Those know, and can also bear me witness, with whom 
I have been most intimately concerned, that it is a rare thing to see me carry it 
pleasant towards a woman, the common salutation of a woman I abhor, it is odious 
to me in whosoever I see it. Their company alone, I cannot away with. I seldom so 
much as touch a woman’s hand, for I think these things are not so becoming me. When 
I have seen good men salute those women that they have visited, or that have visited 
them, I have at times made my objection against it, and when they have answered, 
that it was but a piece of civility, I have told them, it is not a comely sight; 
some indeed have urged the holy kiss but then I have asked why they made baulks, 
why they did salute the most handsome, and let the ill-favoured go; thus, how laudable 
soever such things have been in the eyes of others, they have been unseemly in my 
sight.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p52">316. And now for a wind up in this matter, I calling not only men, but angels, 
to prove me guilty of having carnally to do with any woman save my wife, nor am 
I afraid to do it a second time, knowing that I cannot offend the Lord in such a 
case, to call God for a record upon my soul, that in these things I am innocent. 
Not that I have been thus kept, because of any goodness in me more than any other, 
but God has been merciful to me, and has kept me; to whom I pray that He will keep 
me still, not only from this, but from every evil way and work, and preserve me 
to His heavenly kingdom. Amen.</p>

<p class="normal" id="v-p53">317. Now as Satan laboured by reproaches and slanders, to make me vile among 
my countrymen, that, if possible, my preaching might be made of none effect, so 
there was added hereto a long and tedious imprisonment, that thereby I might be 
frighted from my service for Christ, and the world terrified, and made afraid to 
hear me preach, of which I shall in the next place give you a brief account.</p>

</div1>

<div1 title="A Brief Account of the Author’s Imprisonment" progress="98.40%" prev="v" next="vii" id="vi">
<h2 id="vi-p0.1">A BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE AUTHOR’S IMPRISONMENT</h2>
<p class="normal" id="vi-p1">318. Having made profession of the glorious gospel of Christ a long time, and 
preached the same about five years, I was apprehended at a meeting of good people 
in the country, among whom, had they let me alone, I should have preached that day, 
but they took me away from amongst them, and had me before a justice; who, after 
I had offered security for my appearing at the next sessions, yet committed me, 
because my sureties would not consent to be bound that I should preach no more to 
the people.</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p2">319. At the sessions, after I was indicted 
for an upholder and maintainer of unlawful assemblies and conventicles, and 
for not conforming to the national worship of the Church of England, and 
after some conference there with the justices, they, taking my plain dealing 
with them for a confession, as they termed it, of the indictment, did 
sentence me to a perpetual banishment, because I refused to conform. 
So, being again delivered up to a gaoler's hands, I was had home to prison, 
and there have lain now complete twelve years, waiting to see what God 
would suffer those men to do with me.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p3">320. In which condition I have continued with 
much content, through grace, but have met with many turnings and goings 
upon my heart, both from the Lord, Satan, and my own corruption; by all 
which, glory be to Jesus Christ! I have also received, among many things, 
much conviction, instruction, and understanding, of which at large I shall 
not here discourse; only to give you a hint or two, a word that may stir 
up the godly to bless God, and to pray for me; and also to take encouragement, 
should the case be their own, not to fear what man can do unto them.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p4">321. I never had in all my life so great an 
inlet into the Word of God as now; Those scriptures that I saw nothing in 
before, were made in this place and state to shine upon me; Jesus Christ 
also was never more real and apparent than now; here I have seen and felt 
him indeed. Oh! that word, We have not preached unto you cunningly devised 
fables, 2 Pet. i 16, and that, God raised Christ from the dead, and gave him 
glory, that your faith and hope might be in God, were the blessed words 
unto me in this my imprisoned condition.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p5">322. These three or four scriptures also have 
been great refreshments in this condition to me, <scripRef passage="John xiv. 1-4" id="vi-p5.1" parsed="|John|14|1|14|4" osisRef="Bible:John.14.1-John.14.4">John xiv. 1-4</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="John xvi. 33" id="vi-p5.2" parsed="|John|16|33|0|0" osisRef="Bible:John.16.33">John xvi. 33</scripRef>; 
<scripRef passage="Col iii. 3" id="vi-p5.3" parsed="|Col|3|3|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Col.3.3">Col iii. 3</scripRef>,<scripRef passage="Col 3:4" id="vi-p5.4" parsed="|Col|3|4|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Col.3.4">4</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Heb. xii. 22-24" id="vi-p5.5" parsed="|Heb|12|22|12|24" osisRef="Bible:Heb.12.22-Heb.12.24">Heb. xii. 22-24</scripRef>. So that sometimes when I have been in the 
savour of them I have been able to laugh at destruction, and to fear neither
the horse nor his rider. I have had sweet sights of the forgiveness of my 
sins in this place, and of my being with Jesus in another world. Oh! the 
Mount Sion, the heavenly Jerusalem, the innumerable company of angels, and 
God the judge of all, and the spirits of just men made perfect, and to Jesus, 
Heb. xii 22-24, have been sweet unto me in this place. I have seen that here, 
that I am persuaded I shall never, while in this world, be able to express: I 
have seen a truth in this scripture, "Whom having not seen, ye love; in 
whom, though now ye see him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy 
unspeakable and full of glory," <scripRef passage="1 Pet. i. 8" id="vi-p5.6" parsed="|1Pet|1|8|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Pet.1.8">1 Pet. i. 8</scripRef>.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p6">323. I never knew what it was for God to stand 
by me at all turns, abd at every offer of Satan to afflict me, etc., as I 
have found him since I came in hither: For look how fears have presented 
themselves, so have supports and encouragements; yea, when I have started, 
even as it were at nothing else but my shadow, yet God, as being very tender 
to me, hath not suffered me to be molested, but would, with one scripture or 
another, strengthen me against all; insomuch that I have often said, Were it 
lawful, I could pray for greater trouble, for the greater comfort's sake, 
Eccles. vii 14; <scripRef passage="2 Cor. i. 5" id="vi-p6.1" parsed="|2Cor|1|5|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.1.5">2 Cor. i. 5</scripRef>.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p7">324. Before I came to prison I saw what was coming, 
and had especially two considerations warm upon my heart; the first was, 
how to be able to encounter death, should that be my portion. For the first 
of these, that scripture, Col. i 11, was great information to me, namely, 
to pray to God, "to be strengthened with all might, according to his glorious 
power, unto all patience and long-suffering with joyfulness." I could seldom 
go to prayer before I was imprisoned, but for not so little as a year 
together, this sentence or sweet petition would, as it were, thrust itself 
into my mind, and persuade me, that if ever I would go through long-suffering, 
I must have patience, especially if I would endure it joyfully. 
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p8">325. As to the second consideration, that saying was 
of great use to me, " But we had the sentence of death in ourselves, that we 
should not trust in ourselves, but in God which raiseth the dead," <scripRef passage="2 Cor. i. 9" id="vi-p8.1" parsed="|2Cor|1|9|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.1.9">2 Cor. i. 9</scripRef>. 
By this scripture I was made to see, That if ever I would suffer rightly I must 
first pass a sentence of death upon every thing that can properly be called a thing 
of this life, even to reckon myself, my wife, my children, my health, my 
enjoyments, and all, as dead to me and myself, as dead to them.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p9">326. The second was to live upon God that is
 invisible, as Paul said in another place; the way not to faint is to 
 "Look not on the things which are seen, but at the things which are not 
 seen: for the things which are seen are temporal; but the things which 
 are not seen are eternal," <scripRef passage="2 Cor. iv. 18" id="vi-p9.1" parsed="|2Cor|4|18|0|0" osisRef="Bible:2Cor.4.18">2 Cor. iv. 18</scripRef>. And thus I reasoned with myself, 
 If I provide only for a prison, then the whip comes at unawares, and so doth 
 also the pillory. Again, if I only provide for these, then I am not fit for 
 banishment: Farther, if I conclude that banishment is the worst, then if 
 death comes I am surprised: So that I see, the best way to go through 
 sufferings is to trust in God through Christ, as touching the world to 
 come; and as touching this world, to count the grave my house, to make my
 bed in darkness; to say to corruption, Thou art my father, and to the worm, 
 Thou art my mother and sister: that is, to familiarize these things to me.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p10">327. But notwithstanding these helps, I 
found myself a man encompassed with infirmities; the parting with my wife 
and poor children hath often been to me in this place as the pulling the 
flesh from the bones, and that not only because I am somewhat too fond of these 
great mercies, but also because I should have often brought to my mind the many 
hardships, miseries, and wants that my poor family was like to meet with should 
I be taken from them, especially my poor blind child, who lay nearer my heart 
than all beside. Oh! the thoughts of the hardship I thought my poor blind one 
might go under, would break my heart to pieces.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p11">328. Poor child! thought I, what sorrow art thou 
like to have for thy portion in this world! Thou must be beaten, must beg, 
suffer hunger, cold, nakedness, and a thousand calamities, though I cannot 
now endure the wind should blow upon thee. But yet recalling myself, thought 
I, I must venture you all with God, though it goeth to the quick to leave you. 
Oh! I saw in this condition I was as a man who was pulling down his house upon 
the head of his wife and children ; yet thought I, I must do it, I must do it.
 And now I thought on those two milch kine that were to carry the ark of God 
 into another country, and to leave their calves behind them, <scripRef passage="1 Sam. vi. 10" id="vi-p11.1" parsed="|1Sam|6|10|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Sam.6.10">1 Sam. vi. 10</scripRef>.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p12">329. But that which helped me in this temptation 
was divers considerations, of which three in special here -I will name: The 
first was the consideration of these two scriptures, " Leave thy fatherless 
children, I will preserve them alive, and let thy widows trust in me." And 
again, " The Lord said, Verily it shall be well with thy remnant, verily I 
will cause the enemy to entreat thee well in the time of evil," <scripRef passage="Jer. xlix. 11" id="vi-p12.1" parsed="|Jer|49|11|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.49.11">Jer. xlix. 11</scripRef>; <scripRef passage="Jer 15:11" id="vi-p12.2" parsed="|Jer|15|11|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Jer.15.11">xv. 11</scripRef>.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p13">330. I had also this consideration, that if I 
should venture all for God, I engaged God to take care of my concernments: 
but if I forsook him in his ways, for fear of any trouble that should come 
to me or mine, then I should not only falsify my profession, but should count 
also that my concernments were not so sure if left at God's feet, while I 
stood to and for his name, as they would be if they were under my own care, 
though with the denial of the way of God. This was a smarting consideration, 
and as spurs into my flaw. That scripture also greatly helped it to fasten 
the more on me where Christ prays against Judas, that God would disappoint 
him in his selfish thoughts, which moved him to sell his master. Pray read it soberly, Psalm eix. 6-20.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p14">331. I had also another consideration, and that 
was the dread of the torments of hell, which I was sure they must partake 
of that for fear of the cross do shrink from their profession of Christ, his 
words and laws, before the sons of men; I thought also of the glory that he 
had prepared for those that in faith, and love, and patience, stood to his ways
 before them. These things, I say, have helped me, when the thoughts of the 
 misery that both myself and mine might, for the sake of my profession, be 
 exposed to, have lain pinching on my mind.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p15">332. When I have indeed conceited that I might be 
banished for my profession, then I have thought of that scripture, " They were 
stoned, they were sawn asunder, were tempted, were slain with the sword: they 
wandered about in sheepskins and goatskins; being destitute, afflicted, 
tormented; (of whom the world was not worthy)" <scripRef passage="Heb. xi. 37" id="vi-p15.1" parsed="|Heb|11|37|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.11.37">Heb. xi. 37</scripRef>, <scripRef passage="Heb 11:38" id="vi-p15.2" parsed="|Heb|11|38|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Heb.11.38">38</scripRef>; for all they 
thought they were too bad to dwell and abide amongst them. I have also thought 
of that saying, " The Holy Ghost witnesseth in every city," " that bonds and 
afflictions abide me," <scripRef passage="Acts xx. 23" id="vi-p15.3" parsed="|Acts|20|23|0|0" osisRef="Bible:Acts.20.23">Acts xx. 23</scripRef>. I have verily thought that my soul and it 
have sometimes reasoned about the sore and sad estate of a banished and exiled 
condition, how they were exposed to hunger, to cold, to perils, to nakedness, 
to enemies, and a thousand calamities; and at last, it may be, to die in a 
ditch like a poor and desolate sheep. But I thank God hitherto I have not been 
moved by these most delicate reasonings, but have rather, by them, more approved my heart to God.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p16">333. I will tell you a pretty business : I was once 
above all the rest in a very sad and low condition for many weeks; at which time 
also, I being but a young prisoner, and not acquainted with the laws, I had this 
lying much upon my spirits, that my imprisonment might end at the gallows for ought 
that I could tell. Now therefore Satan laid hard at me, to beat me out of heart, 
by suggesting thus unto me. But how if, when you come indeed to die, you should 
be in this condition; that is, as not to savour the things of God, nor to have 
any evidence upon your soul for a better state hereafter ? for indeed at this time 
all the things of God were hid from my soul.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p17">334. Wherefore when I at first began to think of this, 
it was a great trouble to me; for I thought with myself, that in the condition I 
now was in, I was not fit to die, neither indeed did I think I could if I should 
be called to it; besides I thought with myself, if I should make a scrambling shift 
to clamber up the ladder, yet I should, either with quaking or other symptoms of 
fainting, give occasion to the enemy to reproach the way of God and his people for 
their timorousness. This, therefore, lay with great trouble upon me, for methought 
I was ashamed to die with a pale face, and tottering knees, in such a case as this.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p18">335. Wherefore I prayed to God that he would comfort me, 
and give me strength to do and suffer what he should call me to; yet no comfort 
appeared, but all continued hid; I was also at this time so really possessed with 
the thought of death, that oft 1 was as if I was on the ladder with a rope about my 
neck; only this was some encouragement to me, I thought I might now have an opportunity 
to speak my last words unto a multitude, which I thought would come to see me die; 
and thought I, if it must be so, if God will but convert one soul by my last words, 
I shall not count my life thrown away nor lost.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p19">336. But yet all the things of God were kept out of my 
sight, and still the tempter followed me with, But whither must you go when you die? 
what will become of you ? where will you be found in another world? what evidence have 
you for heaven and glory, and an inheritance among them that are sanctified ? Thus was 
I tossed for many weeks, and knew not what to do; at last this consideration fell with 
weight upon me, that it was for the word and way of God that I was in this condition; 
wherefore I was engaged not to flinch an hair's breadth from it.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p20">337. I thought also that God might choose whether he would 
give me comfort now or at the hour of death; but I might not therefore choose whether 
I would hold my profession or no ; I was bound, but he was free; yea, 'twas my duty to 
stand to his word, whether he would ever look upon me or save me at the last: wherefore 
thought I, save the point being thus, I am for going on, and venturing my eternal state 
with Christ, whether I have comfort here or no. If God doth not come in, thought I, 
I will leap off the ladder even blindfold into eternity, sink or swim, come heaven, 
come hell, Lord Jesus, if thou wilt catch me, do; if not, I will venture for thy name.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p21">338. I was no sooner fixed with this resolution but this 
word dropped upon me, Doth Job serve God for nought? As if the accuser had said, 
Lord, Job is no upright man, he serves thee for bye-respects: hast thou not made an 
hedge about him.  But put forth now thine hand, and touch all that he hath, and 
he will curse thee to thy face. How now, thought I, is this the sign of an upright soul, 
to desire to serve God when all is taken from him? Is lie a godly man that will serve 
God for nothing rather than give out? Blessed be God; then I hope I have an upright 
heart, for I am resolved, God giving me strength, never to deny my profession, 
though I had nothing at all for my pains: and as I was thus considering, that 
scripture was set before me, <scripRef passage="Psalm xliv. 12-26" id="vi-p21.1" parsed="|Ps|44|12|44|26" osisRef="Bible:Ps.44.12-Ps.44.26">Psalm xliv. 12-26</scripRef>.
</p>

<p class="normal" id="vi-p22">339. Now was my heart full of comfort, for I hoped it 
was sincere: I would not have been without this trial for much; I am comforted every 
time I think of it, and I hope I shall bless God for ever for the teaching I have had 
by it. Many more of the dealings of God towards me I might relate, but these, out of 
the spoils won in battles, have I dedicated to maintain the house of God, <scripRef passage="1 Chron. xxvi. 27" id="vi-p22.1" parsed="|1Chr|26|27|0|0" osisRef="Bible:1Chr.26.27">1 Chron. xxvi. 27</scripRef>.
</p>


</div1>

<div1 title="Conclusion" progress="98.65%" prev="vi" next="viii" id="vii">
<h2 id="vii-p0.1">THE CONCLUSION </h2>
<p class="normal" id="vii-p1">1. Of all the temptations that ever I met with in my life, to question the being 
of God, and the truth of His gospel, is the worst, and the worst to be borne; when 
this temptation comes, it takes away my girdle from me, and removeth the foundations 
from under me. Oh, I have often thought of that word, ‘Have your loins girt about 
with truth’; and of that, ‘When the foundations are destroyed, what can the righteous 
do?’</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p2">2. Sometimes, when, after sin committed, I have looked for sore chastisement 
from the hand of God, the very next that I have had from Him hath been the discovery 
of His grace. Sometimes, when I have been comforted, I have called myself a fool 
for my so sinking under trouble. And then, again, when I have been cast down, I 
thought I was not wise to give such way to comfort. With such strength and weight 
have both these been upon me.</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p3">3. I have wondered much at this one thing, that though God doth visit my soul 
with never so blessed a discovery of Himself, yet I have found again, that such 
hours have attended me afterwards, that I have been in my spirit so filled with 
darkness, that I could not so much as once conceive what that God and that comfort 
was with which I have been refreshed.</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p4">4. I have sometimes seen more in a line of the Bible than I could well tell how 
to stand under, and yet at another time the whole Bible hath been to me as dry as 
a stick; or rather, my heart hath been so dead and dry unto it, that I could not 
conceive the least drachm of refreshment, though I have looked it all over.</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p5">5. Of all tears, they are the best that are made by the blood of Christ; and 
of all joy, that is the sweetest that is mixed with mourning over Christ. Oh! it 
is a goodly thing to be on our knees, with Christ in our arms, before God. I hope 
I know something of these things.</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p6">6. I find to this day seven abominations in my heart: (1) Inclinings to unbelief. 
(2) Suddenly to forget the love and mercy that Christ manifesteth. (3) A leaning 
to the works of the law. (4) Wanderings and coldness in prayer. (5) To forget to 
watch for that I pray for. (6) Apt to murmur because I have no more, and yet ready 
to abuse what I have. (7) I can do none of those things which God commands me, but 
my corruptions will thrust in themselves, ‘When I would do good, evil is present 
with me.’</p>

<p class="normal" id="vii-p7">7. These things I continually see and feel, and am afflicted and oppressed with; 
yet the wisdom of God doth order them for my good. (1) They make me abhor myself. 
(2) They keep me from trusting my heart. (3) They convince me of the insufficiency 
of all inherent righteousness. (4) They show me the necessity of fleeing to Jesus. 
(5) They press me to pray unto God. (6) They show me the need I have to watch and 
be sober. (7) And provoke me to look to God, through Christ, to help me, and carry 
me through this world. Amen.</p>
</div1>


<div1 title="Indexes" prev="vii" next="viii.i" id="viii">
<h1 id="viii-p0.1">Indexes</h1>

<div2 title="Index of Scripture References" prev="viii" next="toc" id="viii.i">
  <h2 id="viii.i-p0.1">Index of Scripture References</h2>
  <insertIndex type="scripRef" id="viii.i-p0.2" />



<div class="Index">
<p class="bbook">Genesis</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=25&amp;scrV=1#iv-p227.1">25:1-34</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=25&amp;scrV=34#iv-p227.2">25:34</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=27&amp;scrV=33#iv-p229.1">27:33</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=27&amp;scrV=36#iv-p228.1">27:36</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=30&amp;scrV=33#v-p19.1">30:33</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=33&amp;scrV=9#iv-p227.3">33:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gen&amp;scrCh=50&amp;scrV=15#iv-p218.1">50:15-17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Exodus</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Exod&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=42#iii-p5.1">12:42</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Exod&amp;scrCh=21&amp;scrV=14#iv-p179.1">21:14</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Leviticus</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Lev&amp;scrCh=25&amp;scrV=23#iv-p134.1">25:23</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Numbers</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=25#iii-p6.3">14:25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=36#iv-p178.1">14:36-37</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=23&amp;scrV=9#iv-p38.1">23:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Num&amp;scrCh=33&amp;scrV=1#iii-p4.1">33:1-2</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Deuteronomy</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Deut&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=10#iii-p3.3">4:10-11</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Deut&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=2#iii-p4.2">8:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Deut&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=1#iv-p71.1">14:1-29</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Deut&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=27#iv-p111.1">22:27</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Joshua</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Josh&amp;scrCh=20&amp;scrV=3#iv-p211.1">20:3-4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Josh&amp;scrCh=20&amp;scrV=4#iv-p247.1">20:4</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Judges</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Judg&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=1#iv-p245.1">6:1-40</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Judg&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=1#iv-p245.2">7:1-25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Judg&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=5#iii-p3.1">14:5-9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Judg&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=29#v-p31.1">16:29-30</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Samuel</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Sam&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=10#vi-p11.1">6:10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Sam&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=4#iv-p184.2">16:4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Sam&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=14#iv-p102.1">16:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Sam&amp;scrCh=17&amp;scrV=36#iii-p5.3">17:36-37</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Kings</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Kgs&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=28#iv-p179.2">2:28</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Kgs&amp;scrCh=20&amp;scrV=31#iv-p253.2">20:31</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Chronicles</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Chr&amp;scrCh=26&amp;scrV=27#vi-p22.1">26:27</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Esther</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Esth&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=16#iv-p253.1">4:16</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Job</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Job&amp;scrCh=21&amp;scrV=14#iv-p10.1">21:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Job&amp;scrCh=29&amp;scrV=2#iv-p150.1">29:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Job&amp;scrCh=29&amp;scrV=13#v-p10.1">29:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Job&amp;scrCh=42&amp;scrV=10#iv-p254.1">42:10</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Psalms</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=6#iv-p74.1">16:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=13#iv-p152.1">19:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=19&amp;scrV=13#iv-p240.1">19:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=42&amp;scrV=6#iii-p5.2">42:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=44&amp;scrV=12#vi-p21.1">44:12-26</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=68&amp;scrV=18#iv-p167.1">68:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=77&amp;scrV=5#iii-p8.1">77:5-12</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=77&amp;scrV=7#iv-p203.1">77:7-9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=78&amp;scrV=3#iii-p3.4">78:3-5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=106&amp;scrV=11#iii-p6.4">106:11-13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=107&amp;scrV=16#iv-p81.1">107:16</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=127&amp;scrV=3#v-p26.2">127:3-5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=130&amp;scrV=3#iv-p194.1">130:3-4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ps&amp;scrCh=150&amp;scrV=1#iv-p237.1">150:1-2</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Proverbs</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Prov&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=30#v-p22.2">11:30</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Prov&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=30#v-p26.1">11:30</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Prov&amp;scrCh=30&amp;scrV=15#iv-p42.1">30:15</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Ecclesiastes</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eccl&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=15#iv-p19.1">10:15</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Song of Solomon</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Song&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=0#iv-p89.1">4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Song&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=8#iii-p1.1">4:8</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Isaiah</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=6#iv-p122.1">9:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=26&amp;scrV=19#iv-p236.1">26:19</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=38&amp;scrV=19#iii-p3.2">38:19</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=44&amp;scrV=22#iv-p174.2">44:22</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Isa&amp;scrCh=45&amp;scrV=5#iv-p81.2">45:5</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Jeremiah</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=25#iv-p25.1">2:25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=14#iv-p180.1">11:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=11#vi-p12.2">15:11</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=18&amp;scrV=12#iv-p25.2">18:12</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=31&amp;scrV=3#iv-p191.1">31:3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jer&amp;scrCh=49&amp;scrV=11#vi-p12.1">49:11</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Ezekiel</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Ezek&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=63#iv-p195.1">16:63</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Daniel</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Dan&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=19#iv-p70.1">5:19</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Dan&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=14#iv-p199.1">10:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Dan&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=3#v-p22.3">12:3</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Hosea</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Hos&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=2#iv-p236.2">6:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Hos&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=1#iv-p198.1">9:1</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Joel</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Joel&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=21#iv-p76.1">3:21</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Matthew</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=9#iv-p107.1">4:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=11#v-p45.1">5:11</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=14#iv-p55.2">7:14</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=32#iv-p222.2">12:32</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=21#iv-p253.3">15:21-28</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=28#iv-p202.1">15:28</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Matt&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=17#iv-p118.1">16:17-17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Mark</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=13#iv-p74.2">3:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=29#iv-p148.1">3:29</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=2#iv-p187.1">5:2-5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=38#iv-p222.3">8:38</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=5#iv-p215.2">9:5-7</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Mark&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=20#iv-p80.2">9:20</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Luke</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=42#iv-p80.1">9:42</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=5#iv-p253.4">11:5-8</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=13&amp;scrV=25#iv-p229.2">13:25-27</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=22#iv-p68.1">14:22-23</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=19#iv-p256.1">22:19</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=31#iv-p93.1">22:31</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Luke&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=32#iv-p146.1">22:32</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">John</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=37#iv-p216.1">6:37</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=37#iv-p251.1">6:37</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=35#iv-p196.1">10:35</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=1#vi-p5.1">14:1-4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=6#iv-p55.1">14:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=14&amp;scrV=19#iv-p113.3">14:19</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=33#vi-p5.2">16:33</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=John&amp;scrCh=20&amp;scrV=17#iv-p121.1">20:17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Acts</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=9#iv-p121.2">1:9-10</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=18#iv-p165.1">1:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=12#iv-p183.1">4:12</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=56#iv-p121.3">7:56</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=4#v-p6.1">8:4</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=16#iv-p113.4">10:16</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=42#iv-p121.4">10:42</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=9#iv-p91.1">12:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=18&amp;scrV=24#v-p6.2">18:24-25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=20&amp;scrV=23#vi-p15.3">20:23</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=22&amp;scrV=1#iii-p6.1">22:1-30</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Acts&amp;scrCh=24&amp;scrV=1#iii-p6.2">24:1-27</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Romans</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=24#iv-p260.1">3:24</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=9#iv-p186.1">6:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=0#iv-p92.1">8</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=17#iv-p262.3">8:17</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=31#iv-p113.2">8:31</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=38#iv-p111.2">8:38</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=16#iv-p58.1">9:16</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=6#v-p6.4">12:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=18#v-p21.1">15:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rom&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=20#v-p25.1">15:20</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Corinthians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=30#iv-p232.1">1:30</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=2#v-p11.2">9:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=8#iv-p47.1">12:8-9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=13&amp;scrV=1#v-p33.1">13:1-2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=15&amp;scrV=55#iv-p263.1">15:55</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Cor&amp;scrCh=16&amp;scrV=15#v-p5.1">16:15-16</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">2 Corinthians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=5#vi-p6.1">1:5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=9#vi-p8.1">1:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=2#v-p11.1">2:2</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=8#iv-p215.1">3:8-12</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=18#vi-p9.1">4:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=21#iv-p113.1">5:21</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Cor&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=7#v-p32.1">12:7-9</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Galatians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Gal&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=11#v-p21.2">1:11-12</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Ephesians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=2#iv-p4.1">2:2-3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=6#iv-p236.3">2:6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Eph&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=30#iv-p235.1">5:30</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Colossians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Col&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=20#iv-p115.1">1:20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Col&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=3#vi-p5.3">3:3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Col&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=4#vi-p5.4">3:4</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Thessalonians</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Thess&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=19#v-p22.4">2:19-20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Thess&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=20#iii-p2.1">2:20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Thess&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=17#iv-p121.8">4:17-18</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">2 Timothy</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Tim&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=9#iv-p262.2">1:9</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Tim&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=26#iv-p4.2">2:26</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Titus</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Titus&amp;scrCh=3&amp;scrV=5#iv-p262.1">3:5</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Hebrews</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=14#iv-p116.1">2:14-15</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=16#iv-p241.1">4:16</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=1#iv-p224.1">6:1-3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=1#iv-p210.1">6:1-20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=4#iv-p197.1">6:4-6</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=24#iv-p121.5">7:24</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=7&amp;scrV=25#iv-p204.2">7:25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=8&amp;scrV=3#iv-p121.6">8:3</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=9&amp;scrV=22#iv-p86.1">9:22</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=26#iv-p222.1">10:26</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=26#iv-p197.2">10:26-27</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=28#iv-p226.1">10:28</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=10&amp;scrV=31#iv-p174.1">10:31</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=37#vi-p15.1">11:37</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=11&amp;scrV=38#vi-p15.2">11:38</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=16#iv-p141.1">12:16-17</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=16#iv-p197.3">12:16-17</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=22#iv-p265.1">12:22-24</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=22#iv-p266.1">12:22-24</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=22#vi-p5.5">12:22-24</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=12&amp;scrV=25#iv-p175.1">12:25</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=13&amp;scrV=5#iv-p217.1">13:5</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Heb&amp;scrCh=13&amp;scrV=8#iv-p231.1">13:8</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">James</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jas&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=13#iv-p214.1">2:13</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Jas&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=20#v-p22.1">5:20</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 Peter</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Pet&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=8#vi-p5.6">1:8</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Pet&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=19#iv-p120.1">1:19-20</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1Pet&amp;scrCh=4&amp;scrV=10#v-p6.3">4:10</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">2 Peter</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=2Pet&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=21#iv-p210.2">2:21</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">1 John</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1John&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=7#iv-p143.1">1:7</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1John&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=1#iv-p118.2">5:1</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1John&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=16#iv-p189.1">5:16-17</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=1John&amp;scrCh=5&amp;scrV=18#iv-p152.2">5:18</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Revelation</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rev&amp;scrCh=1&amp;scrV=18#iv-p121.7">1:18</a>  
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Rev&amp;scrCh=6&amp;scrV=1#iv-p184.1">6:1-17</a> </p>
<p class="bbook">Sirach</p>
 <p class="bref">
 <a class="TOC" href="?scrBook=Sir&amp;scrCh=2&amp;scrV=10#iv-p65.1">2:10</a> </p>
</div>




</div2>
</div1>




</ThML.body>
</ThML>
